<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Apps | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/apps/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Explore Your Creativity Mac App Store Sale]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/17/explore-your-creativity/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-17T22:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/17/explore-your-creativity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/07/explore-your-creativity.png" title="Explore Your Creativity" ></p>

<p>The Mac App Store has a great promotion going on right now called “Explore Your Creativity.” Some really powerful apps are 50% off. A few of my favorites:<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ulysses-iii/id623795237?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Ulysses III</a> – $21.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/slugline/id553754186?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Slugline</a> – $19.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/highland/id499329572?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Highland</a> – $14.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pixelmator/id407963104?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Pixelmator</a> – $15.99</li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/scrivener/id418889511?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Scrivener</a> – $22.99</li>
</ul>

<p>I use <a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com">Ulysses III</a> almost every day. Check out <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/04/09/ulysses-iii-review/">my review</a> for more on how I use it; it’s only gotten better since. Before Ulysses I was a huge <a href="http://www.literatureandlatte.com/scrivener.php">Scrivener</a> user. I still go back to it from time to time, especially when I have to organize an inordinate amount of data, like planning what I’m <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2012/02/16/scrivener-festival-planning/">going to see at a film festival</a>.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><a href="http://slugline.co">Slugline</a> and <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/highland/">Highland</a> are both excellent <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain</a> writing and previewing apps. If you write screenplays in Fountain, buy both. You won’t be sorry. And if you still think you need it in your arsenal, even <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/final-draft-9/id454277974?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Final Draft 9 is on sale for $125</a>.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.pixelmator.com">Pixelmator</a> is regularly a steal, but $16 is downright criminal for such a powerful photo editing app.</p>

<p>So if price has been the barrier to getting any of these apps, you’re out of excuses. Sale ends July 24.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>This list (and only this list) contains Mac App Store affiliate links and current promotional sale prices. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>iA’s Writer Pro is also on sale, but I left it off my list <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/12/23/no-thanks-ia/">because, you know</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instapaper Highlighting]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/instapaper-adds-highlighting/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T22:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/instapaper-adds-highlighting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/05/instapaper-highlight.png" title="Instapaper Highlighting in Action" ></p>

<p>You would have no way of knowing this, but I’ve been trying to write more about movies around here. That means <em>reading</em> more about movies too. Which in turn means my usual screwing around with apps and workflows and things…</p>

<p>I’ve been trying to write a piece that involves pulling together the disparate strands of a number of things other folks have written in the past little while. No foolin’: earlier this week I spent an hour or two trying to find a quick and easy way to organize highlights from my Instapaper account. I cobbled together a number of tools and gave up, assuming it was hopeless.</p>

<p>Then today <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/instapaper/id288545208?mt=8&amp;at=11l5Fb">Instapaper</a> pushed out a <a href="http://blog.instapaper.com/post/85125160146"><em>huge</em> update</a> to their apps and web backend, including integrating highlighting. What luck!</p>

<p>Highlights do just what they say on the tin and then some. Select text in an article, click highlight, and voila, the text turns into a different color. Highlights also get their own section in Instapaper, allowing you to quickly see all the highlighted text across folders in one view. Plus you can set Instapaper to automatically trigger an action when you highlight text. More on that in a moment.</p>

<p>Before I go any further I should mention a point that has already kicked up some dust in the Instapaper Blog comments. In order to get unlimited highlights across Instapaper, you need to have a subscription. Otherwise, you get 5 free highlights per month.</p>

<p>Instapaper subscriptions have long been a confusing point of contention for some users who think an app that costs money shouldn’t have additional costs. According to <a href="https://www.instapaper.com/faq">Instapaper’s FAQ</a>, for $1 a month (really $3 every 3 months) you get:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li>Full-text search</li>
    <li>Unlimited highlighting</li>
    <li>Third-party API access</li>
    <li>Better Kindle functionality</li>
    <li>Ads removed from website</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>That third-party API access is key for me since I <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/31/readkit-2-and-rediscovering-instapaper/">love using ReadKit</a> to organize articles. Honestly, now with highlighting, an Instapaper subscription is a steal at twice the price. But it’s an important point: without a subscription you’ll want to use highlighting sparingly.</p>

<p>Back to highlighting tricks.</p>

<h3 id="highlights-to-evernote">Highlights to Evernote</h3>

<p>Any sharing account you have set up in Instapaper (like <a href="https://twitter.com">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.evernote.com/referral/Registration.action?uid=236765&amp;sig=c3f3f41ea30c00be54920d4456371862">Evernote</a> or <a href="https://pinboard.in/">Pinboard</a>) can automatically share out a highlight in the background. So if you’ve set up Evernote to “Post Highlights” every time you highlight text, a new note will be created in your default notebook with the article title as the note title and the highlighted text and url as the note content.</p>

<p>Here’s a tip: save a search in Evernote for <code>author:no-reply@instapaper.com</code>. This will filter out only notes emailed to Evernote from Instapaper, which in my case will only be highlights.</p>

<h3 id="highlights-to-pinboard">Highlights to Pinboard</h3>

<p>Right now I have everything I save to Instapaper going to Pinboard as a sort of firehose backup of all my links. Now that highlighting adds the ability to post to Pinboard, with the highlighted text going into the description field, I’m thinking of changing that setup. This way only articles I have enough of an interest in to highlight some text will make their way to Pinboard. Even better: highlighting text is much, much faster than using Instapaper’s sharing panel to send articles to Pinboard.</p>

<p>I’ve long used Instapaper and Pinboard alongside one another, but that relationship has become fraught over time. Ideally Instapaper is my “hot” storage while Pinboard is my “cold,” or deep, storage. However, more or less the Instapaper links clutter up Pinboard. Highlighting with background sharing, I hope, should help the bring out the best of both services. I’ll give it a go and report back.</p>

<h3 id="other-goodies">Other Goodies</h3>

<p>I also really like that the article view includes a small, conspicuous flag letting you know if an article has highlights and how many it has. In daily use this may not seem important, but when I’m doing deep research on a topic in folders, this could be a huge boon.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/05/instapaper-highlight-flag.png" title="Instapaper Highlighting Flag" ></p>

<p>All this gushing about highlighting and I haven’t even mentioned the major redesign of the web app (pictured in screenshots above) with drag and drop organization, plus subtle but important tweaks to the iOS apps. And they’ve even got a brand new logo from Kris Sowersby, the typographer behing my <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/dancing-couriers/">preferred monospaced</a> font, <a href="https://klim.co.nz/blog/tag/fonts-in-use/pitch/">Pitch</a>.</p>

<p>Though the rest of these features play second fiddle to highlighting today, I’m interested to see how they change the way I think about Instapaper. For so long it has been an app for <em>reading</em> content. Today’s updates prove that it’s no slouch when it comes to <em>organizing</em> content. Mostly, though, I’m excited to see how ambitious all of these updates are. It’s nice to know there are people working, iterating and making a service and app you love better.</p>

<p>Anyway, I’ve got to get back to marking up all of these articles in Instapaper so I can get back to writing about movies.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekend Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/11/weekend-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T22:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/11/weekend-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John August and the team at Quote-Unquote apps have done it again. <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/weekendread/">Weekend Read</a> reformats screenplays and other text files to fit comfortably on an iPhone screen. PDFs, Fountain, Markdown, Final Draft. Dark mode, four fonts and text resizing. And a brilliant file browser to boot. (Oh and character highlighting because why stop there?)</p>

<p>Free for iPhone. $9.99 In-App Purchase to unlock unlimited library storage. <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/id502725173">Go get it</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Support Information Architects UPDATED]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/23/no-thanks-ia/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-23T15:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/23/no-thanks-ia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week Information Architects (iA) released Writer Pro, a follow-up to the company’s popular text editor, iA Writer. By far, their most heavily touted new feature is Syntax Control. Oliver Reichenstein, iA’s director, promised in <a href="http://ia.net/blog/writer-pro/">a blog post</a> to vigorously protect this new feature:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Syntax Control is a solid innovation, one we’ve been working on for more than four years. As with every serious design, once you have seen how it works, you can figure out cheap ways to copy it. We’ve trademarked and obtained patent pending for Syntax Control. If you want it in your text editor, you can get a license from us. It’s going to be a fair deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve read this paragraph probably a dozen times now and I can think of no better word to describe it than “<a href="http://gawker.com/on-smarm-1476594977">smarmy</a>.” It’s not just the bravado in Reichenstein’s insistence that Syntax Control is such a solid innovation, it’s the pre-emptive accusation that any similar feature in an app would be “cheap.” This isn’t just an insult, it’s a threat.</p>

<p>When I hand my money over to a developer, I want to at least <em>feel</em> like I’m the reason their product exists, that it otherwise wouldn’t but for my interest, support and cash. Goading other developers into forking over licensing fees undercuts that feeling for me. While the full patent application isn’t available yet, Reichenstein <a href="https://twitter.com/reichenstein/status/414932666387927040">tweeted</a> an image that has “Method of editing text in a text editor” listed as the “Title of Invention.” That sounds precisely like the sort of broad software patent that discourages innovation. </p>

<p>But then there’s Syntax Control itself. I can’t figure out what, exactly, the innovation <em>is</em>. Here’s how iA describes Syntax Control on their <a href="http://writer.pro">product page</a>: </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Syntax Control dims everything but the chosen syntax, helping you focus, and control your writing style.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On the Writer Pro <a href="http://support.iawriter.com/help/discussions/writer-pro-for-mac-problems/6-do-writing-modes-only-change-the-cursor-color-and-font#comment_30701362">support forums</a>, Oli Studholme speaks for iA in responding to early adopters unhappy with the app (emphasis not mine):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>While we understand Writer Pro is not for everyone, I’m very surprised to hear you say it does “nothing new”. Regardless of your thoughts on Workflow, <em>Syntax Control is not available in any other program, period.</em></p>
</blockquote>

<p>But what about Agile Tortoise’s <a href="http://agiletortoise.com/phraseology/">Phraseology</a>? That two year-old app has a feature called “Inspect” that offers comprehensive statistics about your document like word count and readability. There is also a parts of speech analysis.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/12/phraseology-inspect.jpg" title="Phraseology’s Inspect View" ></p>

<p>Had Agile Tortoise threatened action against anyone who would try to copy Phraseology’s Inspect view, would we even <em>have</em> Writer Pro’s Syntax Control?</p>

<p>All of this leads me to the conclusion that I should stop supporting Information Architects and I suggest you do the same. I bought iA Writer for the Mac and iOS long ago, but from here on out, unless Reichenstein and company do an about face, I won’t be giving them a dime. If you like the typefaces they include with their apps, go buy them from <a href="http://www.boldmonday.com/en/nitti/">Bold Monday</a> and <a href="https://klim.co.nz/retail-fonts/tiempos-text/">Klim Type Foundry</a>. If you need a text editor there are plenty of others available from less threatening developers. Here are some ideas:<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/phraseology/id484666152?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Phraseology</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/daedalus-touch-text-editor/id406964546?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Daedalus Touch</a>
    <ul>
      <li>Hint: you can <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/12/19/custom-fonts-in-daedalus/">load custom fonts</a>, including Nitti Light and Tiempos Text into Daedalus.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/byword/id482063361?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Byword</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/editorial/id673907758?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Editorial</a></li>
</ul>

<p>There is no need to support a smarmy, litigious operation like Information Architects. There is so much innovation coming out of other developers. Now get writing.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p><strong>Further reading:</strong> Gabe Weatherhead <a href="http://www.macdrifter.com/2013/12/writer-pro-developers-double-down-on-innovations-in-being-douchebags.html">nails it</a>, Ben Brooks <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2013/12/isue/">offers some insight</a>, The Soulmen whip up <a href="https://github.com/macguru/SyntaxCheck">a demo</a> showing how simple it is to recreate Syntax Control and Verge forum poster “Weswanders” does the hard work of <a href="http://theverge.com/2013/12/21/5234580/patent-pending-ias-militant-stance-on-syntax-control">questioning iA’s claims</a> that The Verge sidestepped <a href="http://theverge.com/2013/12/18/5222948/ia-writer-pro">in this piece</a>.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATED December 26, 2013:</strong> This evening, after a <a href="http://storify.com/poritsky/discussion-from-twitterrific-5">public conversation</a> with David Heinemeier Hansson, iA’s official Twitter account (managed by Oliver Reichenstein) tweeted the following:</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>We will drop our patents pending. Thank you <a href="https://twitter.com/dhh">@dhh</a> for clearing our minds.</p>&mdash; iA Inc. (@iA) <a href="https://twitter.com/iA/statuses/416393539182796800">December 27, 2013</a></blockquote>

<p>Sounds good to me. I look forward to reading Reichenstein’s side of this.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Affiliate links. I thank you in advance. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">

      <p>A brief postscript to all of this because I don’t want to write a separate piece.</p>

      <p>I wish both the press beta and the negative review were as prevalent in the software world as they are in the film world. Most movies, except for the real stinkers, are shown to the press ahead of time with the full knowledge that many of them won’t like what they see. And they’re going to <em>tell</em> people so.</p>

      <p>The iA forums and iTunes reviews are lousy with people crying foul because Writer Pro wasn’t what they were expecting. I wonder if a launch day <a href="http://macstories.net">Macstories</a> longread on the specifics of what the app can and can’t do wouldn’t have changed Writer Pro’s early sales. Come to think of it, I don’t think iA even offered a press beta.</p>

      <p>Remember: it’s the stinkers that don’t screen early for the critics.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Load Custom Fonts on iOS in Daedalus Touch]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/19/custom-fonts-in-daedalus/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-19T16:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/19/custom-fonts-in-daedalus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The Soulmen, developers of <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/04/09/ulysses-iii-review/">Ulysses III</a> and <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2011/06/02/daedalus-touch-brings-beautiful-text-editing-to-the-ipad/">Daedalus Touch</a>, never fail to impress. They just updated Daedalus, the universal iOS text editor, to 1.7 and brought a slew of goodies to it. The headlining features:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Daedalus Touch is now free with In-App Purchase
    <ul>
      <li>Users who paid for the app in the past will get all features unlocked on download</li>
      <li>$2.99 gets you all of the features or you can piecemeal only what you need for $0.99 apiece</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>The app requires iOS 7 and has been redesigned for the current OS as well</li>
  <li>Updated to the latest <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/textexpander/id326180690?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">TextExpander</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> SDK</li>
  <li>New support for <a href="http://x-callback-url.com">x-callback-url</a></li>
  <li>The ability to customize fonts</li>
</ul>

<p>I could go on and on about this app, but I want to just focus on the custom font selections as this is something that wasn’t immediately clear to me and seems revolutionary on iOS.</p>

<p>Daedalus Touch has always had three font choices: Classic, Modern and Mono. In previous iterations of the app The Soulmen bundled custom fonts with the app. Each sheet (or document) features a title line in a large, headline-style typeface above the body text.</p>

<p>In 1.7 Daedalus retains the names of the old themes but now relies solely on built-in iOS fonts: Cochin, Helvetica Neue and Menlo. Below the font options there is a toggle labeled “Custom.” Flip it and you now have the option of setting both the title and the body text to any iOS system font.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/12/daedalus-settings.png" title="Daedalus Touch Settings" ></p>

<p>Now, this is cool, but it’s not revolutionary for an iOS text app to allow you access to the system font library. While I was enjoying myself flipping through different theme options, I noticed a tweet from the Daedalus twitter account.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet" lang="en"><p>For those of you fiddling with the fonts feature: You can have *any* font file (even .zips) “Open In Daedalus”. <a href="https://twitter.com/search?q=%23daedalusapp&amp;src=hash">#daedalusapp</a></p>&mdash; Daedalus Touch (@daedalusapp) <a href="https://twitter.com/daedalusapp/statuses/413465364371374080">December 19, 2013</a></blockquote>

<p>Immediately I dropped a font into my Dropbox folder on my Mac and loaded Dropbox on my iPhone. I downloaded the font and used Dropbox’s share button to get to the “Open in…” dialog. Tap Daedalus and it will open up. At first it will be unclear that anything happened. Go back into the custom fonts selection menu and there, at the top of the list, will be your font.</p>

<p>Even better, as promised you can zip up all the weights of a font and open it in Daedalus. All of the weights will be available and organized.</p>

<p>iOS ships with a wide array of fonts that should keep most users happy, but it’s extremely nice to be able to load any font I want to write with. I loaded up my preferred monospaced fonts (<a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/dancing-couriers/">and favorite of the dancing Couriers</a>), <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/courierprime/">Courier Prime</a> and <a href="https://klim.co.nz/blog/pitch-design-information/">Pitch</a>, both of which look gorgeous in Daedalus.</p>

<p>Many of the writing apps I love ship with custom fonts, some of which I love and wouldn’t otherwise be able to afford.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> However, the ability to load your own fonts is a huge win from a consumer perspective. So many apps differentiate themselves on an array of features; I’d rather not have to choose app A solely because it has a font that app B doesn’t.</p>

<p>One final thought on the matter. Plain text editing is one thing, but imagine being able to load custom fonts in a layout app like <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/keynote/id361285480?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Keynote</a> or <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/pages/id361309726?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Pages</a> or <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/omnigraffle/id363225984?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">OmniGraffle</a>. I really hope The Soulmen share this code and make iOS an even more customizable landscape.</p>

<p><em><a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/daedalus-touch-text-editor/id406964546?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Daedalus Touch</a> is free with In-App Purchase in the App Store. It’s a great syncing companion to <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ulysses-iii/id623795237?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Ulysses III</a>, which is $44.99 in the Mac App Store.</em></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>This is the first of a few affiliate links in this piece. If you purchase apps with these links you support the candler blog. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>See the new <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/writer-pro-note-write-edit/id775737172?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Writer Pro’s</a> use of <a href="http://www.boldmonday.com/en/nitti">Nitti</a> and <a href="https://www.klim.co.nz/blog/tiempos-design-information/">Tiempos</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
