<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Announcement | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/announcement/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Introducing Hindsight: A Weekly Collection of Last Year's Writing]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/28/introducing-hindsight/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T18:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/28/introducing-hindsight</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/08/hindsight.png" title="Hindsight" ></p>

<p>Last week, Shawn Blanc published an <a href="http://shawnblanc.net/2013/08/feed-reading-today-and-tomorrow/">excellent piece</a> on the state of RSS feed reading. Here’s the part that stuck with me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There is <em>so much</em> great stuff being written and published every day. We’re subscribing to some of the sites and writers who are producing it, and we’re trying to read what we can, but a lot of great things to read fall through the cracks every day. And a lot of dumb stuff gets much more attention than it deserves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I save interesting things I come across to <a href="http://www.instapaper.com/">Instapaper</a> and <a href="https://pinboard.in/">Pinboard</a> every day. As I <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/05/31/readkit-2-and-rediscovering-instapaper/">explained back in May</a>, sometimes I read the articles I cull, but more often they linger in my accounts until they’re forgotten, tamped down by another layer of links I might one day get to. And yes, I as guilty as anyone of getting caught up in nonsense that doesn’t deserve my attention at all.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Shawn’s piece got me thinking about what I could do to prevent great content from getting lost over time. And then it hit me: just read it.</p>

<p>Today I’m introducing Hindsight, a weekly collection of older content you may have missed from around the Web. Hindsight will be published once a week and contain links to longer stories that are one year old. Some ground rules:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Linked articles should have been published within the same numbered week of the previous year.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></li>
  <li>At least one story a week should be ten years old or older.</li>
  <li>Stories should be at least one thousand words long.</li>
  <li>Stories should be fairly <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Evergreen_(journalism)">evergreen</a>.</li>
</ul>

<p>These rules will be broken, probably weekly, but I think they provide a nice starting point. Hindsight is about slowing down the news cycle. It’s about setting current events aside and catching up on great writing.</p>

<p>Hindsight will appear like any other post here on <em>the candler blog</em>. I’ve also set up an <a href="http://feedpress.me/hindsight" title="Hindsight Feed">RSS feed just for Hindsight</a>.</p>

<p>So fire up your read later app of choice and grab your favorite beverage; the <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/08/28/hindsight-1/" title="Hindsight 1">first Hindsight is up</a>. Happy reading.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>This week is a great example: I’ve been privy to far too many conversations about Miley Cyrus. Meanwhile: the NSA is spying on the UN and we’re on the brink of entering Syria, but OMG that foam finger.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Numbered weeks are based on a Sunday through Saturday calendar. For example: since the week of August 25th is the 35th week of 2013, stories linked this week will have been published between August 26th and September 1st 2012, the 35th week of 2012.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Update on Feeds]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/13/feed-updates/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-13T22:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/13/feed-updates</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, after months (years, really) of deliberation, I turned off the <a href="https://feedburner.google.com">FeedBurner</a> feed for <em>the candler blog</em> and redirected it to <a href="https://feedpress.it">FeedPress</a>. If you’re a subscriber to the candler blog, you shouldn’t notice any difference, but if you’re experiencing any issues you can <a href="http://feedpress.me/candlerblog">resubscribe with this link</a>.</p>

<p>FeedPress offers a few advantages over FeedBurner, but there are two main reasons I’ve been wanting to make the switch:</p>

<ol>
  <li>FeedBurner is <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abandonware">abandonware</a>. It’s no longer a question of if Google will kill it, but when.</li>
  <li>Google creeps me out. The more data I can take off of their servers the better. (I’ve got a long way to go still, but every little bit counts.)</li>
</ol>

<p>And so I took the plunge yesterday. FeedPress’s best feature is that, unlike FeedBurner, it isn’t intended as a replacement for your RSS feed, but rather as a sort of proxy that enhances a given feed. If I understand correctly (and I probably don’t) the feed I host here on my server redirects to FeedPress, which in turn redirects <em>back</em> to my original feed. In other words: my feed is my feed. Always.</p>

<p>In that same vein, FeedPress recently introduced <a href="https://www.dropbox.com">Dropbox</a> integration. Once a day, a .txt document with the day’s subscription numbers gets dropped into a folder in my Dropbox account. I love that in order to check the numbers, I don’t even need to log into FeedPress; they just plop a report onto my hard drive.</p>

<p>If RSS isn’t your thing, then you can subscribe to the <a href="https://twitter.com/thecandlerblog">Twitter</a> and <a href="https://alpha.app.net/thecandlerblog">App.net</a> accounts of <em>the candler blog</em>. These feeds will only provide links and headlines. Posts are sent to Twitter via <a href="https://ifttt.com">IFTTT</a> and to App.net via <a href="https://adn-pourover.appspot.com">PourOver</a>. Both of those accounts use links from a custom RSS feed generated through <a href="http://pipes.yahoo.com">Yahoo! Pipes</a> which I <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/08/31/static-link-posts-to-tweets/">wrote about</a> in detail last year, though I had to tweak a few settings after switching to FeedPress.</p>

<p>I welcome any <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/contact/">feedback</a> about these feeds. Here they are once more:</p>

<ul>
  <li>RSS: <a href="http://feedpress.me/candlerblog">http://feedpress.me/candlerblog</a></li>
  <li>Twitter: <a href="https://twitter.com/thecandlerblog">@thecandlerblog</a></li>
  <li>App.net: <a href="https://alpha.app.net/thecandlerblog">@thecandlerblog</a></li>
</ul>

<p>As ever, thanks for reading.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Don't Call it a Redesign]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/09/dont-call-it-a-redesign/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-09T15:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/09/dont-call-it-a-redesign</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re a regular reader, <em>the candler blog</em> may look a bit different to you today. Here’s (roughly)<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> what it looked like yesterday:</p>

<p><img src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0b0O0h2i1G2R13393d1d/Screen%20Shot%202012-09-05%20at%205.08.13%20PM.JPG" width="2012"></p>

<p>The type is now bigger, columns are better aligned, footnotes look more like footnotes and a whole bunch of little visual mistakes have been corrected.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> I wouldn’t say I redesigned the site per se. Well, maybe I would.</p>

<p>For a few months I’ve been toying with the site’s design privately. I’ve broken it down and built it from the ground up a few times, but ultimately I couldn’t find a design that I wanted to commit the energy to building out. In the end I retained the design I’ve had here <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/09/05/off-schedule-redesign/">since last September</a>, which is a heavily modified version of the <a href="http://octopress.org">stock Octopress theme</a>.</p>

<p>More changes will be rolling out over time, possibly some big ones. I feel more at home in this design of the site, so I’ll likely be posting more (though hopefully not <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/01/what-i-have-been-reading-lately/">reading less</a>) than I have been. As ever, thanks for reading.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>A few small changes have rolled out since that screenshot was taken a year ago.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>There are still plenty of design elements I know need fixing. If you spot something that looks out of place, please <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/contact/">drop me a line</a>.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Thank You, Readers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/23/thanks/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-23T12:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/23/thanks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’m traveling for Thanksgiving this week and haven’t had much of a chance to write. But I should post <em>something</em>, right?</p>

<p>I just wanted to take a moment to thank you, my readers. 2012 has been a landmark year for <em>the candler blog</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and I probably wouldn’t keep this project going if people didn’t come by to read it every once in a while.</p>

<p>So thank you. Have a great holiday and be safe on your travels.</p>

<p>Okay, enough of that. Back to tech and film and nonsense next week. (Or sooner, who knows?)</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That’s a topic I’ll swing back around to, I’m sure, as the year winds down and I get sentimental.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[An Off-Schedule Redesign]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/09/05/off-schedule-redesign/"/>
    <updated>2012-09-05T12:37:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/09/05/off-schedule-redesign</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Every year since I started the candler blog I make the foolhardy decision to redesign the site, almost <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/10/more-than-a-new-design/">like clockwork around New Years</a>. This year I even went so far as to switch from Wordpress to Octopress. Well, I don’t know why but I recently felt the need to change things up around here a bit.</p>

<p>Maybe I felt that <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/07/06/goodbye-new-york/">moving halfway across the country</a> wasn’t enough of a change. Maybe I was jealous that Gabe over at Macdrifter was having <a href="http://www.macdrifter.com/2012/08/moving-to-pelican-design-planning.html">all the static redesigning fun</a>. I don’t know. But I do know that Monday’s post, “<a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/09/03/practice/">Practice Makes Better</a>,” was the result of me trying to pump myself up to finally take on the challenge of moving things around here. For the longest time I figured that, if the site is working as-is, why mess with it? Because I can, because I want to and because, if and when I break it, I can always fix it.</p>

<p>So, welcome to the new candler blog. And if this is your first time joining, please take a look at what it looked like this morning:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2012/09/old-design.jpg" title="Old Candler Design" ></p>

<p>I know there are parts of the site that may look off for now. If you run into any problems or have suggestions, please don’t hesitate to let me know in the comments or <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/contact">in an email</a>.</p>

<p>And please enjoy the site. Plenty more to come.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
