<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Media | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/media/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[BuzzFeed's Native Advertising Is Nothing But A Confidence Game]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/05/spread-it-like-nutella/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-05T19:18:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/05/spread-it-like-nutella</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://copyranter.blogspot.com/2014/06/buzzfeeds-native-advertising-is-nothing.html">Copyranter</a>, earning his title:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>BuzzFeed’s native advertising is really—ultimately—terrible for brands. But it’s great for BuzzFeed. And this giddy circle jerk underway between media sites desperate for revenue and misguided advertisers desperate to feel instant gratification, continues.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Classic.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alec Baldwin on (Leaving) Public Life]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/24/public-life/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-24T17:38:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/24/public-life</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Alec Baldwin <a href="http://www.vulture.com/2014/02/alec-baldwin-good-bye-public-life.html">in New York Magazine</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I used to engage with the media knowing that some of it would be adversarial, but now it’s superfluous at best and toxic at its worst. If MSNBC went off the air tomorrow, what difference would it make? If the Huffington Post went out of business tomorrow, what difference would it make?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I agree with much of his piece but Baldwin’s disdain may be misdirected. The question isn’t what if MSNBC or the Huffington Post goes dark tomorrow, it’s what if Facebook does. What if Twitter disappears? Which is to suggest that the problem isn’t the media, it’s us. Baldwin intimates as much later in the piece:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The heart, the arteries of the country are now clogged with hate. The fuel of American political life is hatred.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And still later, on living in New York City since 1979:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>To be a New Yorker meant you gave everybody five feet. You gave everybody their privacy. I recall how, in a big city, many people had to play out private moments in public: a woman sobbing at a pay phone (remember pay phones?), someone studying their paperwork, undisturbed, at the Oyster Bar, before catching the train. We allowed people privacy, we left them alone. And now we don’t leave each other alone. Now we live in a digital arena, like some Roman Colosseum, with our thumbs up or thumbs down.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There was a time the entire world didn’t have a camera in their pocket—the first thing that cell phones did was to kill the autograph business. Nobody cares about your autograph. There are cameras everywhere, and there are media outlets for them to “file their story.” They take your picture in line for coffee. They’re trying to get a picture of your baby. Everyone’s got a camera. When they’re done, they tweet it. It’s … unnatural.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yeah, I know, boo hoo for the famous the person, but I think he’s on to something that requires at least a little introspection on our part. How do we separate the person from the celebrity? How do we tell the difference between the gossip and the news?</p>

<p>Anyway, Baldwin closes with the worst thing a person can say about New York:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything I hated about L.A. I’m beginning to crave. L.A. is a place where you live behind a gate, you get in a car, your interaction with the public is minimal. I used to hate that. But New York has changed. Manhattan is like Beverly Hills.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Oof.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baseball’s First Pitch Loses Its Exclusivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/29/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T14:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/29/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Andrew Keh <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/29/sports/baseball/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity.html">for the New York Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a sport that clings to its traditions — from managers wearing uniforms to the playing of “Take Me Out to the Ball Game” during the seventh-inning stretch — one time-honored feature at the ballpark has taken an absurd turn, at least for the game’s purists: the ceremonial first pitch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m torn. The first pitch <em>is</em> a time-honored tradition that is being sullied by corporate sponsorship. On the other hand, the Phillie Phanatic’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aW-ljrm7a6g">Hatfield hot dog launcher</a> holds a special place in my heart and has nothing to do with the game either.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[YouTube Set to Introduce Paid Subscriptions This Spring]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/youtube-subscriptions-coming/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-29T11:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/youtube-subscriptions-coming</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Speaking of <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/eagle-hox-funds-tuition/">lessons in monetizing video content</a>, here’s Jason Del Rey <a href="http://adage.com/article/digital/youtube-set-introduce-paid-subscriptions-spring/239437/">at Ad Age</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>YouTube has reached out to a small group of channel producers and asked them to submit applications to create channels that users would have to pay to access. As of now it appears that the first paid channels will cost somewhere between $1 and $5 a month, two of these people said. In addition to episodic content, YouTube is also considering charging for content libraries and access to live events, a la pay-per-view, as well as self-help or financial advice shows.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Remember <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/09/19/vimeo-monetization/">Vimeo’s Tip Jar and forthcoming pay-to-view service</a>? Like I said back in September, 2013 is shaping up to be a big year in this space.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Newsweek Kills its Print Edition]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/10/18/goodbye-newsweek/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-18T08:35:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/10/18/goodbye-newsweek</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tina Brown and Baba Shetty, <a href="http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2012/10/18/a-turn-of-the-page-for-newsweek.html">this morning</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Newsweek will transition to an all-digital format in early 2013. As part of this transition, the last print edition in the United States will be our Dec. 31 issue.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I don’t read Newsweek, and have found their digital offerings thus far appalling.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> However, this is major news in the media world. I expect this is the first of many similar announcements throughout 2013.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In our judgment, we have reached a tipping point at which we can most efficiently and effectively reach our readers in all-digital format. This was not the case just two years ago. It will increasingly be the case in the years ahead.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s a brave new world, I suppose.</p>

<p>Still, I give the all-digital Newsweek a year, maybe two at best.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Perhaps they’ve updated their Newsstand app, but once upon a time it was terrible.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
