<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: People | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/people/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Director of the Decade: Steven Soderbergh]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/30/director-of-the-decade/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-30T08:51:15+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/30/director-of-the-decade</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>After a great deal of discussion on our <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/28/bests-of-the-decade-candlercast-part-iv-directors/">bests of the decade
podcast</a>, we are
finally ready to let you in on our director of the decade: Steven Soderbergh. He won an Oscar, made a slew of
successful films while keeping his arthouse street cred, legitimized the RED Camera, and pretty much just
blew everyone out of the water in the last ten years. But don’t take my word for it, Sunrise provided a great
writeup of the man and his decade. Let us know in the comments if you think we chose wisely (or not).</em></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/5989656.jpg" title="Steven Soderbergh" ></p>

<p>The way in which Steven Soderbergh starts off this decade is with such veracity and force with <em>Traffic</em> and
<em>Erin Brochovich</em>, it is a wonder that he not only maintains such consistency towards the end, but implements
a fascinating success that is important not only for him as an artist, but for us as an audience.</p>

<p>Leaving the nineties as a “Sundance” poster boy with questionable box office draw, he made a sudden turn with
1998’s <em>Out of Sight</em> and opened the decade with winning one of two Best Director nominations, to which only
Michael Curtiz’s 1938 double nomination loss comes close in comparison. While Curtiz was just as much of a
workhorse, what makes Soderbergh’s nomination so amazing is the metaphoric weight of self-challenge it
represents. This challenge, as it were, is extended beyond his own growth as an artist into the ever-growing
challenges he places upon his peers and audience.</p>

<p>With the thunderous advance in technology, the accessibility of media has allowed for more consumption
without the challenge directed toward its make and read. While cinematic history notes figures such as
Jan-Luc Godard or Martin Scorsese pushing past previous cinematic limitations, not just through language and
syntax, but from it’s preparation right through to reception, Soderbergh has been able to successfully propel
American cinema into the digital/non-linear realm with the same vigor, enthusiasm and progressive attitude
toward the possibilities. And while the Best Director Oscar is awarded one evening, his going right back to
work on <em>Ocean’s Eleven</em> the following day suggests an allegiance to advancement rather than revelry in the
successes of the day.</p>

<p>Securing his <em>Ocean’s Eleven</em> strategy successfully enacted theories of cinema’s past: simultaneous stature
as a studio director and the experimental freedom suggested by previous studio/indie predecessor models
Scorsese and Coppola. This balance of work has opened up the opportunity not to only deliver a meaningful
punch through his experimental works (such as <em>Full Frontal</em> or <em>Bubble</em>) but such depth trickles back into
his studio works and blurs the line between a “wide audience” film and “art-house” fare, so that <em>The Good
German</em> or <em>Ocean’s Thirteen</em> is both and neither. What is so amazing about the ability of his films to stand
out beyond these “terms” is that he has allowed modern American box-office cinema to finally stand on it’s
legs as “art,” whether it’s opening to a substantial amount of money on opening day or not. What’s more, is
that he expects you to interact and participate with any of his films in the same way, so that a political
message is intrinsic to <em>Che</em> just as much as it is to the <em>The Informant!</em>.</p>

<p>Besides the audience participation challenge, implicit within the work is a drive to push narrative work into
a dialog with other dominant American filmmakers. My favorite film of the decade, <em>Ocean’s Twelve</em>, implies a
conversation with Tarantino, Shyamalan and amazingly Garry Marshall, in a manner less like homage and more
like respectful challenge to “do one better.” This suggests a cinematic challenge among the masters that
results in rapid artistic progression, bringing the real collaborative feel of his beloved sixties cinema!
Such command he has to work with the quiet humble that allows any of his films to work without any such
notice of these workings. That was the craftsman Curtiz would appreciate, while the artistic and progressive
flourishes are what Scorsese can pat him on the back for.</p>

<p>These feats have allowed Soderbergh to confirm the man seen in his <em>sex, lies and videotape</em> Sundance win of
1989, a means of continual development that secures him as the new American cinema master in the likes of all
the greats that persevere to push an art form ahead. Please check the updates for his current Aussie stage
play <em>Tot-Mom</em>, or the future 3D “Cleopatra” musical- opus, that I’m sure will continue to evolve the media
landscape in the manner appropriate for the “digital/non-linear” age.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Watching Inglourious Basterds in a Room Full of Jews]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/17/watching-inglourious-basterds-in-a-room-full-of-jews/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-17T12:23:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/17/watching-inglourious-basterds-in-a-room-full-of-jews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/inglourious-basterds-may13photo-03.jpg"></p>

<p>Last night, the Jewish Theological Seminary (JTS, the primary higher educational institution of the Conservative Movement) hosted a screening and panel on <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>. (To catch up on how the candler blog feels about the film, you can check Sunrise Tippeconnie’s essay, <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/08/21/once-upon-a-time-in-violence-occupied-cinema-an-analysis-of-inglourious-basterds/">Once Upon a Time in Violence Occupied Cinema</a>, which was written for the film’s theatrical release.) Though an appearance by Quentin Tarantino was promised, the auteur was a no show claiming a sore throat (he gets the benefit of the doubt from me). Luckily, the producer of the film, Lawrence Bender, one of QT’s hebraic guides on the project, was in attendance to discuss the topic of “Jewish Persecution and the Fantasy of Revenge” alongside Dr. Amy Kalmanofsky, a bible and horror film scholar, and Rabbi Jack Moline, a pulpit Rabbi in Virginia whose Kol Nidre sermon about <em>Inglourious Basterds</em> sparked the institution’s interest in hosting such an event. Also, leading the panel was the school’s Chancellor, Arnold M. Eisen. Phew, now you have all the details, so how was it?</p>

<p>This was my third public screening of the film, though the first one on video. I have to say, if you missed this movie on film, you pretty much missed it. But that’s neither here nor there. This was an academic event so I gave some leeway on projected quality, though I will say I’ve seen much worse in other college auditoriums. Unsurprisingly, watching the film in a room full of mostly Jews, mind you months after the film had been unleashed on the masses, was barely different from watching the film in a room full of gentiles. Duh. A great fry cook once said “peoples is peoples”, of course, these are the chosen people watching their greatest enemies slaughtered on screen with great flair. There must be something different.</p>

<p>Well, let’s see, the audience wasn’t quite as “in” on the jokes that a room full of film critics would be in on. There are points in the film at which I was the only one laughing hysterically, usually violent scenes, but again that happened at my other screenings. While there were no great cheers as Hitler’s corpse gets the Swiss cheese treatment, which Mr. Bender says there were at the Israeli premiere, the audience did seem to get a kick out of some of the Nazi-killing gore. “Say aufedersein to your Nazi balls”, for example, got everyone quite excited. Just as I felt at the film’s release, this is an altogether human story, not one of Jewish redemption. But don’t tell the curators of this event, because they brought up some really interesting points about the film in the context of modern (and ancient) Jewish thought.</p>

<p>Dr. Kalmanofsky, no stranger to Judeo-Chrisitian-pop deconstruction, opened the discussion with some fascinating points about the concept of the revenge fantasy, positing that the Jewish bible, specifically the story of the exodus from Egypt, indulges the concept of violent revenge. Besides the ten plagues brought down against their aggressors, arguably deserved, the Israelites break out in song and dance after they cross the parted Sea of Reeds, which closes and drowns the entire Egyptian faction that was chasing them. This punishment goes well beyond the tit-for-tat measures of the plagues, and remorse is not really discussed until the Rabbinic era of Judaism several hundred years after the fact. In other words, while the modern Jew may be morally inquisitive and emotionally conflicted, in the bible, living out the revenge fantasy was something very real.</p>

<p>Rabbi Moline proffered that the Jewish people have become mired in thought for so long that the idea of physical redemption has been lost. The saying “two Jews, three opinions” comes to mind on this point. As the concept of Talmudic discourse has proliferated, especially in the wake of the Holocaust (Why did this happen to us? Is it our fault?), Jews may have lost the instinct of revenge, which Moline points out is in fact a basic human instinct. The film provides that for a generation of Jews who view the holocaust in a new light. <em>Inglorious Basterds</em> represents a voice for that generation.</p>

<p>Producer Lawrence Bender’s input, obviously the most cinematic in this crowd, was quite interesting. After telling a story about Tarantino calling actors by their characters’ names on set which resulted in more than a few awkward moments with Martin Wuttke, the actor who portrays Hitler in the film, he joined in on Rabbi Moline’s generational perspective of the film. Looking to a specific arc from the last twenty years, he mentioned that we go from <em>Schindler’s List</em> to <em>Life Is Beautiful</em> to <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>. Another way to put it is from drama to comedy to fantasy. This is a concept I could write volumes about, but I’ll spare you for now. Another interesting point Mr. Bender brought up is that in both the Israeli and German premieres of the film, the audiences felt a sense of personal redemption. In both cases, the press mentioned that only a non-German/non-Jew could pull off such a film. I’m not sure that there is any validity to this point, however the fact remains that a non-German/non-Jew <em>did</em> make this film.</p>

<p>All in all it was a fascinating evening. Kudos to JTS for putting together such a relevant program. I don’t really believe that there is all that much specifically Jewish about the film, but Rabbi Moline kept harping on the fact that the film has awoken something in the Jewish community. Not a call to arms, but a call to deconstructing the meaning of the inner vengeance of a people. Polemics have always been an important pillar of Rabbinic discourse, but visceral nature is something often pushed to the side in favor of academics. Perhaps, says the Rabbi, it is a time to finally confront that urge we have to murder Hitler, to root out our enemies. Not to indulge it, but to question it.</p>

<p>Hell, if one little film can bring out all that from the leaders of one of the world’s major religions, it must be doing something right. What say you, readers? Fill up the comments with your thoughts on the matter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Remembering Mr. Movie, Steve Friedman, 1947-2009]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/09/25/remembering-mr-movie-steve-friedman-1947-2009/"/>
    <updated>2009-09-25T09:57:11+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/09/25/remembering-mr-movie-steve-friedman-1947-2009</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2009/09/mrmovie-300x286.jpg" alt="Steve Friedman, aka Mr. Movie" />For as long as I can remember, my
father has listened to talk radio to fall asleep. As a boy, I tried to emulate
this mannerism upon receiving my first clock radio. There was a certain charm
to being lulled to sleep by people chatting non-sensically about politics,
current events, and other issues of which I had no vested interest. But on
Sunday nights, sleep would not come so easily. That was the night I actually
listened to the radio; that was the night that Steve Friedman took the
airwaves in Philadelphia.</p>

<p>Also known as Mr. Movie, Friedman, who passed away earlier this week, was a
radio host with an encyclopedic knowledge of cinema. Part film critic, part
historian, he was a man who very simply loved movies. Back in the days before
IMDb, the forgetful viewer had a choice of unwieldy tomes such as Halliwells
or Moviehound to keep one’s facts straight. For the unanswerable, or what I
would now call the un-googleable, there was Mr. Movie. “It was the movie where
there was a murder in it…”; “Who was that actor? He always played a bad guy,
except this one time…”; “I think the director was  from Europe…” He always
had an answer and a story to share with his eager listenership.</p>

<p>What is so baffling to a critic of my generation about Mr. Movie is that he
managed to retain an incredible amount of information before the advent of
home video. The bulk of the movies he would discuss, Hollywood classics, are
films he would have seen in the theater, maybe only a handful of times. He was
a film buff who never grew up. Up to his dying day (he passed away a few hours
after a broadcast), Mr. Movie never lost that childish love of movies.</p>

<p>One memory that sticks out for me was listening to how fondly he spoke of the
1985 film <em>Explorers</em>. On it’s face, <em>Explorers</em> is a children’s film. Three
friends build a spaceship out of an abandoned tilt-a-whirl car after they all
experience the same dreams. Upon reaching the mothership that sent them the
plans for the spacecraft, they find that their extraterrestrial pen pals are
actually just kids, who are in trouble for making such a long distance call.
Given that his favorite film, according to <a href="http://www.philly.com/philly/blogs/the-insider/Steve_Friedman.html">Philly.com’s
obituary</a>,
was <em>Forbidden Planet</em>, it is no wonder that he would lean so favorably
towards a sci-fi flick for youngsters.</p>

<p>To the mind of someone like Mr. Movie, there is no distinction between a good
arthouse movie and a good blockbuster. A good movie is a good movie. As
viewers and critics, we can only strive to be as democratic in our approach as
the man they called Mr. Movie. He will be missed.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Von Trier as Trickster, Cannes You Believe It?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/21/von-trier-as-trickster-cannes-you-believe-it/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-21T12:19:59+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/21/von-trier-as-trickster-cannes-you-believe-it</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>The candler blog is based in New York City and is still in it’s first year, so when I went to the airport to buy my ticket to the French Riviera but could only hand them the lint in my pockets, I was rebuffed and sent back to my Manhattan abode. So yeah, I’m not at Cannes reporting on the biggest film news in the world, but we certainly can get some work done at a safe distance, no? Let’s gather some of the noise and make a little story about it. With me? Here goes…</em></p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.offoffoff.com/film/2004/images/fiveobstructions.jpg"></p>

<p>Last week, the latest film from the ineffable Lars Von Trier, <em>Antichrist</em>, screened at the 62nd Cannes Film Festival, apparently causing the international film community to synchronously blush and squirm on the edge their seats. The internets are aflutter with talk about how great/sexy/violent/evil/awful/awesome the movie is. Is anyone surprised that Mr. Von Trier is once again a polarizing figure in cinema? What were you expecting?</p>

<p>An original member of the Scandinavian Dogme 95 collective, Lars Von Trier is one of the group’s most illustrious ex-pats. He made a real impact in the U.S. with his video musical <em>Dancer in the Dark</em>, starring Björk and Catherine Deneuve. After recieving  flack for making a film critiquing North American lifestyles (<em>Dancer</em> takes place in Canada) without ever having visited the continent, the director responded defiantly with <em>Dogville</em>, a grandiose experiment set in 1930s America. For some reason, every time you come close to pinpointing exactly what kind of filmmaker Mr. Von Trier is, he eludes you, sidestepping any label and making something completely unexpected.</p>

<p>I don’t want to talk about his newest film or the headier work mentioned above. I want to talk about Lars Von Trier, the unabashed trickster.</p>

<p>For 2006’s <em>The Boss of it All</em>, the acclaimed director utilized a system dubbed “Automavision”. Basically, he shot the film only from wider angles, or all establishing shots, and allowed a computer randomly tilt, pan, or zoom. Watching the film, you would never know this. It feels wholly organic, intentional. In fact, for Mr. Von Trier, it seems almost tame. Of course, behind the curtain the Danish cinéaste had a pile of tricks he was working with.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2009/05/23boss600a.jpg" title="Boss Of It All Still" ></p>

<p>The plot is endearing and appropriate for such a ludicrous filmmaking method. Kristoffer is a struggling actor who is hired for a job at an IT company that he doesn’t quite understand. He quickly learns that Ravn is the company’s CEO, but has been pretending that he is just a manager answering to a higher power, the elusive boss of  it all who no one has ever met. By acting like an underling to the non-existent boss, Ravn is absolved of any real responsibility, particularly when it comes to firing people. He can just blame it on the the boss of it all, whom Kristoffer has been hired to play for the purposes of merger negotiations with an Icelandic company.</p>

<p>The scope of the story is small but the laughs are big and the form is unique. The Automavision process seemingly enhances the story more than detracting from it but questions abound. How much control does the computer really have? Why would Lars Von Trier relinquish so much control? What’s the point of reinventing the wheel here anyway? After leaving the Dogme 95 movement behind, Mr. Von Trier has gone out of his way to break all of the rules of that group’s <a href="http://cinetext.philo.at/reports/dogme_ct.html">“Vow of Chastity”</a>. Besides breaking the specific codes of conduct with <em>The Boss of It All</em>, he has left the ideals of Dogme completely in the dust. Giving control over to a machine, he is simultaneously removing himself as creative controller and, amazingly, further pressing his status as provocateur by drawing attention to his shrunken role.</p>

<p>This is Trier the trickster. By defying our best attmepts to define him, he is toying with our expectations not only of the director but of the cinema itself. So bring on Antichrist, Lars. We may not be ready to watch it, but it seems that every time you pick up a camera we are left reconsidering the purposes of filmmaking. For that, we thank you. It is this boldness, this artistry, this prickishness that keeps us moving forward.</p>

<p>For a look at where he’ll take us next, check out this preview of <em>Antichrist</em>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reading, Remebering Jack Cardiff; 1914-2009]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/23/reading-remebering-jack-cardiff-1914-2009/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-23T15:22:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/23/reading-remebering-jack-cardiff-1914-2009</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was in the basement of a Manhattan bookshop when I was forced to purchase
Jack Cardiff’s memoir, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Magic-Hour-Jack-Cardiff/dp/0571176402"><em>Magic Hour: The Life of a
Cameraman</em></a>. A
cinematographer friend of mine refused me a ride back to Philadelphia unless I
purchased it. “But don’t you own it? Can’t I borrow it?” I pleaded. “Trust me,
you’ll need a copy for yourself”. He was right.</p>

<p>Mr. Cardiff, who passed away earlier this week at the ripe age of 94, was a
cinematographer and filmmaker whose most well known claim to fame was being
the first British cameraman to shoot with Technicolor. His autobiography,
published under the prolific Faber &amp; Faber film moniker is an incredible read
for film geeks and cinema civilians alike. While so many other memoirs are
drizzled in name-droppery, fluffy anecdotes and grandiose “I-pioneered-that”
ego-centricisms without any semblance of an actual story, Mr. Cardiff’s tale
is one of adventure, invention, and discovery.</p>

<p>For us film folk living in a competitive and advanced 21st century, it is
often hard to remember the early wonder that was the cinema. In Mr. Cardiff’s
heyday, the motion picture was still a young art trying to find equal footing
with its established brethren: painting, photography, theater and the like. Of
course, without the introspection we have now looking back on olden times, Mr.
Cardiff approached these advancements in stride.</p>

<p>In 1936, Count von Keller and his wife hired Jack Cardiff to film their world
travels in glorious Technicolor. As a young man relatively new to the
business, he was given an opportunity like no other, to not only see the world
but to record it as had never been done before. Romantically, the artist
describes his world travels in great detail in his book. These are the parts
that will astound any reader, film buff or not.</p>

<p>Embarrassingly, the only film of his that I have seen in its entirety is
<a href="http://www.amazon.com/Black-Narcissus-Collection-Deborah-
Kerr/dp/B00004XQN4/ref=pd_bbs_sr_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=dvd&amp;qid=1240585728&amp;sr=8-1"><em>Black Narcissus</em></a>.
Watching it, you can see Mr. Cardiff’s worldly influence. Even today, there is
a certain amount of magic in the sheer expanse of the colorful film. Directors
Michael Powell and Emeric Pressburger put together a film that we well ahead
of its time in both form and content. How fitting it was to have a look that
would influence generations to come.</p>

<p>I have had very little exposure to Jack Cardiff, yet what little I know of him
has greatly influenced the way I approach film. You can look up a list of his
films on <a href="http://www.imdb.com/name/nm0002153/">IMDb</a> and, like I will be
doing, pop them on your queue. But for a real treat, you should check out
<em>Magic Hour</em>. Either way, bringing more Cardiff into one’s life is a very good
thing.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
