<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Production | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/production/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NYC's Production Growing Pains]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/17/nyc-production-growing-pains/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-17T07:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/17/nyc-production-growing-pains</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>“It’s just not fair because businesses are temporarily being shut down to accommodate filming,” said Joseph Conley, chairman of Community Board 2 in Queens, which represents Long Island City, Sunnyside, Woodside and a portion of Maspeth. Contrary to what City Hall says, Mr. Conley sees little evidence of an upside.</p></p><p><p>“Production crews don’t localize, so there’s no benefit to the community,” he said, pointing out that when it comes to meals, for example, the crews bring in their own outside catering companies.</p><footer><strong>-Marine Cole</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20120115/REAL_ESTATE/301159997'>Crain’s New York Business</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I see this issue from both sides. New York City is lucky to have as many productions as it has and could use a lot more. On the other it can be extremely annoying to have a film production on your block for even a day.</p>

<p>Every once in a while I get a film shooting near my apartment. The last one had its camera village camped out near my stoop. The crew couldn’t have cared less that I was trying to get in and out of my building. I gave them a pass because I know how gruelling a day on a film set can be. Other residents didn’t seem so pleased.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>The gist of this Crains article is actually quite positive. People tend to view New York City as monolithic and overpowering, worth putting up with only so long as you need to. In reality it’s a place like any other and the locals need to be wooed and taken care of like anywhere else. It looks like efforts are coalescing to help make this relationship better for everyone. That can only be a good thing.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>This set in particular was very poorly run. It was never clear to me where I should and shouldn’t be, felt like I was walking through shots sometimes. Worse, there was glass all over the sidewalk leftover from a car accident they were shooting. The sidewalk was completely open and I walked through it.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
