<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Travel | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/travel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dispatches from OKC: Day 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/15/dispatches-from-okc-day-5/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-15T11:11:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/15/dispatches-from-okc-day-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The internet has been touch and go the past two days, and I’m on a friend’s
computer instead of my own, so I can’t add the usual flair you have come to
know and love to this post. Even with the fest completed, this continues to be
an intensely film-related vacation. After a buffet breakfast at a place called
Ingrid’s Kitchen, I headed over to the best bookstore in Oklahoma City, Full
Circle. Designed with all kinds of nooks and crannies and rolling ladders, it
is a store whose selection is not only Okie specific, but wide ranging. It’s
design encourages discovery and their staff are super friendly. No one paid me
to say that, seriously.</p>

<p>I went to Full Circle because my friend, Sunrise Tippeconnie, was signing a
book in which an essay of his is featured. The book is <em><a href="http://www.fortysixthstarpress.com/?page_id=265&amp;c
ategory=1&amp;product_id=5">Sooner Cinema:
Oklahoma Goes to the Movies</a></em> and I’m in the process of reading it. Quite
interesting. This state has a long history of making movies and being
portrayed in them. Which brings me to my next point.</p>

<p>The talk of the town right now is Michael Winterbottom’s <em>The Killer Inside
Me</em>, which is shooting here right now. The film has brought stars Casey
Affleck, Jessica Alba, and Ned Beatty. During the final day of deadCENTER they
had blocked off streets downtown and filled them with 1950s cars. Last night I
headed to Cookie’s, a tiny bar with a lot of heart, for the Cast and Crew
more-than-halfway-through-production party. It was a nice time with some
wonderful karaoke singers. The only celeb to show up was Mr. Beatty, and he
was a gentleman.</p>

<p>I love hanging out with film crews. They are so much more tolerable than
filmmakers because they rarely want to talk about movies. After the bar I went
straight to a Sonic for the second time today. For those of you who don’t know
about Sonic, well, you just have to drive until you find one. I got an Ocean
Water Slushie and some onion rings. They tasted delicious after drinking a
Pacifico cerveza.</p>

<p>We are off to the Wichita Mountains now, probably no more film to deal with
today. I still owe you all some reiews and you’ll get them, but probably not
until I’m back in New York. Poke around the site in the meantime, there’s a
lot going on here.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
