<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: technology | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/technology/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Screenplay Markdown for Marked is Here]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/08/screenplay-markdown-for-marked-is-here/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-08T16:12:38+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/08/screenplay-markdown-for-marked-is-here</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is exciting. I’ve mentioned Stu Maschwitz’s Screenplay Markdown (SPMD) here a <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/08/16/i-hope-screenplay-markdown-kills-the-page-paradigm/">few</a> <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/08/17/screenbundle-the-plain-text-screenwriting-solution-you-can-use-right-now/">times</a> <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/06/the-writing-in-screenwriting/">before</a>. I’ve been smitten with the idea ever since he cooked it up in August. Thankfully, I’m not alone.</p>

<p>About a month ago, I <a href="http://twitter.com/poritsky/statuses/132857242004357122">tweeted</a> asking if it would be possible to use Screenplay Markdown in Brett Terpstra’s excellent Markdown previewing app, <a href="http://markedapp.com/">Marked</a>. To my surprise, Brett <a href="http://twitter.theinfo.org/132857242004357122">responded</a> enthusiastically, then Stu got in touch as well. Before long we were all communicating, along with <a href="http://www.librador.com/">Martin Vilcans</a>, whose command line utility, <a href="https://github.com/vilcans/screenplain">Screenplain</a>, was the first to turn SPMD text files into formatted screenplays.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>In order to learn a new syntax, it helps to have a way to preview your output so you know you’re properly formatting your document. It took me about a year to learn Markdown because I didn’t have an application as easy and robust as Marked to show me what my formatted writings scribblings look like.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Markdown and SPMD aren’t that difficult to master, but once you do you realize how quickly you can get your thoughts out of your head and into a document, from anywhere. That’s the point. Marked makes it super simple to format your plain text document. Now Screenplay Markdown for Marked makes it as straightforward as possible to preview your formatted scripts.</p>

<p>So what does it look like? On the left is a sample script in TextEdit. On the right is the same script in Marked.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/textedit-marked-sidexside.png"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/textedit-marked-sidexside.png" alt="TextEdit Marked Side by Side" /></a></p>

<p>Screenplay Markdown for Marked is still missing some features, but it will only get better from here. Stu, Martin and Brett have all been working hard to make this a great solution for writing screenplays. This is feels like the beginning of a wider SPMD project. We value your input and feedback, so please leave comments here or on Twitter (or wherever) to let us know how you like using SPMD for Marked.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Installation instructions are below and on the <a href="http://support.markedapp.com/kb/how-to-tips-and-tricks /using-screenplay-markdown-with-marked">Marked support site</a>. Go get <a href="http://markedapp.com/">Marked</a>, the SPMD package below and your favorite text editor and write something already.</p>

<p><strong>UPDATE 02/08/2012:</strong> Screenplay Markdown for Marked is now Fountain for Marked. Please <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/02/08/fountain-for-marked">visit the updated page</a> for more information.</p>

<h2 id="deldownload--installation"><del>Download &amp; Installation</del></h2>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><del>Download <a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/plugins/download-monitor/download.php?id=SPMD_Marked.1.0.zip">SPMD_Marked.1.0.zip</a>.</del></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>Install the files</del></p>

    <ul>
      <li><del>Double click the .zip file to extract its contents</del></li>
      <li><del>Move <code>marked-screenplain</code> folder to a folder of your choice
</del>        <ul>
          <li><del>Suggestions: Your home folder, <code>/usr/local/bin</code>, <code>~/Library/Application Support/Marked</code></del></li>
          <li><del>Move the Screenplay.css file to <code>~/Library/Application Support/Marked/Custom CSS/</code></del></li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>Launch Marked and open Preferences</del></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>In the <strong>Behavior</strong> panel, check the Custom Markdown Processor box and in the field below it, enter the path to screenplain_marked</del></p>

    <ul>
      <li><del>This will be the full (no ~) UNIX path. If you put it in <code>/usr/local/bin/</code> it would be <code>/usr/local/bin/marked-screenplain/bin/screenplain</code>.</del></li>
      <li><del>If you put it in your users’s home folder, it would be: <code>/Users//marked-screenplain/bin/screenplain</code></del></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>Go to the <strong>Style</strong> tab of Preferences</del></p>

    <ul>
      <li><del>Click the plus button (+) under the table to add a new custom style</del></li>
      <li><del>In the file select dialog, navigate to <code>~/Library/Application Support/Marked/Custom CSS/Screenplay Markdown.css</code> and add it</del></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><del>Open a <a href="http://prolost.com/storage/downloads/spmd/SPMD_proposal.html">Screenplay Markdown</a> document.</del></p>

    <ul>
      <li><del>The custom processor you entered should be on by default. It can be toggled per-document using the gear menu or ⌥⌘C.</del></li>
      <li><del>Select the “Screenplay Markdown” style from the Style selector in the bottom left.</del></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<h4 id="delnotes"><del>Notes:</del></h4>

<ul>
  <li><del>This is a customized version of <a href="https://github.com/vilcans/screenplain/tree/master/screenplain">screenplain</a> by <a href="http://www.librador.com/">Martin Vilcans</a></del></li>
  <li><del>It creates <code>h2</code> instead of <code>div</code> for “slug” types to allow for TOC navigation in Preview (hover over the upper right edge of the preview)</del></li>
  <li><del>Currently there are no export abilities for formats other than PDF/HTML</del></li>
  <li><del>Pagination doesn’t work properly just yet. While you can print and export PDFs of your scripts, note that pages will not be numbered and may not accurately render (Characters may be on different pages than their dialogue, no “mores” or “continueds”, etc.). This may be fixed in future updates.</del></li>
</ul>

<h2 id="delicon"><del>Icon</del></h2>

<p><del>Check out this awesome SPMD for Marked icon Brett made. <a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/downloads/MarkedSPMDIcon.png">Download</a> and enjoy.</del></p>

<p><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2011/12/MarkedSPMDIcon.png" alt="" /></p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>The <a href="http://screenplain.appspot.com/">Screenplain web app</a> can even quickly create FDX files from your SPMD scripts. It’s pretty awesome.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Or don’t like, but be nice.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hulu Face Match Points out Actors Whose Names You Can't Remember]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/08/hulu-face-match-points-out-actors-whose-names-you-cant-remember/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-08T13:16:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/08/hulu-face-match-points-out-actors-whose-names-you-cant-remember</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From Hulu’s <a href="http://blog.hulu.com/2011/12/08/from-hulu-labs- face-match/">official blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When you turn it on, the Hulu Face Match Engine can tell you more about the actors in the video the instant they appear. Just hover the mouse over a character’s face, and the video will pause to tell you a little bit more about that guy whose name you just can’t remember.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>We’re in the future. Neat.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/12/hulu-face-match/">Brooks Review</a>)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Writing in Screenwriting]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/06/the-writing-in-screenwriting/"/>
    <updated>2011-12-06T22:06:48+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/06/the-writing-in-screenwriting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Screenplay formatting has turned out to be one of the most enduring aspects of the filmmaking process. Can you think of anything else in the movie business that looks roughly the same as it did sixty years ago?</p>

<p>Screenwriting software has become a cottage industry. These applications aim to make it dead simple to write a screenplay, moving the onus of formatting out of the heads of writers and into computers. So why do most screenwriting applications suck?<!-- more --></p>

<p>Most of these apps have shifted focus away from writing and instead have become information managers. When was the last time a screenwriting application innovated in how we actually approach writing? Profanity count? Names database? Tagger? Please. We can do better.</p>

<p>My biggest writing fear has always been the blank page. With my iPad and iPhone always at arm’s length, that isn’t as much of an issue anymore. Most of my writings start with random notes I come up with when I’m out, on the subway or, ahem, in dispose. Gone are the days when I sit down at my computer, launch a new blank document and wonder “What am I supposed to do now?”</p>

<p>I moved my workflow to all <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/20/my-text-problem/">plain text documents</a> because of their portability. Screenwriters have no such luxury. Final Draft’s FDX format is good, but in order for other applications to use them they must either be exported or rewrapped as something else. It’s impossible to work on the same FDX file in two different applications, while I’m able to work on my text documents in literally dozens of applications. Why should anyone be stuck writing in one application forever?</p>

<p>Stu Maschwitz articulated the solution this past summer when he envisioned <a href="http://prolost.com/spmd">Screenplay Markdown</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>So the ultimate mobile screenwriting solution may be, for the time being, your favorite among the many lovely Dropbox-based plaintext writing apps out there.</p>
</blockquote>

<blockquote>
  <p>Are other screenwriters as dissatisfied with their workflow as I am? Is there a part of your workflow where you’d give up WYSIWYG and accurate pagination to just get words on the page in a way that freed you from a specific device, and specific software? Or do we expect that Final Draft, Inc.’s <a href="http://www.finaldraft.com/products/ipad/">promised-but-delayed</a> iPad app will be what we’ve been wanting?</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Screenplays haven’t changed in who knows how long, but the needs of writers have. It’s time to turn the act of writing a script into as straightforward and simple a process as writing a note to yourself. That’s why I believe <a href="http://prolost.com/storage/downloads/spmd/SPMD_proposal.html">Screenplay Markdown</a> may just take off.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FBI and Homeland Security May Be Screwing Up Piracy Seizures; Shocker]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/29/fbi-and-homeland-security-may-be-screwing-up-piracy-seizures-shocker/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T22:50:26+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/29/fbi-and-homeland-security-may-be-screwing-up-piracy-seizures-shocker</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jeff Roberts for <a href="http://paidcontent.org/article/419-feds-play-movie-industry-messages-on-seized-websites-legality-unclear/">Paid Content</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The FBI and Homeland Security announced the latest seizures in exultant <a href="http://www.theregister.co.uk/2011/11/28/feds_seize_130_sites_ in_cyber_monday_crackdown/">press releases</a> lauding the eighth phase of the “Operation In Our Sites” campaign under which the federal government is seizing the names of websites that sell counterfeit merchandise.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In short, the Feds are cracking down on film piracy by seizing Web sites that seem to have nothing to do with film piracy based on a 1970 anti-drug law. Also, they’re redirecting to a dubious PSA instead of unloading the seized URLs. Here it is.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/6YScoXn31Mg "></iframe></div></p>

<p>This is a gross misrepresentation of who piracy hurts. Film piracy hurts the executives at multi-national conglomerates and above-the-line talent with residual contracts. A boom operator? Gimme a break. This distorts the matter to the point of disbelief. They’re screwing it up.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://brooksreview.net/2011/11/fed-legality/">Brooks Review</a>.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[iCloud Workflow that Rivals Dropbox in the New iA Writer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/29/iawriter-icloud/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-29T10:47:12+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/29/iawriter-icloud</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As you may know, I love <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/20/my-text-problem/">playing with text editors</a>. Information Architects’ <a href="http://www.iawriter.com/">iA Writer</a> has been one of the more mesmerizing apps available for both iPad and the Mac. Its core feature is a beautiful monospaced typeface from Bold Monday called <a href="http://www.boldmonday.com/en/nitti_overview">Nitti Light</a>. Beyond that, Writer sells itself based its lack of features. You can’t change the font size, color scheme or page width. It’s the distraction-free writing software worth a <a href="http://www.kungfugrippe.com/post/1169153343/only-you">Merlin Mann lampoon</a>.</p>

<p>Though I own both versions of Writer, I rarely find myself writing in it because of its many limitations.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> However, there’s a new feature that is pretty damn cool in the latest update: iCloud syncing. Only a handful of developers have figured out how to implement Apple’s new iCloud service and iA Writer is the first writing app to add it. For as long as plain text editors have exploded into a cottage industry on iOS, <a href="http://www.dropbox.com/">Dropbox</a> has been the de facto file syncing solution. Writer proves that iCloud might, <em>might</em> give Dropbox a run for its money.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Here’s how it works. On your iPad, you’ve got three storage options: iPad, Dropbox and iCloud. The iPad option is basically local, un-synced storage. One new feature of Writer’s Dropbox syncing is that you can now access any folder on your account, not just the “Writer” folder. You can create new documents directly in any of the storage buckets or move them between one another. The iCloud option doesn’t support subfolders, but instead acts as a root folder on for your synced Writer documents.</p>

<p>On your Mac, you can still access any text document in your file system, including in your Dropbox folder. The difference is that now, under the File menu, you have an “iCloud” option. Hover over it and all of your available documents are there ready for editing. If you want to move another document into iCloud, you can use the same File&gt;iCloud menu to “Move to Cloud.” Clicking that on any open document, no matter where it is, makes it accessible in your Writer iCloud storage.</p>

<p>It sounds confusing, especially after getting used to Dropbox’s “file system in the cloud” simplicity. Here’s the thing, though. The iCloud sync is fast and pretty rock solid. Editing the same document on my Mac and on my iPad updated quickly and smoothly. The changes propagated across both systems in that “it just works” kind of way. Better, if you want the file system advantages of Dropbox to do something like, say, open an iCloud document in another text editor, you can actually do that do. As a <a href="https://plus.google.com/u/0/115711522874757126523/posts/aytBnbpK8iA">Google+ commenter notes</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You can save directly to iCloud on the Mac if you navigate to Writer’s iCloud ‘Documents’ folder located in <code>~/Library/Mobile Documents/~jp~informationarchitects~Writer/Documents</code>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>From this folder, you can copy older documents you’d like to use on your iPad or open up any of your documents in any other text editors. This is still not the simplest solution for a tweaker, but it’s a pretty good one. You’ll need to keep your User Library visible and there are a <a href="http://www.macworld.com/article/161156/2011/07/view_library_folder_in_lion. html">few ways to make that happe n</a>. To go one step further, you could even use a <a href="http://seiryu.home.comcast.net/~seiryu/symboliclinker.html">symbolic link</a> to make your iCloud Writer documents more accessible to you in another folder.</p>

<p>iA Writer is the first out of the gate on iCloud writing apps, but Information Architects have proven that it can be used as an alternative to Dropbox syncing. Their solution is more elegant than Apple’s own implementation in iWork. I can’t wait to see what other developers come up with next.</p>

<p>iA Writer is currently discounted in both the Mac and iOS App Stores. If you purchase with the links below you will be supporting the candler blog. Thank you and happy writing.</p>

<table>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Purchase <a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=Oajfc*AWWvY&subid;=&offerid;=146261.1&type;=10&tmpid;=3909&RD;_PARM1=http%3A%2F%2Fitunes.apple.com%2Fus%2Fapp%2Fia-writer%2Fid439623248%3Fmt%3D12">iA Writer for Mac</a></td>
      <td><a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=Oajfc*AWWvY&subid;=&offerid;=146261.1&type;=10&tmpid;=3909&RD;_PARM1=http%3A%2F%2Fitunes.apple.com%2Fus%2Fapp%2Fia-writer%2Fid392502056%3Fmt%3D8">iA Writer for iPad</a></td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>It supports Markdown syntax, but the keyboard shortcuts aren’t as nice as in ByWord, which also lets me change the font. Perhaps my biggest gripe is that the only way to “typewriter scrolling” in Writer is to go into “Focus Mode,” which also requires that all but the current sentence is grayed out. To me, that <em>becomes</em> the distraction.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
