<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SXSW 2010 | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/sxsw-2010/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #14: An Interview with Lena Dunham]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/16/candlercast-14-an-interview-with-lena-dunham/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-16T22:47:46+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/16/candlercast-14-an-interview-with-lena-dunham</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/tinyfurniture_officialstill_300dpi.jpg" title="Still from Tiny Furniture" ></p>

<p>Lena Dunham’s <em>Tiny Furniture</em> just had its world premiere here at SXSW yesterday. It is an extremely funny and revealing film from this New
York-based director. This is only her second feature, though she views it as her first since her last film, Creative Nonfiction, which
premiered at SXSW 2009, was about an hour long. Taking full advantage of the Austin vibe, Dunham made some friends here a year ago, gathered
a crack team in New York City, and spent the last year making this new film.</p>

<p>Her hard work paid of well. <em>Tiny Furniture</em> is ferociously funny and with a heart to boot. It is easy to apply the label of “coming of age
tale” to the film, but that really undersells it. This is not the kind of movie that involves staring into puddles, mirrors or other
reflective surfaces that twenty-somethings on film seem to be attracted to. Instead, we find Aura, played by Ms. Dunham, returning home to
the big apple after college, thrust into a world with no structure, few consequences and little prospects. Between her genius younger sister
soaking up the limelight and her preoccupied artist mother, Aura must blaze her own path in the naked city.</p>

<p>I sat down with Lena to discuss her process and her film. Listen in for some really interesting details about the making of this film, which
was shot entirely on the Canon 7D, a digital still camera that also shoots video. And there’s more! But you have to click play or download.</p>

<p>You can learn more about <em>Tiny Furniture</em> at the film’s <a href="http://www.tinyfurniture.com/">Official Website</a>. The film will be screening once
more at SXSW on Saturday, March 20, 4:15pm at the Alamo Ritz.</p>

<audio controls>
  <source src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-14-lena-dunham.mp3" type="audio/mpeg">
Sorry, your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-14-lena-dunham.mp3">Right-Click to Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in
iTunes</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #13: An Interview with Justin Molotnikov and Claire Mundell]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/16/candlercast-13-an-interview-with-justin-molotnikov-and-claire-mundell/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-16T11:19:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/16/candlercast-13-an-interview-with-justin-molotnikov-and-claire-mundell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/Crying_With_Laughter.jpg"><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/Crying_With_Laughter-
300x199.jpg" alt="Crying With Laughter Still" /></a>Justin Molotnikov’s <em>Crying
With Laughter</em> was the first screener I watched in advance of SXSW this year.
Though it is described as a thriller, that is a particularly unfair label to
put on it. When I sat down with Justin, who is here in Austin for the North
American premiere of his film, I learned that he couldn’t agree more, and in
the best of senses.</p>

<p>The film follows down-on-his-luck comedian Joey Frisk, whose visceral brand of
jokes can be tough to laugh at. Very quickly the film changes its tone from
the mundane to the mysterious. Then  again to the adventurous, and eventually
to the melancholy. The brevity with which it moves from emotion to emotion, or
from genre to genre, is astounding. <em>Crying With Laughter</em> will surprise you
around every turn.</p>

<p>Justin and the film’s producer, Claire Mundell, took some time out of their
schedule to sit with me and discuss their film and some other tid-bits.
Perhaps the most interesting thing Justin and Claire mention is that the
script grew out of a lot of workshopping and improv. In fact, they say, it was
easier to get the film funded without a script than it would have had they had
a finished one from the outset. Sound backwards? Listen in as they explain
their process in making this first feature.</p>

<p><em>Crying with Laughter</em> has two more screenings at SXSW: Tuesday March 16th,
1:30am at the Alamo Ritz and Wednesday, March 17th, 4:30pm at the Alamo Lamar.
It is also available on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Crying-
Laughter-SXSW-Festival-Premiere/dp/B003AOI6DQ/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;s=digital-
video&amp;qid=1268752572&amp;sr=8-1">Amazon Video On Demand</a> and will soon be available on demand through your
cable provider in the U.S. You can find out more information at the film’s
<a href="http://www.cryingwithlaughter.co.uk/">Official Website</a>.</p>

<p>[podcast]http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-13
-crying-with-laughter.mp3[/podcast] <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-13
-crying-with-laughter.mp3">Right-Click to
Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/Web
Objects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTunes</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW 2010 Photo Gallery 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/15/sxsw-2010-photo-gallery-1/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-15T12:27:59+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/15/sxsw-2010-photo-gallery-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve only snaped a few pics so far. Too busy sitting in the dark watching
films. I’ll bring you more as I take them. Enjoy these.</p>

<p>[imagebrowser id=6]</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW Review: Marwencol]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/14/sxsw-review-marwencol/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-14T18:56:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/14/sxsw-review-marwencol</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/marwencol_01.jpg" title="Mark Hogancamp of Marwencol" ></p>

<p>See <em>Marwencol</em>. That’s it. I can try to explain it to you, I can try to let you know how I feel about it, but you and can’t really talk about <em>Marwencol</em> until you see <em>Marwencol</em>.</p>

<p>Okay, I’ll tell you a few things about it since you asked so nicely. The film follows Mark Hogancamp, a man who starts his life over after being beaten half to death. Once he can walk and talk and read again, he begins to learn a few things about his former life, of which he remembers nothing. He was a drunk; a drunk who kept detailed and often horrific journals of his darkest moments. As he slowly tries to put his life together, the pain of dealing with his attack and coming to terms with his former self, he begins practicing his own kind of unconventional therapy.</p>

<p>Mark has built a 1/6th scale WWII Belgian town he calls Marwecol. It is populated with dolls who all have a real world doppelganger, people close to Mark in his everyday, full-scale life. He dresses the characters up, creates plots for them to carry out, and photographs their goings on. The level of authenticity Mark keeps the world running at is astounding. The guns soldiers carry have moving parts. He wheels around a truck full of character so that the truck doesn’t look like it just came out of the box. He wants everything to be as real as possible in Marwencol.</p>

<p>There is more to Mark’s story, a lot more. Director Jeff Malmberg had great access to all things Hogancamp, including his family, his coworkers, and of course the town itself. Narratively, the film progresses in a manner that keeps things interesting. Mark’s former selkf, and current one, has a lot of skeletons in his closet which slowly come out as the film goes on. I would have wanted more from the cinematography of the film, however. I realize it’s a documentary and the character profile here is of the utmost importance, but when you are focusing in on a 1/6th scale world it would be great to have some nicer macro photography. Perhaps I’m spoiled or asking the world, but given how beautifully twisted the town of Marwencol can become, I would love to have seen it more vividly. Like I said, the character here is key, and boy oh boy what a fascinating story Mark Hogancamp has. This is definitely one worth seeing.</p>

<p>You can learn more about <em>Marwencol</em> at the film’s <a href="http://www.marwencol.com">Official Website</a>. There is one more SXSW Screening on Friday March 19th, 1:15 at the Alamo Ritz.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW Review: Kick-Ass]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/14/sxsw-review-kick-ass/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-14T11:33:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/14/sxsw-review-kick-ass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/kickass1_gallery_primary.jpg"><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03
/kickass1_gallery_primary-300x207.jpg" alt="Still from Kick-Ass" /></a>Kick-Ass</em> fits perfectly
into the SXSW landscape as it is what we in the business call a “crowd-
pleaser”. The trick here is that Matthew Vaughn’s film pleases a very specific
crowd, and Austin seems to be the capital not just of Texas, but of the
cynical fanboy (fangirl, fanperson). Based on the comic book series by Mark
Millar, <em>Kick-Ass</em> tells the tale of a mild-mannered high school geek who
gives into his fantasies of becoming a super hero. The story is tight enough,
the visuals pop, and the gore is outrageous. Still this film is missing
something pretty big: an audience outside of Austin.</p>

<p>Let me tell you what we have before I go into my opinion. In a cartoonish New
York City, one ruled by organized (and not so-organized) crime, Dave Lizewski
is a loser at the bottom of every food chain. He gets picked on at school,
mugged in the streets and nothing but bored at home. On the brink of growing
up, he decides to try his hand at being a super hero. After ordering a wet-
suit online, he goes out to fight some crime and eventually becomes an
internet sensation. Of course, there has to be some darkness to any super
tale. <em>Kick-Ass</em>, as Dave has named himself, quickly discovers that there are
villains more evil than he can handle, and heroes more well-equipped than he
could imagine. Accidentally, he has thrust himself into a war for the ages:
good versus evil.</p>

<p>The film balances two very different but overlapping genres with great
finesse. It is a comic book adaptation and a parody of comic book cinema. As a
comic book film, it ticks off marks on the list of required content. Bright
colors and inspired production design, provided by cinematographer Ben Davis
and production designer Russell De Rozario, make almost every frame feel like
it lives on a page. Overlaid text boxes fill out the effect to the delight of
hardcore comic kids. As a parody, it plays brilliantly. Its main cinematic
inspiration is Sam Raimi’s <em>Spiderman</em>, which stands out as the biggest
catalyst to our current heroically saturated film market. Pulling scenes,
musical themes, narration and set designs from Mr. Raimi’s take on the hero,
Mr. Vaughn is able to dance the line of homage and theft while building his
own original language for this film.</p>

<p>Aaron Johnson delivers a nerdy, yet adorable as the title character. He fills
Tobey Maguire’s spandex boots nicely. Christopher Mintz-Plasse, who the
internet will never know by a name other than McLovin’, brings his endearing
brand of geekery to the screen. Even the most trivial of statements out of his
mouth had the Austin audience rolling in the aisles. Nicholas Cage, who spends
a lot of the film spoofing himself and the heroes on which his character is
based, provides some of his best comedic moments since <em>Face/Off</em>. Finally,
the young Chloe Moretz brings her potty mouth into the mix. Kids dropping
f-bombs always bring the yuks.</p>

<p><em>Kick-Ass</em>’s violence is wildly vivid, perhaps to a fault. The filmmakers have
gone above and beyond to deliver fast-paced action that warps your mind inside
out as you try to process what the hell just happened. When you think there’s
only one way to use a weapon, Mr. Vaughn and his creative team will take that
weapon, put a string on it and grab someone’s arm and make them shoot their
own face off. And the blood. Oh the blood. Heads explode, bludgeonings cause
splatter, and limbs fly every which way. To put it lightly, it is an indulgent
film.</p>

<p>That indulgence is really where the trouble lies. <em>Kick-Ass’_s audience is
extremely specific and, ironically, discerning. It is tough to please fandom,
but it is even harder to please the fans and everyone else at the same time.
When I say this doesn’t have an audience outside of Austin, I am speaking of
the proverbial Austin; the state of mind where fanaticism, gore and comedy
collide. This film delivers the laughs that the audience asked for, but how
refreshing it could be to give us something we didn’t expect, or at least
something that can be enjoyed by a bigger niche. I realize this is perhaps a
cynical take on a generally tight film. After all, it _does</em> deliver. You just
need to know what you’re getting into beforehand. Odds are, if you’re headed
to see the film, you’re hyper aware of what you’re being sold, in which case
you’re really going to love <em>Kick-Ass</em>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
