<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Animation | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/animation/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[&#8220;The Filmmaker&#8221; by Robert Lyons]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/22/the-filmmaker-by-robert-lyons/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-22T23:26:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/22/the-filmmaker-by-robert-lyons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/35435433?portrait=0" width="451" height="338" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>

<p>I came across the work of <a href="http://vimeo.com/rlyons">Robert Lyons</a> today on Vimeo. He posts (and links to) a lot of experimental and animation work in addition to his own films. Here’s how he describes the above piece, “The Filmmaker”:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A combination of 2-D cut-out animation, 3-D clay animation, and a little bit of pixilation, I made this film in 1979 shooting with a 16mm Canon Scoopic camera. This is currently the oldest animated film of mine that I have posted, and was created when I was in college at SUNY, New Paltz, when I was 20 years old. This was my earliest attempt at doing clay animation. The music “Communication Breakdown” by Led Zeppelin was added recently, as the original film was silent. It was chosen because it related to the theme of the film and was of the time period from which the film was made.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I really enjoy this little film, though I think he should have left it silent. Zeppelin just doesn’t work here for me. Perhaps I’m being influenced by the fact that it’s so much cleaner and crisper than the picture. In any event, it’s easy enough to hit mute. I wonder what other goodies Robert will be uploading.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
