<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: DVD | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/dvd/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Why People Redbox the Movies They Do]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/16/why-people-redbox-the-movies-they-do/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-16T20:39:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/16/why-people-redbox-the-movies-they-do</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>But <strong><em>I Am Number Four</em></strong>? <strong><em>The Green Hornet</em></strong>? Come on. Most people had the good sense to avoid these movies when they were in theaters. They didn’t get any better on DVD.</p></p><p><p>Or did they?</p></p><p><p>Well, no, not literally. But your expectations are dramatically different when you’re paying a dollar for the entire family to watch a DVD as opposed to $10 apiece at the theater. For most people, “one dollar” is approximately the same as “free.” There’s no investment, no risk. So yeah, everyone said <strong><em>Just Go with It</em></strong> wasn’t very funny. But it’s Adam Sandler, and you’ve laughed at a lot of his stuff in the past, so maybe this one will at least have its moments — and if it doesn’t, so what? It was only a buck.</p><footer><strong>Eric D. Snider</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.film.com/movies/why-people-redbox-the-movies-they-do'>Film.com</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>A lot of good points from Snider about what differentiates Redbox from Netflix. Maybe people just want crap that’s bad for their teeth. Good business model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Conan Takeover Requires Viewing of The Late Shift]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/01/conan-takeover-requires-viewing-of-the-late-shift/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-01T12:08:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/01/conan-takeover-requires-viewing-of-the-late-shift</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2009/05/lateshift.png" alt="Late Shift Promo Still" />This evening, Conan O’Brien starts his
new job as host of “The Tonight Show”. The late night host enters the 11:30
arena with much fanfare and only a tad bit of drama. His predecessor, Jay
Leno, will now be his lead-in at 10:00 this fall; his critics don’t believe
his brand of humor is accessible to the middle of the country, and on top of
that he has the weight of one of the most revered jobs in television resting
on his shoulders.</p>

<p>But whatever struggles he may be having, whatever growing pains may be
occurring in the late night landscape, it cannot be compared to the mess that
occured the last time there was a transition in this space almost tow decades
ago. That affair is best illustrated in the 1996 HBO Original Movie <em>The Late
Shift</em>.</p>

<p>Directed by the actress Betty Thomas, <em>The Late Shift</em> is many things all at
once. It is a backstage opera, a comedy about comedy, a biopic and a winding
espionage-tinged drama. The two leads, Daniel Roebuck as Jay Leno and John
Michael Higgins as David Letterman, embrace their roles with only a hint of
impersonation, fulfilling the recognizable look and feel of the nationally
recognized artists while connecting to the emotional roots of each. It is
burlesque, it is revealing, and it is damn funny stuff.</p>

<p>The story centers around Johnny Carson’s moving on to greener pastures without
ever naming a replacement for his most sought after job in television. What
took place in the aftermath was a whirlwind of negotiations and heartbreak
between the network, Leno, Letterman and seemingly anyone close to either
party. Mr. Leno had proven himself a worthy stand-in for the aging Carson on
air, while Mr. Letterman had given over a decade of his life to NBC, not a
small price to pay in hopes of one day sitting in the same chair as Steve
Allen, Jack Paar and of course, Johnny. But the intrigue and backstabbing of
the film is not what interests us here. No, it is the almighty power of
television that makes the story so compelling.</p>

<p>In the film, television is something worth fighting for. Both a barometer and
a compass for American social mores, television helps bring the nation
together under one flag, under one host it seems. And so now we find ourselves
in the waning days of the medium. With the growing juggernaut that is
internet-based content, the idea that nearly any flat surface can instantly be
updated with original programming, television is fighting for it’s life. This
has happened before with the advent of VHS, the rental model, DVR and the
like, but the one constant has always been the daily commentary provided by
shows like “The Tonight Show”. It has weathered storms before now Conan will
have to lead it through the muck to come.</p>

<p>If you haven’t seen <em>The Late Shift you really should give it a spin. It will
make you miss the 1990s and wonder what the world would be like with Letterman
on NBC every night. For my money the world would be a whole lot funnier, but
that’s just me. Maybe in a few years, we’ll see the battle that went on to get
Conan to the top. For now, The Late Shift</em> is a great watch at this major
juncture in television history.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
