<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Movies | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/movies/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Dissolve Shutters]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/08/goodbye-the-dissolve/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-08T15:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/08/goodbye-the-dissolve</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Well this sucks. Keith Phipps, founder of <em>The Dissolve</em>, pens the movie site’s <a href="http://thedissolve.com/news/6187-the-end/">final post</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For the past two years—well, two years this Friday—it’s been our pleasure to put up this site, a site founded on and driven by a love for movies, alongside a company with passion and talent for creating thoughtful, important work. Sadly, because of the various challenges inherent in launching a freestanding website in a crowded publishing environment, financial and otherwise, today is the last day we will be doing that</p>
</blockquote>

<p><em>The Dissolve</em> was an ambitious effort. The pitch, from my outsider’s perspective, was a film site that could stay relevant while operating outside the daily grind of marketing nonsense (“leaked” set photos, regurgitated press releases, et al.). It kills me that they couldn’t make it.</p>

<p>They’ve got helluva stable of incredible film writers looking for work today. Best of luck to everyone.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Deep Web Tries to Unravel the Mystery of Silk Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/29/review-deep-web/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-29T21:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/29/review-deep-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/05/deep-web.jpg" title="Still from Deep Web" ></p>

<p>The title of actor and director Alex Winter’s engrossing new documentary, <em>Deep Web</em>, contains multitudes. It primarily refers to a place, that obscure no-man’s-land on the Internet that goes unseen by the majority of users. It also alludes to another, more literary meaning. In traditional true crime reportage, if you pull the thread, the truth will unravel. Not so in this tale, though. When you pull the thread you just find more thread; a deep web that goes on forever.</p>

<p>The film, which I saw at this year’s SXSW, follows the story of Silk Road, a notorious underground marketplace for drugs and illicit goods that was shut down in 2013 after raids by multiple federal agencies. The site existed in the “dark net,” part of the “deep web” that goes unseen by the vast majority of connected users. Think of the Internet as an iceberg. Part of it sits just above water, visible to all. This is where we shop and download music, chat with friends, and read blogs. Below the surface, though, is an expanse exponentially greater in size and almost unfathomably, well, deep. It’s a place where everything from Oxycodon to rocket launchers can be purchased anonymously. When you connect to the dark net, there is nothing that ties you to an IP address; you have no identity, no nation. It is in this notorious pocket of the unseen Internet that the film takes place.</p>

<p>The Silk Road was something of an online Souk, a cacophonous nook of the world where nothing was above haggling, and where almost every drug imaginable could be purchased as easily as ordering paper towels off Amazon. Marijuana, cocaine, heroine; all could be ordered anonymously from the comforts of home, with a package arriving inconspicuously a few days later. The site relied on Bitcoin, the popular cryptocurrency that allows for anonymized transactions (if you’re careful). Since Bitcoin, like Silk Road, is nationless, it acts like an invisible dollar, keeping every aspect of the sales on the site undetected.</p>

<p>According to the Silk Road sellers interviewed anonymously for Deep Web, the site was also a community built around libertarian ideals. The idea was to make the sale and purchase of illicit items so dead simple, there would be no need for turf wars. Some on the site believed they could end the drug war by taking violence out of the equation completely. Perhaps the most illuminating point on the topic, featured in the film, comes from a <a href="http://assange.rt.com/cypherpunks-episode-eight-full-version-pt1/">2012 episode of the Julian Assange Show</a>, a roundtable discussion web series on RT that ran throughout that year. The episode featured noted “cypherpunks,” or cryptographic activists, including Tor developer Jacob Appelbaum, who says this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Force of authority is derived from violence. One must acknowledge with cryptography, no amount of violence will ever solve a math problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In other words, since you can’t break down the door of an algorithm, violence is suddenly removed from the equation. The users of Silk Road were looking to do an end run around the drug war. In hindsight they proved unable to avoid that “force of authority” Appelbaum refers to. The government caught up with them.</p>

<p>Which brings us to Ross Ulbricht, the 30 year old whose current legal predicament lies at the heart of <em>Deep Web</em>. Earlier this year, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/05/nyregion/man-behind-silk-road-website-is-convicted-on-all-counts.html">Ulbricht was convicted of being a “digital kingpin”</a> for running Silk Road under the pseudonym Dread Pirate Roberts, or “DPR,” the protagonist from William Goldman’s The Princess Bride. Just as in the book and popular film, “Dread Pirate Roberts,” is a title, not a name, belonging to whoever holds the position at present. Even though <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/05/nyregion/man-behind-silk-road-website-is-convicted-on-all-counts.html">Ulbricht has been convicted</a>, questions still loom over his exact role in Silk Road, and whether or not he was, in fact, <em>the</em> DPR. According to one Silk Road seller interviewed in the film, the DPR account, like the literary anti-hero, did not represent a single person. It was passed down from user to user, and was maintained by multiple people as well. So was Ulbricht the kingpin, or merely the fall guy?</p>

<p>The film offers no real answers because there are still so many murky details about Silk Road. To cite just one glaring example, there’s the issue of a federal agent who infiltrated the site using the name “nob.” Nob not only communicated with whoever was running the DPR account, he was supposedly contracted by DPR to commit murder for hire. Whenever DPR asked an enemy to be rubbed out, the federal agent would send photos of a staged murder. Ulbricht was pilloried in the press when his arrest was made public for this. Not only was he accused of being the head of a massive, international drug enterprise, but he was supposedly behind brutal, mob-like murders, even though the murders never actually occurred. In fact, when federal prosecutors brought their case against Ulbricht, no murder-for-hire charges were brought against him. Ulbricht’s defenders believe this was a calculated ploy to allow him to be found guilty in the eyes of the public before bringing charges against him.</p>

<p>In late March, an even stranger twist in the tale of Silk Road was revealed. Nob, the federal agent who staged the murders, was actually a DEA agent named Carl Mark Force IV. Force, who, along with Secret Service agent Shaun W. Bridges, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/31/nyregion/silk-road-case-federal-agents-charges.html?_r=2">deposited bitcoins extracted from Silk Road in the course of the investigation into his own personal account</a>. The agents used the anonymized nature of their investigation to their advantage, keeping encrypted conversations and transactions from their superiors.</p>

<p>The version of <em>Deep Web</em> that EPIX will air this weekend will have an end title briefly explaining the stunning turn of events regarding Force and the federal corruption that came to light only after Ulbricht’s convition. The card will likely change further as Ulbricht recieved his sentence today: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/nyregion/ross-ulbricht-creator-of-silk-road-website-is-sentenced-to-life-in-prison.html">life in prison</a>.</p>

<p>Deep Web raises more questions than answers, not just about Silk Road and Ulbricht, but about what is fast becoming one of the defining struggles of our times. Are we prepared for the crypto-revolution? When everything is encrypted and anonymous, what rule of law is there? As more and more of our lives become digital, what scrutiny, government or otherwise, are we opening ourselves up to?</p>

<p>The technology that allowed Silk Road to operate so successfully also enabled corrupt government agents to extort money for personal gain. In our digital future, who are the good guys? Winter’s film exposes us to the idea that it’s getting increasingly hard to tell.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Deep Web</em> premieres on EPIX this Sunday, May 31st, at 8:00pm EDT.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The 56 Films that Opened in New York This Year Without a Review in The New York Times]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/22/times-unreviewed/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-22T21:01:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/22/times-unreviewed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/05/accidental-love.jpg" title="Accidental Love" ></p>

<p>Media folks whipped themselves into a tizzy yesterday over news that <em>The New York Times</em> is no longer reviewing every single film that opens in New York City. <a href="http://variety.com/2015/film/news/new-york-times-changes-film-review-policy-cant-guarantee-coverage-1201502465/">Variety broke the story</a> like it was the Pentagon Papers, but the grey lady’s co-chief film critic A.O. Scott <a href="https://twitter.com/aoscott/status/601532182591569921">took to Twitter</a> (and an <a href="http://blogs.indiewire.com/criticwire/ao-scott-on-why-the-new-york-times-changed-its-review-policy-20150522">interview with Indiewire</a>) to throw cold water on the idea that this was any sort of scandal.</p>

<p>As the paper of record, editorial changes at the <em>Times</em> may certainly reverberate throughout the industry. I’m not sure this change is quite the “blow to independent, documentary films” <a href="http://www.thewrap.com/new-york-times-cuts-movie-reviews-in-blow-to-independent-documentary-films/">The Wrap is making it out to be</a>, but it certainly is a change.</p>

<p>I got to wondering which films that have opened in New York City this year have not recieved a <em>Times</em> review. So I set to work (with the help of my pal <a href="https://twitter.com/norobotdiving">Clint Bishop</a>, whose programming skills probably saved me 100 hours of copy/pasting) figuring it out.</p>

<p>We took Mike D’Angelo’s invaluable <a href="http://www.panix.com/~dangelo/nymaster.html">“New York City 2015 Commercial Releases”</a> list and fed all of the titles into Metacritic, looking for links to <em>Times</em> reviews. From there, we took the remaining titles and manually searched for reviews.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I checked IMDb for alternate titles and fed those into the search as well to see if something was lost in translation.</p>

<p>I should note that this methodology is not perfect. We did not check every single reviewed film that the Metacritic script spit back out at us. Also it doesn’t account for certain inconsitincies, such as three films by Ruben Östlund, <em>The Guitar Mongoloid</em>, <em>Involuntary</em> and <em>Play</em>, recieving a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/01/14/movies/ruben-ostlunds-involuntary-play-and-the-guitar-mongoloid.html?">single omnibus review</a>.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> However I’m confident that the films listed below did not, in fact, recieve a review. I’ve got the browser history to back that up.</p>

<p>I want to clarify one more point. D’Angelo’s master list does not, to my knowledge, adhere to the same standards that the <em>Times’</em> editors do. I may well be subtracting apples from oranges here. Some of the films listed below may have had a theatrical run but would never have recieved a <em>Times</em> review in any year. But it’s my best guess for now.</p>

<p>In the end, 56 out of 380 titles released in New York City were not reviewed in <em>The New York Times</em> from January 1 to May 22.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> The majority of those titles, 24, are American. The next largest grouping, 10 films, are from India.</p>

<p>I haven’t seen a single one of these films so I can’t really speak to any common threads. For the most part they look exactly like the sort of titles Scott mentioned in his Indiewire interview: “obvious four-walls, vanity releases and movies that would have been straight-to-video releases in the past.”</p>

<p>So here they are, the 56 films that opened in New York without a review in <em>The New York Times</em>.</p>

<ul>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4409852/">12 Golden Ducks</a></em>, Matt Chow (Hong Kong)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2760800/">A Convenient Truth</a></em>, Dominick Bagnato (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2523832/">A Girl Like Her</a></em>, Amy S. Weber (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4357170/">A la mala</a></em>, Pitipol Ybarra (Mexico)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3503840/">Absolution</a></em>, Keoni Waxman (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1137470/">Accidental Love</a></em>, Stephen Greene (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2884308/">Anita B.</a></em>, Roberto Faenza (Italy)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3525346/">Bad Asses on the Bayou</a></em>, Craig Moss (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3678782/">Badlapur</a></em>, Sriram Raghavan (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4246900/">Beneath the Helmet: From High School to the Home Front</a></em>, Wayne Kopping (Israel)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3262990/">Brotherly Love</a></em>, Jamal Hill (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2876428/">Buen Día, Ramón</a></em>, Jorge Ramírez Suárez (Mexico)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4430992/">C’est Si Bon</a></em>, Kim Hyun-seok (South Korea)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2930974/">Challat of Tunis</a></em>, Kaouther Ben Hania (Tunisia)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3481000/">Chocolate City</a></em>, Jean-Claude La Marre (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2330815/">Death of a Tree</a></em>, John Martoccia (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4056738/">Do You Believe?</a></em>, Jonathan M. Gunn (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4332114/">Dolly Ki Doli</a></em>, Abhishek Dogra (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3215846/">Dreamcatcher</a></em>, Kim Longinotto (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2176722/">Ejecta</a></em>, Chad Archibald &amp; Matt Wiele (Canada)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0835775/">Electric Slide</a></em>, Tristan Patterson (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1945084/">Everly</a></em>, Joe Lynch (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3735554/">Freetown</a></em>, Garrett Batty (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3548962/">Freeway: Crack in the System</a></em>, Marc Levin (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2424988/">Gabbar Is Back</a></em>, Krish (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2302966/">I</a></em>, Shankar (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1468325/">Innenkind</a></em>, Thomas Lee (Germany)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4572856/">Let’s Get Married</a></em>, Liu Jiang (China)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2980708/">Let’s Kill Ward’s Wife</a></em>, Scott Foley (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1935302/">Monsters: Dark Continent</a></em>, Tom Green (UK)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4029998/">My Life Directed by Nicolas Winding Refn</a></em>, Liv Corfixen (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4621100/">Nanak Shah Fakir</a></em>, Sartaj Singh Pannu (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3742284/">Nh10</a></em>, Navdeep Singh (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4456982/">No Deposit</a></em>, Frank D’Angelo (Canada)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2048824/">Old Fashioned</a></em>, Rik Swartzwelder (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2976182/">Roy</a></em>, Vikramjit Singh (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4412218/">Running Man</a></em>, Hu Jia &amp; Cen Junyi (China)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3084028/">See You in Valhalla</a></em>, Jarret Tarnol (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3836958/">Shamitabh</a></em>, R. Balki (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3912040/">Sister Code</a></em>, Corey Grant (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3585004/">Snow Girl and the Dark Crystal</a></em>, Zhao Tianyu (China)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4074958/">Somewhere Only We Know</a></em>, Xu Jinglei (China)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4342506/">Son Mektup</a></em>, Özhan Eren (Turkey)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2815720/">Straight Outta Tompkins</a></em>, Zephyr Benson (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2140465/">Tanu Weds Manu Returns</a></em>, Aanand L Rai (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3398048/">Tevar</a></em>, Amit Sharma (India)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2449310/">The Business of Disease</a></em>, Sonia Barrett (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4319112/">The Con Artists</a></em>, Kim Hong-sun (South Korea)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2275671/">The King of Najayo</a></em>, Fernando Baez Mella (Dominican Republic)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4545806/">The Left Ear</a></em>, Alec Su (China)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1850397/">The Loft</a></em>, Erik Van Looy (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2962876/">The Road Within</a></em>, Gren Wells (USA)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2597718/">Three Night Stand</a></em>, Pat Kiely (Canada)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt2091427/">Treading Water</a></em>, Analeine Cal y Mayor (Mexico)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1929433/">Triumph in the Skies</a></em>, Matt Chow &amp; Wilson Yip (Hong Kong)</li>
  <li><em><a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt4415016/">Twenty</a></em>, Lee Byeong-Heon (South Korea)</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Image from Accidental Love.</em></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><code>site:nytimes.com</code> is a very helpful prefix for these sorts of searches.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>These films are each counted separately for my total film release count.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>I exempted 5 shorts compilations released in New York City: <em>Sundance Film Festival Animated Shorts</em>; <em>2015 Oscar-Nominated Animation, Documentary</em> and <em>Live-Action Shorts</em>; and <em>Remarkable Shades of Gay</em><a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Brief History of PG-13]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/04/brief-history-of-pg-13/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-04T14:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/04/brief-history-of-pg-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cute video from <a href="https://thedissolve.com/news/5588-and-now-a-very-special-video-essay-about-the-histo/"><em>The Dissolve</em></a>.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/IKpJIWGNvLc "></iframe></div></p>

<p>See also: Chris Klimek’s December 2014 <a href="http://thedissolve.com/features/movie-of-the-week/839-the-ongoing-failure-of-the-pg-13-rating/">“The ongoing failure of the PG-13 rating”</a> and, if you have a bit more time, Kirby Dick’s 2006 <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0493459"><em>This Film Is Not Yet Rated</em></a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spalding Gray, depression, and the Big Fish connection]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/24/spalding-gray-big-fish/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-24T21:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/24/spalding-gray-big-fish</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://johnaugust.com/2015/spalding-gray-depression-and-the-big-fish-connection">John August</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Real people aren’t fictional characters. They don’t follow a plot. None of us wakes up in the morning with the aim of advancing our narrative or reinforcing our core themes. Instead, we simply live, pursuing our interests while adapting to the changing circumstances around us. It’s messy. It’s unwritten.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
