<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Reviews | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/reviews/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Deep Web Tries to Unravel the Mystery of Silk Road]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/29/review-deep-web/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-29T21:34:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/29/review-deep-web</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/05/deep-web.jpg" title="Still from Deep Web" ></p>

<p>The title of actor and director Alex Winter’s engrossing new documentary, <em>Deep Web</em>, contains multitudes. It primarily refers to a place, that obscure no-man’s-land on the Internet that goes unseen by the majority of users. It also alludes to another, more literary meaning. In traditional true crime reportage, if you pull the thread, the truth will unravel. Not so in this tale, though. When you pull the thread you just find more thread; a deep web that goes on forever.</p>

<p>The film, which I saw at this year’s SXSW, follows the story of Silk Road, a notorious underground marketplace for drugs and illicit goods that was shut down in 2013 after raids by multiple federal agencies. The site existed in the “dark net,” part of the “deep web” that goes unseen by the vast majority of connected users. Think of the Internet as an iceberg. Part of it sits just above water, visible to all. This is where we shop and download music, chat with friends, and read blogs. Below the surface, though, is an expanse exponentially greater in size and almost unfathomably, well, deep. It’s a place where everything from Oxycodon to rocket launchers can be purchased anonymously. When you connect to the dark net, there is nothing that ties you to an IP address; you have no identity, no nation. It is in this notorious pocket of the unseen Internet that the film takes place.</p>

<p>The Silk Road was something of an online Souk, a cacophonous nook of the world where nothing was above haggling, and where almost every drug imaginable could be purchased as easily as ordering paper towels off Amazon. Marijuana, cocaine, heroine; all could be ordered anonymously from the comforts of home, with a package arriving inconspicuously a few days later. The site relied on Bitcoin, the popular cryptocurrency that allows for anonymized transactions (if you’re careful). Since Bitcoin, like Silk Road, is nationless, it acts like an invisible dollar, keeping every aspect of the sales on the site undetected.</p>

<p>According to the Silk Road sellers interviewed anonymously for Deep Web, the site was also a community built around libertarian ideals. The idea was to make the sale and purchase of illicit items so dead simple, there would be no need for turf wars. Some on the site believed they could end the drug war by taking violence out of the equation completely. Perhaps the most illuminating point on the topic, featured in the film, comes from a <a href="http://assange.rt.com/cypherpunks-episode-eight-full-version-pt1/">2012 episode of the Julian Assange Show</a>, a roundtable discussion web series on RT that ran throughout that year. The episode featured noted “cypherpunks,” or cryptographic activists, including Tor developer Jacob Appelbaum, who says this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Force of authority is derived from violence. One must acknowledge with cryptography, no amount of violence will ever solve a math problem.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>In other words, since you can’t break down the door of an algorithm, violence is suddenly removed from the equation. The users of Silk Road were looking to do an end run around the drug war. In hindsight they proved unable to avoid that “force of authority” Appelbaum refers to. The government caught up with them.</p>

<p>Which brings us to Ross Ulbricht, the 30 year old whose current legal predicament lies at the heart of <em>Deep Web</em>. Earlier this year, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/05/nyregion/man-behind-silk-road-website-is-convicted-on-all-counts.html">Ulbricht was convicted of being a “digital kingpin”</a> for running Silk Road under the pseudonym Dread Pirate Roberts, or “DPR,” the protagonist from William Goldman’s The Princess Bride. Just as in the book and popular film, “Dread Pirate Roberts,” is a title, not a name, belonging to whoever holds the position at present. Even though <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/02/05/nyregion/man-behind-silk-road-website-is-convicted-on-all-counts.html">Ulbricht has been convicted</a>, questions still loom over his exact role in Silk Road, and whether or not he was, in fact, <em>the</em> DPR. According to one Silk Road seller interviewed in the film, the DPR account, like the literary anti-hero, did not represent a single person. It was passed down from user to user, and was maintained by multiple people as well. So was Ulbricht the kingpin, or merely the fall guy?</p>

<p>The film offers no real answers because there are still so many murky details about Silk Road. To cite just one glaring example, there’s the issue of a federal agent who infiltrated the site using the name “nob.” Nob not only communicated with whoever was running the DPR account, he was supposedly contracted by DPR to commit murder for hire. Whenever DPR asked an enemy to be rubbed out, the federal agent would send photos of a staged murder. Ulbricht was pilloried in the press when his arrest was made public for this. Not only was he accused of being the head of a massive, international drug enterprise, but he was supposedly behind brutal, mob-like murders, even though the murders never actually occurred. In fact, when federal prosecutors brought their case against Ulbricht, no murder-for-hire charges were brought against him. Ulbricht’s defenders believe this was a calculated ploy to allow him to be found guilty in the eyes of the public before bringing charges against him.</p>

<p>In late March, an even stranger twist in the tale of Silk Road was revealed. Nob, the federal agent who staged the murders, was actually a DEA agent named Carl Mark Force IV. Force, who, along with Secret Service agent Shaun W. Bridges, <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/03/31/nyregion/silk-road-case-federal-agents-charges.html?_r=2">deposited bitcoins extracted from Silk Road in the course of the investigation into his own personal account</a>. The agents used the anonymized nature of their investigation to their advantage, keeping encrypted conversations and transactions from their superiors.</p>

<p>The version of <em>Deep Web</em> that EPIX will air this weekend will have an end title briefly explaining the stunning turn of events regarding Force and the federal corruption that came to light only after Ulbricht’s convition. The card will likely change further as Ulbricht recieved his sentence today: <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/05/30/nyregion/ross-ulbricht-creator-of-silk-road-website-is-sentenced-to-life-in-prison.html">life in prison</a>.</p>

<p>Deep Web raises more questions than answers, not just about Silk Road and Ulbricht, but about what is fast becoming one of the defining struggles of our times. Are we prepared for the crypto-revolution? When everything is encrypted and anonymous, what rule of law is there? As more and more of our lives become digital, what scrutiny, government or otherwise, are we opening ourselves up to?</p>

<p>The technology that allowed Silk Road to operate so successfully also enabled corrupt government agents to extort money for personal gain. In our digital future, who are the good guys? Winter’s film exposes us to the idea that it’s getting increasingly hard to tell.</p>

<hr />

<p><em>Deep Web</em> premieres on EPIX this Sunday, May 31st, at 8:00pm EDT.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Creep]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/03/10/review-creep/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-10T17:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/03/10/review-creep</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/03/creep.jpg" title="Creep Film Still" ></p>

<p>A found-footage mumblecore horror film basically sounds like the last thing I would want to watch. One of my goals at this year’s SXSW, though, is to leave my comfort zone a bit and see films contra what my gut tells me. So I went and saw Patrick Brice’s <em>Creep</em>, and I’m quite glad I did.</p>

<p>The film stars its two creative fathers: director Brice as Aaron, a videographer, and Mark Duplass as Josef, who, I think it’s fair to say based on the film’s own promotional material’s, fulfills the role of the film’s title.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> At the film’s opening we see Aaron heading to a cabin in the mountains where he has been hired (via Craigslist) to shoot an undisclosed subject for Josef for $1000. Two guys, a cabin, a camera and a mystery. Go.</p>

<p>So, here’s my problem with found footage films: they’re (often) based on the false premise that the camera and the eye are in equal standing when it comes to perspective. Of course, they are not. The eye can’t zoom or rack focus, has peripheral vision and works in conjunction with the brain and the rest of the body to scan an area so our field of vision is, ideally, extremely wide. We can’t see behind us, but we know how to look. The camera doesn’t.</p>

<p>Brice’s camera offers us an extremely limited perspective in order to heighten tension. This is no sin, but it also feels inorganic. We learn a bit about Aaron, over time, starting with the fact that he uses his video camera as a diary. Aaron and his camera are very much a character in the film, but there is a disconnect between the two. Why, for example, does he use only one camera both for professional filming and self-diarizing? Who is he documenting his life for? As far as we know he is a loner; no family, no friends. Does he put his diaries online? Save all the tapes in his apartment? The answer to these questions is probably “Who cares?” because Aaron’s camera is a creative conceit to move the found footage premise forward.</p>

<p>Duplass, as Josef, is a delight. He commits to the role to an incredible degree. There is no wink-wink cleverness to his performance. He rises to the challenge of presenting us with a compassionate, charismatic creep. He manipulates Aaron and the audience in equal measure. It is a deft performance from him that, frankly, makes the whole project watchable (as it should since he’s the only person on camera some 80-90% of the film). The same, I should mention, cannot be said for Brice. It would have been nice for Duplass to play off of a more seasoned actor, but the film works despite Brice’s forced and stilted performance.</p>

<p>For about the first half to two-thirds of <em>Creep</em> I basically tolerated it. The narrow perspective of Brice’s camera is used to pull off a few too many simple horror parlor tricks (actually just “Boo!” sometimes). The dialogue sort of circles around aimlessly<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> and somewhat predictably. After all, we know that Josef is a creep; we assume he will get creepier.</p>

<p>I won’t give anything away, but at the aforementioned halfway/two-thirds marker the film takes a turn with a rather clever plot device that pulled me back in and elevated the whole story. To Brice and Duplass’s credit, this turn would not function the same without the groundwork they had already laid. And so one must take the good with the bad, but the good is, in fact, <em>so</em> good that it changes the entire experience.</p>

<p><em>Creep</em> is basically a backlot horror picture. The story is simple and the execution even a little sloppy, but it all comes together, eventually, as a great, chilling little yarn. Duplass’s performance is a career milestone. The complexity he brings to Josef makes the film almost a master class in lunatic charisma. If you see it for no other reason, see it for him.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>There is one other performance, a woman’s voice from off-screen, that goes uncredited.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>This, mind you, is why I will apply the admittedly outmoded “mumblecore” moniker to the film.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW 2012 Review: Sleepwalk With Me]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/03/18/sleepwalk-with-me/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-18T11:11:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/03/18/sleepwalk-with-me</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I was late, which in SXSW parlance means <em>only</em> 45 minutes early, to the first screening here of Mike Birbiglia’s <em>Sleepwalk With Me</em>. After barely making it into the screening, I searched for a seat at the Alamo Ritz as the “no talking or texting” PSA played on screen. An usher sat me down in the section reserved for filmmakers and their friends. I quickly dropped my things between a young woman and a gentleman in a zip-up sweathshirt, scrawled out a dinner order on a slip of paper (Alamo theaters are also full-service restaurants and I was starving) and turned to head to the bathroom. The be-sweatshirted gent seemed confused that I wanted to leave the theater even though the film was unspooling, but he pulled his knees back anyway. After expelling fluids in record time, I settled back into my seat and began watching all but the first minute of this deft comedy.</p>

<p><em>Sleepwalk With Me</em> is the story of aspiring stand-up comedian Matt Pandamiglio, played by first-time director Birbiglia. He tends bar at a comedy club, taking the rare opportuities he gets to do sets when comics bail on their time slots. He has been with his girlfriend, Abby, played by Lauren Ambrose, since college and both she and Matt’s family are starting to wonder when things will move to the next, nuptial level. As his career slowly revs up, their relationship becomes strained. Oh, and Matt has a particularly rough disorder in which he sleepwalks and acts out the things he is dreaming about, often to violent effect.</p>

<p>The whole film is told in flashback from present-day Matt. This narrative conceit is lifted straight out of Woody Allen’s <em>Annie Hall</em>. The two films feel almost intertwined, as if Birbiglia wants to make his own version of it. Surpsingly, this doesn’t get in the way of the film’s own originality.</p>

<p>The director brings to the table an unfettered honesty. Pandamiglio’s comedy becomes funnier as he shares embarrassing tid bits about his personal life. The more he divulges, the more gigs he is able to book. This is a theme in films about any kind of artistic, especially comic, refinement. At some point, a comedian learns to stop being a spectator and become a raw nerve, an open book that invites his audience into his private, perhaps demented world. <em>Sleepwalk With Me</em> focuses on Matt’s move from the outside in, moving from a pew to the pulpit, as it were.</p>

<p>Much like a young(er) Woody Allen, Birbiglia is learning the tools he has at hand, sometimes with a foolhardy ambition. He executes a ridiculous long take that feels out of place when compared to the film’s otherwise straightforward form. There is an argument for its narrative necessity as it does precede a major plot point that requires spatial understanding, but it still smacks of, “Hey, what if we just did an insanely difficult shot here?” That isn’t necessarily a bad attitude to have. After all, Allen played fast and loose with cinematic conventions with <em>Annie Hall</em>.</p>

<p>I don’t want to mislead you into believing that Mike Birbiglia is the next Woody Allen. <em>Sleepwalk With Me</em> feels like the product of a student of Allen’s, one who took away the specifics of his style but not the knowledge that led him to become a modern master. There is a lot to love in this film, but it would be nothing without the filmmaker’s willingness to share a very personal story. Will Birbiglia be able to tackle someone else’s tale? We’ll see.</p>

<p>Oh, and about my missing the first few minutes of the film. When the lights came up, someone from the festival went up on stage to announce Mike Birbiglia for a Q &amp; A. The man to my right hopped out of his seat and sauntered down the aisle, walked on stage and took the mic. I sat next to Mike Birbiglia the whole time and had no idea. I was wondering why he wasn’t laughing at any of the jokes as I chuckled my head off. Sorry about running out, Mike, I really had to pee. Great work, though.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW 2012 Review: Cabin in the Woods]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/03/10/review-cabin-in-the-woods/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-10T14:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/03/10/review-cabin-in-the-woods</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>How does one even begin to review a film like <em>Cabin in the Woods</em>, whose very premise is a spoiler? That’s the question that has been bugging all the film journos (well, most of them) here at SXSW.</p>

<p>When he introduced the film at the premiere last night, producer and co-writer Joss Whedon implored the audience to enjoy the film and not tell anyone what it’s after the credits rolled. He recommended we just call it “awesome” and tell our family and friends to see it.</p>

<p>So here’s the thing: this movie <em>is</em> awesome. It manages to be a great horror film and a great comedy <em>and</em> a great something-something-lips-are-sealed at the same time. It’s increasingly rare to find a film that turns a genre on its head while still staking claim to a level of originality, but that’s exactly what we have here.</p>

<p>So what happens in Drew Goddard’s movie?</p>

<p>Everything…
Goes…
Nuts.</p>

<p>You think you know why a group of stereotypical hardbodied coeds are in for a horrific say at the eponymous cabin in the woods, but you really don’t. (One hint: Goddard wrote 9 episodes of <em>Lost</em>. <em>Cabin</em> will make you wish he wrote the final season.)</p>

<p>It feels like Goddard and Whedon knocked it out of the park on this one. This film is fun and refreshing. It’s good for the horror fan and, well, the Whedon fan in us all. I had a blast.</p>

<p>Go see it when it comes out in April and let’s talk specifics then.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: “Waves (Response to a Blog Post)”]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/29/review-waves-response-to-a-blog-post/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-29T17:02:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/29/review-waves-response-to-a-blog-post</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2012/01/waves-still.jpg" title="Still from “Waves (Response to a Blog Post)”" ></p>

<p>I’d like to talk about Daniel Anderson’s short video essay, “Waves (Response to a Blog Post),” which he released a week ago on Vimeo. First, let’s take a look at it, shall we?</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/35552232?portrait=0" width="551" height="413" frameborder="0" webkitAllowFullScreen mozallowfullscreen allowFullScreen></iframe>

<p>I first watched this film on my television, comfortably sitting on my couch. I tensed up almost immediately, succumbing to a kind of claustrophobia. This digital work, this “screencast,” is something I relate to viscerally. As a writer and, particularly, as a blogger, “Waves” illustrates the work I do on computers in a way I hadn’t conceived of before. It’s…frightening.</p>

<p>Here is Mr. Anderson’s description of the film:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is my response to the blog posting, The Digital Humanities and the Transcending of Mortality. See the mantra: you don’t study digital composing, you perform it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The post in question was published on January 9 by <a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/09/the-digital-humanities-and-the-transcending-of-mortality/">Stanley Fish at the New York Times</a>. In it he discusses scholarship in the digital age and why he has opted to reframe his “column” as a “blog.” He ends his piece with a question or, perhaps, a challenge:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The pertinent challenge to this burgeoning field has been issued by one of its pioneer members, Jerome McGann of the University of Virginia. “The general field of humanities education and scholarship will not take up the use of digital technology in any significant way until one can clearly demonstrate that these tools have important contributions to make to the exploration and explanation of aesthetic works” (“<a href="http://www.ivanhoegame.org/">Ivanhoe Game</a> Summary,” 2002). What might those contributions be? Are they forthcoming? These are the questions I shall take up in the next column, oops, I mean blog.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>“Waves” appears to be the answer to that loaded question. Consider what the film is: it’s a window onto the desktop of a scholar who is mashing up and remixing the work of others in almost every conceivable way. The text, the music, the videos, the applications and even the graphical interface itself are wholly unoriginal, conceived not by the filmmaker but by other artists. Any one of us could replicate the work that Anderson performs in his film, but why would we?</p>

<p>Taking it further, we can talk about the way that Anderson released this work into the world. It was uploaded to Vimeo, where many would be watching it on a computer screen. The experience changes if you watch it on a tablet or on a television; it is completely different if you watch it windowed or fullscreen; and the experience of watching this either on a Mac or a Windows machine alters the viewer’s perspective even further. The portal through which we view the work completely changes the experience. If the challenge is that scholarship will ignore digital technology “until one can clearly demonstrate that these tools have important contributions to make to the exploration and explanation of aesthetic works,” then I’d say that burden has been met.</p>

<p>I spend a great deal of time in front of screens. When I’m not in front of a computer, I am usually watching television or tapping away on my iPad or iPhone. Digital tools surround me because I like them and they enhance the way I work and live. No matter what the screen, I am always aware of my surroundings. The coins and papers on my desk, the subway train on which I clack away on my iPad, the park from which I am tweeting, etc. The screencast, however, disembodies the act of making a digital work. Anderson’s film feels corpse-like, a computer almost running itself for its own amusement and gains. Like I said, it is frightening, but I can’t look away.</p>

<p>According to his <a href="http://iamdananderson.net/">Web site</a>, Daniel Anderson is an English professor at the University of North Carolina where he studies “new media composing and instructional technology.” His aim here may have been academic, but I would argue that the outcome is entirely cinematic. There are a severe amount of interpretations that “Waves” is open to which only adds to the joy of experiencing it. Plop ten people down in front of this film and you’ll get at least ten different explanations, maybe more. Now that’s cinema.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
