<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Contest | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/contest/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candler Contest: Autographed Book Giveaway!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/24/candler-contest-autographed-book-giveaway/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-24T08:59:50+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/24/candler-contest-autographed-book-giveaway</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2009/06/sc1.jpg" alt="Sooner Cinema Cover" />Hold onto your hats folks, it’s time for the
first ever candler giveaway. Readers, you have been very good to me this
month, so it’s time to give something back. After last month’s <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/22/starting-out-in-film-now-what/">Starting Out
In Film</a>
post gained some traction thanks to some linkage from the excellent blog <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/17/full-deadcenter-
coverage/">Self
Reliant Film</a>, you came back for more in June. Many of you were intrigued by my
<a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/05/google-
wave-for-filmmakers-a-concept/">Google Wave for Filmmakers</a> post, but there is no question that above all
else you showed up for <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/17/full-deadcenter-coverage/">my coverage of the deadCENTER Film
Festival</a>. In
fact, Oklahoma can now lay claim to the candler blog’s second highest
readership in the U.S. Thanks!</p>

<p>Now to the contest. While I was in Oklahoma City, I popped into the <a href="http://www.fullcirclebooks.com/">Full
Circle Book Store</a>, an incredible local find,
for a signing of a new collection of essays, <a href="http://www.fortysixthstarpress.com/?page_id=265&amp;category=1&amp;product
_id=5">Sooner Cinema: Oklahoma Goes to
the Movies</a>. I’ve only just started to read it and it is fascinating. The authors
of this book take an interesting look at the cinematic history of the Sooner
State. Trust me, this is the only book of its kind. If you are fascinated by
local cinema, American history, or just a new take on American filmmaking,
this will be a nice book for your collection.</p>

<p><strong>I have one copy to give away and it is autographed by five of the authors.</strong> The rules are simple, leave a comment on this post with a legitimate e-mail address. That’s it! I don’t care if you use an alias and I will not be making a mailing list out of this data, I simply need your e-mail to contact you if you win. Please leave only one comment on any topic. Feel free to share your favorite film or director, suggestion for the candler, whatever you want to write. Keep it clean, dirty comments won’t get posted and are ineligible. You may enter up until 12:00am Thursday July 9th, as in midnight on Wednesday July 8th, two weeks from today. Best of luck to all!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
