<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fitness | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/fitness/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Day One as Running Diary]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/20/day-one-running/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-20T19:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/20/day-one-running</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/year-pics.jpg" title="Jon’s Face" ></p>

<p>When I wrote about <a href="http://www.eater.com/2015/7/20/9003323/paul-rudd-works-baskin-robbins-ant-man-marvel">running with my Apple Watch</a> two weeks ago, I mentioned in a footnote that “entering run notes into <a href="http://dayoneapp.com/" title="Day One">Day One</a>” was a key reason I preferred keeping my phone on me. I’d like to elaborate on that just a small bit.</p>

<p>In case you don’t know, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/day-one-journal-notes-diary/id421706526?mt=8&amp;at=11l5Fb">Day One</a> is a journaling app for iOS and Mac. You can file your writings by date, tag posts, add a photo and even add numerous bits of metadata to each piece. Your location, the weather, what music you’re listening to and whether or not you were walking, driving or sitting still can all be attached to each entry. It’s like your own private little blog (it can even become a <a href="http://dayoneapp.com/publish/">public blog</a> if you like).<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>While I have done plenty of writing in Day One, lately I tend to do most of my writing either in a <a href="http://fieldnotesbrand.com">Field Notes memo book</a> or in <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ulysses/id623795237?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Ulysses</a> on my Mac. But Day One is still one of my most used apps. I’ve been using it for over a year<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> as a running diary. Every time I run I create an entry with a photo (usually a selfie) and a few words about how I felt during the run. I always add the tag “Running” to these so I can keep track.</p>

<p>Now, <a href="http://runkeeper.com">RunKeeper</a> can hold all of this information pretty well too. Each run can have a photo and a note attached to it. I tend to upload photos to RunKeeper as well, and will sometimes add a short note. The truth is that, while RunKeeper does an incredible job displaying and tracking data related to exercise, it’s not great at displaying anything personal. It’s a colder app, which is fitting since it needs to be as reliable as a stopwatch. But for storing and retrieving how running makes me <em>feel</em> I need something more personal, more beautiful. Day One fits the bill.</p>

<p>Here are screen grabs of what my Day One “Timeline” (left) and “Photos” (right) views look like today.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/day-one-running-shots.jpg" title="Inside Day One" ></p>

<p>Somewhere around the end of my run, I take a photo of myself. I may use filters in <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/vsco-cam/id588013838?mt=8&amp;at=11l5Fb">VSCO Cam</a>, but more often I’ve been enjoying Apple’s built-in photo filters. As I cool down I create a new Day One photo entry and tap out a few notes.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> I may include my split times, or I may just talk about how I feel and what in my life may have caused the run to go the way it did (e.g. too little sleep, a heavy meal). Sometimes it has almost nothing to do with running, as when I spotted a dog that had ventured out of his owner’s yard and I helped him get back home.</p>

<p>This is where Day One really shines over something like RunKeeper. I run for many reasons; going faster and further are only a small part of that. Running is now part of my routine. It’s part of (most of) my days. There is a macro view of the thoughts I have while running and what the long-term effects it has on my health and demeanor that Day One allows me to track. No other tool comes close.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>When I get the urge to tweet something that I really shouldn’t, I type it into Day One and tag it as “Untweet.” I like to think this has kept me out of more than a few shouting matches.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>First running entry: November 15, 2013.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Day One also offers an excellent Watch app that allows me to pre-populate a post with a “Running” tag and the most recent photo. I don’t really use this though as I’m so used to actually typing out the entry as I create it.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Running With My Apple Watch]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/07/running-with-apple-watch/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-07T22:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/07/running-with-apple-watch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/move-streak.png" title="Move Streak" ></p>

<p>From the moment I first strapped on my Apple Watch, I’ve been diligent to fill all three rings in the Activity app. Though it may seem silly, it felt <em>great</em> when I got the below badge for filling them all every day in the month of June.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/june-achievement-image.jpg" title="June 2015 Achievement Badge" ></p>

<p>I still use <a href="http://runkeeper.com">RunKeeper</a>, which I’ve used to track my runs since October 2013. Rifling through my old running stats, I can see that I’ve gone through quite a few workout spurts over the years. The regimen I’ve kept up these last two months and change is by far my most consistent fitness effort to date.</p>

<p>And it’s working!</p>

<p>Since May I’ve shaved about 90 seconds off my first mile time and 6 pounds off my gut.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> This is <em>after</em> I spent a little over a year trying to lose all the weight I put on eating my way through Texas after I first moved here.</p>

<p>So, is this all because of Apple Watch? I don’t know. Will it last? Who knows. But I can tell you personally that I really, <em>really</em> like my Apple Watch, with this latest burst of fitness perseverance being my most illustrative reason.</p>

<p>I still always run with my iPhone. For one, Apple’s Workout app doesn’t let you retrieve split timings, so I need to rely on RunKeeper for that. Once they add splits I’ll most likely be done with RunKeeper. (Right now I use both apps to track my runs.)</p>

<p>The other, bigger reason I run with my phone is for safety’s sake. It allows me to call for help if I need it and provides emergency contacts for others to help me. While I appreciate the ability to run with only my Apple Watch, I don’t see myself heading out without my iPhone any time soon.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<h3 id="some-apple-watch-workout-tips--tricks">Some Apple Watch Workout Tips &amp; Tricks</h3>

<p>Here are a few things I’ve learned from running with the Apple Watch. Some of these may be obvious or known, but they weren’t to me at first. So I thought I’d share them.</p>

<ol>
  <li>6 Second Start
    <ul>
      <li>It takes 6 seconds from the moment you tap “Start” on a workout to the time your Watch actually starts tracking the workout</li>
      <li>If you tap the screen after you hit “Start” it will end the countdown and go right into tracking</li>
      <li>I have a 10 second countdown on RunKeeper runs, which gives me a little leeway to sync RunKeeper and Workout</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Elapsed Time, Distance and Heart Rate on One Screen
    <ul>
      <li>Here’s what I like to see on my watch during a run:
 <img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/watch-setup-sample.jpg" title="Watch Workout Sample" ></li>
      <li>Set a distance goal so the middle numbers on the Watch screen will be your mileage</li>
      <li>Swipe the bottom metric all the way to the right to get your live heart rate during your run</li>
      <li>Tap the clock in the top of the workout screen to get your elapsed time to display there</li>
      <li>If you need to know the time, I find it’s easier to just switch back to the watch face (double tap the crown) than cycle through your options on the line</li>
      <li>For reference, here are the options for each row on the workout screen in the order you can cycle through them
        <ul>
          <li>Top row: Current Time, Pace or Elapsed Time</li>
          <li>Middle row displays your goal, either: Calories, Time or Distance. An Open workout will display the elapsed time</li>
          <li>Bottom row: Elapsed Time, Pace, Distance, Calories, Heart Rate</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Taking the Watch Off Mid-Workout Isn’t All That Bad
    <ul>
      <li>If you want to wipe some sweat out from under the heart rate sensor, just take the watch off to wipe it</li>
      <li>You can pause your run if you want, but it will work and continue timing even if you don’t</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>You Can’t Come Back From Accidentally Ending a Workout</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>If you accidentally end your workout instead of pausing it, there’s nothing you can do</li>
      <li>Just save the workout and start another one where you left off</li>
      <li>I learned this the hard way when I tried pausing a run to clean the heart rate sensor, which is also how I learned how to do that without pausing (see above)</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>That’s all I can think of for now. Apple’s Workout app is pretty rudimentary for now. I really hope it gets better because it’s the best Watch running app available today. I haven’t mentioned RunKeeper’s Watch app because it’s not so great yet. The text is hard to read while you’re running, and it’s missing some key metrics, namely heart rate. When watchOS 2 debuts later this year I’m sure RunKeeper will have a chance to give Apple a run for its money…or maybe the other way around.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Give or take on both counts. It <em>was</em> just a holiday weekend, you know…<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Other reasons include: camera, streaming music (hello, Apple Music and Beats 1), listening to podcasts, entering run notes into <a href="http://dayoneapp.com">Day One</a> and probably a dozen others I can’t think of right now.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
