<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Criticism | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/criticism/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[This 1926 Film Review Sounds Familiar]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/19/the-sea-beast/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-19T20:50:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/19/the-sea-beast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/02/the-screen.jpg" title="The Screen Headline" ></p>

<p>You really should be following <em>The New York Times’</em> tumblog, <a href="http://livelymorgue.tumblr.com">The Lively Morgue</a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Every few days they publish photos from the paper’s massive collection.</p>

<p>This week saw the surfacing of <a href="http://livelymorgue.tumblr.com/post/111376489978/oct-1-1925-capt-ahab-ceeley-played-by-john">a photo of John Barrymore</a> on the set of the 1926 silent <em>Moby-Dick</em> adaptation, <em>The Sea Beast</em>. The film is not readily available save for <a href="http://youtu.be/Uv2Fji7njow">a few clips on YouTube</a><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> (there is a single DVD copy going for $150 on <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B001LIM0SU/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=B001LIM0SU&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thecandlerblo-20&amp;linkId=DNWG3BRIOY5U26S4">Amazon</a>). Lucky for us, though, the <a href="http://timesmachine.nytimes.com/timesmachine/1926/01/16/98845052.html?pageNumber=8"><em>Times’</em> review survives</a>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/02/barrymore.jpg" title="John Barrymore in The Sea Monster" ></p>

<p><sup>Photo: The New York Times</sup></p>

<p>This is the first I’ve ever read the criticism of <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mordaunt_Hall">Mordaunt Hall</a>. The first thing that stands out to me is the lasting value of published criticism. <em>The Sea Beast</em>, some ninety-years old, may not survive intact, but Hall’s 1926 experience of it is as vibrant today as it was when it was originally published.</p>

<p>There are a few notable things about Hall’s review. By 1926 cinema had a working language, but some of the terminology was still up for grabs. Hall refers to the film as “the picturization of ‘Moby Dick,’” for example. Today we say adaptation, which perhaps tempers expectations of textual consistency.</p>

<p>“Picturization” feels so dated because the movies have since come into their own. Time was a book could be, theoretically, transplanted onto the screen. Of course, that was never accurate (and I’m overstating things a bit here), but it goes to show the ways in which how we talk about movies has changed over the years.</p>

<p>Hall is impressed by the photography, but not the editing:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The turbulent seas and the sights aboard the vessel are particularly well pictured, but the constant glimpses of a miniature to show the vessel plunging through the angry water are shown too frequently. In fact Millard Webb, who directed this production, often spars for suspense and misses it, and frequently loses his dramatic value by long close-ups, first of one person and then of another. For this reason the production drags quite a good deal.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It looks good, but it’s boring.</p>

<p>I also love that the modern complaint, “too much CGI,” is almost as old as the medium, in a different context of course. Here’s Hall:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There are scenes supposed to be in New Bedford in 1840, and others in Java. It would have been preferable if [director Millard] Webb had decided to forego the use of a property moon in one setting, as it is by no means realistic, any more than some of the backdrops.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s unendingly fascinating to me that, at this juncture in film history, a critic would call for more realism. I’m not sure I even understand Hall’s complaint. The moon (which was likely impossible to expose for alongside actors; it’s not much easier today for that matter) looks fake: so what?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is a good production and one which contains much interest, but it is not a great photoplay.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Sounds like a summer blockbuster.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I’ve <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/09/two-cameras-and-a-cigarette/">mentioned them before</a>.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>The linked video appears to be a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Super_8_film#Packaged_movies">condensed home movie edition</a> of the film; <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0017354/">IMDb pegs <em>The Sea Beast’s</em> run time</a> at 136 minutes.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>You must be a <em>Times</em> subscriber to see more than the abstract.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Primer on Not Being a Music Hater]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/16/a-lot-of-listening/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T19:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/16/a-lot-of-listening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great piece by <a href="https://medium.com/@sixfoot6/getting-out-of-the-woods-a-primer-on-not-being-a-music-hater-fc4c46d4dde0">Ryan Gantz</a> on music listening that I think aptly applies to watching movies:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You should feel free to listen to whatever music <strong>speaks</strong> to you. I do.</p>

  <p>But the hard thing about music (and all types of art) is that <strong>speak</strong> can mean something different for every genre, artist, and album. The emotional, tonal, and verbal vocabulary of heavy metal is almost nothing like the vocabulary of jazz. The intention and cultural contexts differ. The listening experience goals for fans of hip-hop may be at odds with what a classical music-lover wants out of a great symphony.</p>

  <p>And that means that it often requires intellectual/emotional openness and very close listening (or, like, dancing) to understand what a piece of music is getting at, what language it’s speaking, what feelings it wants to evoke—even who its target audience might be—before we can fairly judge what’s successful or unsuccessful about it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Gantz articulates something I try to keep in mind whenever I watch a new film, especially one that exists well outside of my comfort zone.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://waxy.org/links/archive/2014/10/index.shtml">Waxy</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[“Do not let studios make you foot soldiers”]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/06/13/ken-lowerys-tweets/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T19:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/06/13/ken-lowerys-tweets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This afternoon, writer <a href="http://cargocollective.com/kenlowery">Ken Lowery</a> took to Twitter to vent a bit about movie criticism and the reliance on box office as a conversation point. It’s an insightful read.</p>

<p>I’ve compiled his tweets over at <a href="http://storify.com/poritsky/ken-lowery-on-box-office">Storify</a> and organized them below (with permission). The sentences are linked to corresponding tweets. Taken together, they tell the story of the perversion of criticism and fandom into formidable marketing tools. It makes for a great read.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345237606415601664">For God’s Sake Burn Down Rotten Tomatoes</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345238568941260800">I think you guys know I love movie criticism. I really do. I take it seriously and value arts criticism in general as absolutely necessary.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345238640009551872">But Rotten Tomatoes is the fucking pits. Find critics you like and/or trust (for variable definitions of “trust”); read them; be content.</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345238692400599040">It’s not a game. It’s not a race. Do not let studios make you foot soldiers in their dick-measuring wars.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345238921803866113">Box office does not matter. Aggregate percentages and star ratings – and no critic worth their salt likes those things – do not matter.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239142076141568">What did it do to you? That is what matters.</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239350709198848">I will hate Harry Knowles forever because he was INSTRUMENTAL in getting sentimental nerds turned into street teams for movie PR machines.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239496792612865">Why the FUCK should we care about opening weekend B.O.? And yet we do. We act like we’re shareholders and not just another fucking mark.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239613461381120">You didn’t get brought onto the team when you figured out per-screen averages, folks. You got BOUGHT.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239655882579968">And usually all it took was some cool little geegaws with a fucking logo on ‘em.</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239819770789889">I get it – getting into the guts of why something moved you how it did is hard work, and arguments about quantities are so much easier.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239918064316416">We can theorize and bullshit about same-day foreign premieres or whatever-the-balls because it’s something like hard data.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239959948652544">(It isn’t, really, but it FEELS like hard data, which makes it easier to compare A to B.)</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345239981574475776">I swear to you: NONE OF THAT MATTERS.</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345240048653975552">My personal metric for caring about box office is “do people I like get to keep doing what they want to do?” And that is it.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345240074901929984">To toot my own horn, I think that’s a pretty damn good metric.</a></p>

  <p><a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345240422383239168">OK, lots of eloquent messages rolling in but I just got called into a meeting. Brb.</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/kenlowery/status/345240703317712896">Just remember: This is part of the overall plan to make you care more about PRODUCT than about the PEOPLE MAKING IT. This is not an accident</a></p>
</blockquote>

<p>(h/t <a href="https://twitter.com/thejewishdream/">Rafi</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Criticism for Critics]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/06/13/criticism-for-critics/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-13T15:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/06/13/criticism-for-critics</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/06/mos-mutes.png" title="Mute Filters" ></p>

<p>At exactly 10pm CDT this past Monday, the review embargo for <em>Man of Steel</em> was lifted, allowing any site to publish articles about the film a full 73 hours before the public at large would be able to see it. This feels a bit early to me, <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> though certainly not the earliest of late.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup></p>

<p>Most of the people I follow on Twitter (or on any network) are critics. I love reading their snap reactions to films, following the links to interesting things they share and generally basking in the wash of cinematic writings available to us at this unique moment in the history of information. But by 10:05pm on Monday I’d had enough. The moment the embargo lifted a number of people I follow unleashed their reviews and the conversation amongst those who had seen the film began. At 10:17pm I switched Twitter clients to <a href="http://tapbots.com/software/tweetbot/">Tweetbot</a> (from my preferred <a href="http://twitterrific.com/ios">Twitterrific</a>) so I could set up <a href="https://twitter.com/poritsky/status/344292566289768448">search filters</a> to excise <em>Man of Steel</em> tweets from my timeline.</p>

<p>I feel confident saying that today, in the US at least, there are more self-identifying (and duly credentialed) film critics and journalists than at any point in the history of the movies.  Criticism isn’t dying by any stretch, in fact it’s flourishing. Yet it feels like, as a community, we are insulating ourselves from the rest of the world. A lot of the criticism I see feels as though it is aimed at the same crowd that produces it. Critics writing for critics; the rest of the world can watch if they like.</p>

<p>When the <em>Man of Steel</em> embargo lifted, suddenly hundreds (thousands?) of people privy to advance screenings were all in the same place (Twitter) at the same time, ready to discuss it. Personally, I’m not worried about spotting a spoiler. I just don’t like being on the outside of a conversation of a film I won’t be seeing the film until it opens. I could barely make it 5 minutes on Twitter without getting burned out of hearing about it. And I’m part of this community. I can only imagine what it’s like for someone else, on the outside looking in.</p>

<p>Is it any wonder that film critics have less sway on audiences than ever before, that binary watchdogs like Rotten Tomatoes have become the barometers of quality for the masses? The more critics write for themselves the more they cut themselves off from the rest of the world.  But the community is so big now, who cares? Who needs non-critics in a world where your closest friends have already seen the movie you want to talk about 73 hours before the plebes even can?</p>

<p>A word on embargoes. Press screenings come with a caveat: journalists can’t write about the film they’ve seen until a set date a time. Publicists and marketers set when the embargo will lift. The consequence for publishing early is burning the bridge with the studio and/or publicist that set the embargo. In general they’re a mostly reasonable thing that allows all outlets to operate on an even playing field, but make no mistake: embargoes are a marketing tool devised to ensure maximum press saturation.</p>

<p>Back in 2011, when <em>New Yorker</em> critic David Denby broke an embargo by publishing his <em>The Girl With The Dragon Tattoo</em> review two weeks early, producer Scott Rudin told him <a href="http://blogs.indiewire.com/theplaylist/exclusive-scott-rudin-replies-to-david-denbys-embargo-break-of-dragon-tattoo-in-the-new-yorker">in an email</a> he “very badly damaged” the film. What he meant was that Denby upended Sony’s carefully timed marketing campaign. An embargo is set so that no one is talking about your film before the studio wants them to, but there is nothing that says you have to publish the moment the embargo lifts.</p>

<p>Which brings us to 10pm CDT, Monday June 10, 2013, when my feed was firebombed with <em>Man of Steel</em> reviews.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> As of this writing (61 hours after the embargo lifted), the <em>New York Times</em>, which in my opinion retains one of the steadiest hands in the business of film criticism, is yet to publish a review of the film. I doubt it’s because one of their critics hasn’t written one. They publish reviews the night before a film’s New York or nationwide release; a studio’s preference doesn’t change the schedule.</p>

<p>Of course, the <em>Times</em> doesn’t need to elbow for page-views; the readers actually come for the criticism. Perhaps there’s a lesson there.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I grew up reading reviews in the newspaper on Fridays, then later at 9pm sharp Thursday evenings on the Web. This always felt like enough lead time for me, but times change.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><em>Star Trek Into Darkness</em> reviews came out some two weeks before its US release because it opened earlier overseas.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>And the awkward touting of the word count of some folks’ reviews.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Workflows, Intentionality and Authorship]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/02/01/workflows-and-intentionality/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-01T14:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/02/01/workflows-and-intentionality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/02/boss-of-it-all.jpg" title="Boss of it All" ></p>

<p>Ignatiy Vishnevetsky is one of the more thoughtful critics working today, but his latest piece for MUBI’s Notebook, “<a href="http://mubi.com/notebook/posts/what-is-the-21st-century-revising-the-dictionary">What is the 21st Century?: Revising the Dictionary</a>,” throws me for a loop. In it he attempts to introduce “workflow” in the critical lexicon, suggesting that if critics and cinephiles knew more about the filmmaking process they would be better equipped to pass judgement on movies.</p>

<p>I agree with this assertion to a point, but Vishnevetsky goes much further:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of the biggest problems facing film criticism and film culture is that that there is often very little relationship between how movies are written about and how they’re actually made. Film is a medium that is inextricably linked to technology, but the language we use to talk about and evaluate films is by-and-large the language of antique or dying technologies or of environments (such as the old studio system, with its clear divisions of filmmaking labor) that no longer exist. While much of the old critical / cinephilic vocabulary—mise en scène, montage, etc.—still works, it’s often not enough.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is one of the biggest problems facing film culture? I don’t see it, least of all because I don’t think it’s an <em>actual</em> deficiency.</p>

<p>For example, how much ink was spilled, how many bits were deployed discussing Tom Hooper’s decision to record the actors’ singing live on set in his adaptation of <em>Les Misérables</em>? How many reviews mentioned this little nugget of production workflow detail? The entire conversation surrounding the film, I would argue, was predicated on this creative decision.</p>

<p>Or Peter Jackson’s use of 48 frames-per-second in <em>The Hobbit: An Unexpected Journey</em> at. The critical responses that ignore that technological conceit are few and far between. So I would first argue that Vishnevetsky’s thesis is flawed; he’s saying that critics don’t do something they clearly already do.</p>

<p>Still, the workflows he mentions, those of David Fincher and Steven Soderbergh, <em>do</em> often go overlooked in reviews:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Modern film styles are the products of workflows. David Fincher’s <em>The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo</em>, for instance, was widely noted in the film tech sector for its innovative workflow. Footage was shot in 5K with a 2.1 aspect ratio but finished in 4k with a 2.4 aspect ratio. Only 70% of each shot frame was used in the finished film; this meant that Fincher could revise every shot—reframing, altering the speed of camera movements, adding zooms—during editing without any loss of image quality.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Professionally I am intrigued by these sorts of workflows. By day I work in post-production, and my curiosity is always piqued by any sort of advancement. I am smack in the middle of the film tech sector and I wish more directors would improve their workflows to Fincher/Soderbergh levels. It would make my job easier. (Or, as Vishnevetsky also points out, redundant.)</p>

<p>But I take that hat off when I go to watch or review a movie. Why? Because it’s utterly boring. All that’s described above is that Fincher did repositions on his footage, a decades-old technique that predates digital technology. Even the Academy Standard aspect ratio of 1.85:1 is achieved by lopping off the top and bottom of the picture. Kubrick, famously, shot a number of his films utilizing the entire 35mm frame, allowing for multiple projected aspect ratios.</p>

<p>So yes, Fincher took advantage of modern tools, but I don’t see how that should affect how I watch a film. Vishnevetsky:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>What does this mean for critics, cinephiles, and other people who want to talk about movies? It’s still possible to note <em>The Girl with the Dragon Tattoo’s</em> mise en scène or [Steven Soderbergh’s] <em>Side Effects’</em> narrative structure—that hasn’t changed. What has changed is the notion of environment and intent.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Has it, though? Vishnevetsky echoes this again in his conclusion:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Workflow-related processes like HDRx<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> upset old orders; what happens to the idea of the shot when the shot no longer has integrity—that is, when an image doesn’t represent a record of something but is instead a seamless composite of two sets of digital data? The only way to build a critical framework for workflow, it seems, is to exercise doubt while also assuming that everything has the potential for authorship and intent.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>What is the difference between new HDRx technologies and matte paintings of old which accomplish nearly the same effect? In a world where characters are created on a CPU, and have been for two decades, what difference does a workflow make, or rather how can it actually influence the way you watch a film? I do not understand Vishnevetsky’s call to “exercise doubt.” Doubt what? To what end?</p>

<p>The final bit though, “assuming that everything has the potential for authorship and intent,” is dead right and crucial to modern criticism. In fact, I’d counter that a lack of understanding of the concept of intentionality is “one of the biggest problems facing film criticism and film culture.”</p>

<p>It is my strong belief that critics <em>must</em> assume that what they are seeing on screen is the intended work of the author. Anything less, any doubt cast on the simple truth of intentionality, sells film culture short.</p>

<p>A quick story.</p>

<p>After the premiere of his film, <em>Girl Walks Into A Bar</em>, at SXSW 2011, director Sebastián Gutiérrez took the stage for the usual post-screening Q &amp; A. First, though, he had something to tell the audience. He extolled the Alamo Drafthouse as one of his favorite movie theater chains and then complained that the picture we had just seen was a bit too dark. It looked better while he was editing it and he wished we could have seen it that way.</p>

<p>Here’s the thing: the film we saw, as we saw it, was the truth. The images he saw at his editing bay were the fantasy. Why? Because as viewers we can assume nothing less than intentionality when images flicker on screen. If the filmmaker weren’t in the house, would anyone have known the images were “wrong” according to his vision?</p>

<p>Moreover, putting my post hat back on, one color corrects images differently for the Web than one does for theatrical projection. Gutiérrez said the film had “leaked” on YouTube that night. It was <em>never</em> his intention for this to be the canonical screening of the film. Too bad for him.</p>

<p>One more quick story.</p>

<p>At SXSW last year<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> I met a young woman waiting in line for a film. She asked what brought me to the festival and I told her I was a film critic. She bristled. “Oh, one of the bad guys.” I laughed and asked her what she meant. She went on and on to me (a stranger!) about how critics over-intellectualize movies and have no concept of how hard it is to actually make them.</p>

<p>This is the Kevin Smith argument, and it is legion. “<a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/07/18/not-even-supposed-to-be-here-today/">You could either sit around and be entertained, or you could go out and try to be entertaining.</a>” Film critics are the enemy because they never worked a day in their life, or some such nonsense.</p>

<p>It feels like Vishnevetsky’s argument that critics be more mindful of workflows stems from the same gland that causes people to dismiss critics as “bad guys.” If only critics knew the process, if only they knew how <em>hard</em> it is to make a movie, their responses to cinema would be more interesting, more useful.</p>

<p>Perhaps. Or perhaps they will start undermining intentionality by cutting filmmakers a break for the nastiest bits of their workflows.</p>

<p>I’d be remiss if I didn’t mention Lars Von Trier’s <em>The Boss of it All</em>. Here’s what I <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/21/von-trier-as-trickster-cannes-you-believe-it/">said about it back in 2009</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>For 2006’s <em>The Boss of it All</em>, the acclaimed director utilized a system dubbed “Automavision”. Basically, he shot the film only from wider angles, or all establishing shots, and allowed a computer randomly tilt, pan, or zoom. Watching the film, you would never know this. It feels wholly organic, intentional. In fact, for Mr. Von Trier, it seems almost tame.[…]</p>

  <p>Giving control over to a machine, he is simultaneously removing himself as creative controller and, amazingly, further pressing his status as provocateur by drawing attention to his shrunken role.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Von Trier wanted the audience to know of Automavision’s presence, to know the methodology behind the haphazard visuals accompanying his workplace farce. It certainly colors my view of the film (I’m talking about it years later, aren’t I?) but when watching the film it was the furthest thing from my mind. I was wrapped up in the story and, yes, grappling with the oddball camera placements. But did it matter that a computer was to blame/laud? I don’t think so.</p>

<p>How filmmakers create their art is something that will always be of interest to me both personally and professionally, but that information does not influence how I judge the work itself. If it did, I’d love everything. I’d be less critical.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>HDRx is a new mode that allows modern Red cameras to shoot multiple exposures of the same shot at once, then blend them together in post-production to create a shot with high dynamic range. He describes this earlier in the article. <a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>That’s where most of my stories come from.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
