<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Candlercasts | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/candlercasts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #19: Tinkering with Evan Glodell]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/07/26/candlercast-19-tinkering-with-evan-glodell/"/>
    <updated>2011-07-26T16:26:47+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/07/26/candlercast-19-tinkering-with-evan-glodell</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I just barely made it to a screening of <em>Bellflower</em> at SXSW this past year,
but I was <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/03/15/sxsw-11
-review-bellflower/">instantly taken</a> by its apocalyptic charm. For a film that is about the
bitterness of love lost, it has a surprising amount of life, a certain demonic
spring in its step. That melange of emotions comes from the film’s writer,
director and star, Evan Glodell.</p>

<p>Woodrow, the character Evan plays in his film, and best pal Aiden (Tyler
Dawson) are tinkerers, forever trying to build bigger and more explosive
contraptions. The film itself is something of a handmade experiment. Evan and
his team built their cameras by putting vintage bellows systems together with
cutting edge digital sensors, giving <em>Bellflower</em> a look reminiscient of,
well, nothing else I’ve seen. It is at once vintage yet modern, aged yet
entirely new.</p>

<p>I had the opportunity to speak with Evan recently about <em>Bellflower</em> and the
work that inspires him. Give a listen and check out the film when it hits
theaters this summer.</p>

<p>[podcast]http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2011/07/candlercast-19
-evan-glodell.mp3[/podcast]</p>

<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/10/candlercast-18-jeff-malmberg.mp3">Right-Click to Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTun
es</a></p>

<p>Bellflower <em>opens in New York and Los Angeles on Auguest 5th. For more
information, check out the film’s <a href="http://www.bellflower-
themovie.com">official site</a>.</em></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #18: A Full Scale Chat with Jeff Malmberg]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/10/08/candlercast-18-a-full-scale-chat-with-jeff-malmberg/"/>
    <updated>2010-10-08T13:17:16+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/10/08/candlercast-18-a-full-scale-chat-with-jeff-malmberg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/marwencol_10.jpg" title="Jeff Malmberg and Mark Hogancamp of Marwencol" ></p>

<p>If you haven’t heard of the film <em>Marwencol</em> yet, it’s time to perk up. You can <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/14/sxsw-review-marwencol/">read my review from this year’s SXSW</a> to become fully acclimated. The documentary, which follows Mark Hogancamp and his 1/6th scale Belgian village whose name is the same as the film, has been winding its way through the festival circuit all year and is finally ready for its theatrical debut. It opens today in New York City, and with it came director Jeff Malmberg.</p>

<p><em>Marwencol</em> marks Jeff’s directorial debut. He was worked as an editor for a number of years, but it wasn’t until he started cutting documentaries that he found his true calling. He took some time out of his schedule to sit and chat with me about the film and his burgeoning career. More than anything, it seems, Jeff loves to talk about Mark, the star of his film. Don’t take my work for it though. Click on through and listen to Jeff’s story. He talks about how he came to make this film, the state of documentary today, and why he chose a narrative structure for <em>Marwencol</em> that some others may have shied away from.</p>

<audio controls>
  <source src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/candlercast-18 -jeff-malmberg.mp3" type="audio/mpeg">
Sorry, your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/10/candlercast-18 -jeff-malmberg.mp3">Right-Click to Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTunes</a></p>

<p>For more information about <em>Marwencol</em> and release dates, please <a href="http://www.marwencol.com">visit the official site</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #17: Talking Joan Rivers with Ricki Stern and Anne Sundberg]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/06/14/candlercast-17-talking-joan-rivers-with-ricki-stern-and-anne-sundberg/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-14T07:43:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/06/14/candlercast-17-talking-joan-rivers-with-ricki-stern-and-anne-sundberg</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/6a00d8341bff3653ef012877194dcc970c-800wi.jpg" title="Joan Rivers - A Piece of Work Still" ></p>

<p>A few weeks ago, I headed over to a hotel on the Upper East Side of Manhattan to sit down with directors Ricki Stern and Anne Sundebrg (who prefers to be called Annie).
No doubt the setting was picked to appease the eponymous subject of their new documentary, <em>Joan Rivers - A Piece of Work</em>, who actually lives a few blocks from where we met. The day started with a roundtable with
Ms. Rivers, who unleashed her token scathing wit. Bits of that session, and the one you are about to hear, were for a <a href="http://www.heebmagazine.com/joan-
rivers-everyones-favorite-dirty-grandmother-talks-about-her-new-documentary/">piece I wrote for Heeb Magazine</a>. The real story of any documentary, however, comes not from the subject but from the filmmakers themselves, which is why I was delighted
to talk to Ricki and Annie about their latest project.</p>

<p>The film is a solid study of an extraordinary woman, and it avoids the pitfalls an trappings many similar documentaries fall victim too. There are limited talking heads and archival footage is used in a very organic
manner; it is neither reality show nor biography, but something more. Perhaps this has to do with the fact that the Ms. Stern and Ms. Sunberg’s previous works deal in much weightier material, such as Darfur. As they
explain, they are simply after a good story and Joan provided one for them. They simply wanted to capture something compelling. Listen in for some fascinating insight from these excellent filmmakers.</p>

<audio controls>
  <source src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/candlercast-17-ricki-stern-annie-sundberg.mp3" type="audio/mpeg">
Sorry, your browser does not support the audio element.
</audio>

<p><a href="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/06/candlercast-17-ricki-stern-annie-sundberg.mp3">Right-Click to Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTunes</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #16: A Conversation with The Infidel Team]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/29/candlercast-16-a-conversation-with-the-infidel-team/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-29T00:15:43+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/29/candlercast-16-a-conversation-with-the-infidel-team</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The British film <em>The Infidel</em> just reached American shores this week at the
Tribeca Film Festival here in New York City. The irreverent comedy is about a
Muslim who learns he is adopted and his parents are in fact Jewish. What
ensues is a delightful comedy of errors that delves into the murkier depths of
religious and ethnic stereotypes. You can read my full review <a href="http://www.heebmagazine.com/chosen-film-_the-infidel_/">over at Heeb
Magazine</a>.</p>

<p>I was able to get some face time with four people connected to the film. Josh
Appignanesi is the film’s director and David Baddiel wrote the script. The two
offered up some deadpan wisdom on the weighty subject their film deals with.
The bulk of my questions (as you’ll hear) focus on reactions to the film and
whether or not it is controversial. Both Baddiel and Appignanesi are
passionate about their creative choices and the power of comedy in the most
uncomfortable of social conversations. They say it better, so definitely check
it out.</p>

<p>Omid Djalili and Richard Schiff, the film’s stars, are similarly serious when
it comes to discussing <em>The Infidel</em>. Schiff, who is most well known in the
states for his role as Toby Ziegler on <em>The West Wing</em>, takes particular
offense at having any of his roles, including that of Lenny in <em>The Infidel</em>,
labeled as stereotypically Jewish. The two exhude a comic energy that made it
difficult for me to keep a straight face while chatting them up. Especially at
the end of our talk, the two go off on the provenance of a few racial
epithets. It is quite hilarious.</p>

<p>As always, I’ve said too much. Just click play already.</p>

<p>[podcast]http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/candlercast-16
-the-infidel.mp3[/podcast] <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/candlercast-16
-the-infidel.mp3">Right-Click to
Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/M
ZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTunes</a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Candlercast #15: Talking Indie 3D with Noel Paul]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/17/candlercast-15-talking-indie-3d-with-noel-paul/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-17T13:47:33+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/17/candlercast-15-talking-indie-3d-with-noel-paul</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/agb2.jpg"><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/agb2-300x241.jpg" alt="3D Rig used for Annie Goes Boating" /></a>As Hollywood enjoys this latest wave of 3D
filmmaking, I have long hoped that their innovations would eventually trickle
down to benefit the independent filmmaking community. Noel Paul’s short film,
<em>Annie Goes Boating</em>, which just had its world premiere here at SXSW, may be
the film that proves indie directors are dying to get their hands on the
technology. Gone are the flaming projectiles and the prickly protrusions that
are commonly found in big budget 3D films. Instead, Noel gives us a gorgeous
look at a day in the park.</p>

<p>I sat down with Noel to discuss how he was able to make this film on an indie
budget. Once he realized he had access to two Red Digital Cinema cameras, the
filmmaker went to work with his creative team to try to hack together a
workable 3D rig. However, it wasn’t until he got in contact with Lightspeed
Design, whose DepthQ technology is used in a number of 3D applications, that
the pieces really began to come together. The result is a 10 minute short that
is absolutely gorgeous.</p>

<p>[podcast]http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-15
-noel-paul.mp3[/podcast] <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com
/wp-content/uploads/2010/03/candlercast-15-noel-paul.mp3">Right-Click to Download</a> • <a href="http://itunes.apple.com/WebObjects/MZStore.woa/wa/viewPodcast?id=334875368">Subscribe in iTun
es</a></p>

<p><em>Annie Goes Boating</em> feels like a painting, one you could get up and walk
around in. The plot is simple by design: some friends go boating and play
badminton; a love triangle appears and then it ends. The photography, by
Michael Ragen, is reminiscent of impressionist painting. Your eye is free to
wander around the woods throughout the film. The depth is astounding. Some
shots of ducks on a pond make you feel almost as if you could touch the water,
as if the ducks might fall off the screen. Perhaps I’m romanticizing it, but
if you see the film in 3D you will understand my reaction.</p>

<p>It is great to listen to Noel talk about 3D technology and how he likes to use
it. I can’t think of another independent filmmaker who has tried a hand at 3D,
but I truly hope that it sticks. Noel doesn’t care to guess whether or not 3D
will catch on, but he says that he has every intention of making more 3D films
if he is able to get them off the ground. With this one under his belt, I
don’t see how that could be a problem.</p>

<p>I have hardly scratched the surface here. Listen in to my conversation with
Noel Paul, where he gets into some of the nitty gritty of 3D production as
well as speaks on his artistic influences behind this film. It’s one of the
most interesting conversations I’ve had on the subject. Enjoy.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
