<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Theater Review | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/theater-review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Theater Review: Angelika Film Center New York]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/19/theater-review-angelika-film-center-new-york/"/>
    <updated>2009-05-19T08:23:55+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/05/19/theater-review-angelika-film-center-new-york</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps/ms?dirflg=r&amp;daddr=Grand+Cen
tral+Station,+NYC&amp;ie=UTF8&amp;moduleurl=http:%2F%2Fmaps.google.com%2Fhelp%2Fmaps%2
Ftransit%2Fnyc%2Fmapplet.html&amp;mapclient=google&amp;hl=en&amp;msa=0&amp;msid=10622246132034
3446210.00046a42851af44f1b39c&amp;ll=40.726023,-73.99748&amp;spn=0.005838,0.009656&amp;z=1
7">Angelika Film Center</a> On the surface, Soho’s Angelika Film Center’s great location, phenomenal
programming, delectable café and the weight of a national theater alliance to
throw behind riskier fare make it seem like the perfect art house cinema.
Unfortunately, the auditoriums in this Manhattan mainstay are too close to the
earth’s core to allow for a decent screening. Tucked away dangerously close to
the nearby subway stop, you’ll have to wait for a transit strike if you want
to watch a film uninterrupted.</p>

<p>When you walk up to the box office of the Angelika, it doesn’t take long for
the building to enchant you. Perched on a massive corner at Houston and Mercer
streets, the hand changed “Now Playing” sign evokes a simpler time in cinema,
wholly analog in nature. An eave over the box office has art deco inspired
lettering emblazoned on it, with stairs leading up into the ticketing
vestibule; it is like walking up a tongue into a mouth, a warm place to rest.</p>

<p>The entire first floor boast’s one of Lower Manhattan’s most capacious cafés.
Rarely overcrowded, it is a great place to sit and get some work done, chow
down on a pastry and suck back a cup o’ joe. Adding to the fun, it is
unquestionably a cinema cafe, with posters and postcards littering the tables
and walls. It never stoops to the level of a lobby. The movement to add
legitimate café space into theaters is ingenious, this is a haven for
cinéfiles and maker’s alike.</p>

<p>But one can only tarry upstairs for so long. After all, this is a theater as
well, and you probably paid to see a show. Once your ticket is snuffed out by
the usher, the descent into New York’s bowels begins via escalator; stairs for
adventure seekers. Don’t bother silencing your mobile, there’s no service
where you’re going. Okay, this is an exaggeration. The auditoriums are
probably a story and a half, maybe two stories, below street level. Other
theaters go much lower, but none have to compete with the MTA as the Angelika
does.</p>

<p>Looking past the subterranean handicap, the auditoriums themselves are subpar.
The screens are small and too high up, the projectors too far away. The rooms
are long and narrow, trying to fit more seats “vertically”, but the picture
quality must suffer as a tradeoff. When you can’t hear the train coming by
every twenty minutes, you can hear films in the auditoriums next door if stuff
is getting blow’d up in them.</p>

<p>Now, I will say that the Angelika is in the business of doing the impossible,
that being bringing independent cinema of the world to the masses. It is a
very tough business and they do an incredible job of programming for an
increasingly diverse audience. The Angelika always has provocative new work
showing. At time of writing, I can tell you I want to see everything they have
showing right now. In a way, they have cornered the market on independent
fare. They’re not the only art house in the city, but they are one of the
busiest; the breadth of their offerings is remarkable.</p>

<p>So you have a choice to make: see groundbreaking new work from an
international library in a subpar environment or don’t. Personally, I will
always go with the former. Sometimes, what you crave is only at the Angelika,
and you should absolutely go see it. We have been spoiled in recent years. AMC
in particular, <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/22/review-amc-loews-lincoln-
square-nyc/">as mentioned in a previous
article</a>, has made a very strong push to entice audiences with impeccable
aural and visual experiences. Believe it or not, this is a relatively young
movement. Before we cared so much about screening quality we would just go to
the movies, and get lost in the world of film, however broken or degraded our
surrounding may be. If it is great cinema you seek, then the Angelika is
perfect, maybe even magical.</p>

<p>STAND CLEAR THE CLOSING DOOR!!! (naw, I kid)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: AMC Loews Lincoln Square, NYC]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/22/review-amc-loews-lincoln-square-nyc/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-22T11:18:10+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/22/review-amc-loews-lincoln-square-nyc</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://maps.google.com/maps/ms?ie=UTF8&amp;hl=en&amp;msa
=0&amp;msid=106222461320343446210.000467fe0a4e77050dd54&amp;ll=40.775504,-73.98203&amp;spn
=0.005988,0.009656&amp;z=17">AMC Loews Lincoln Square 13</a><em>Plenty of time is spent critiquing movies, but the
films themselves provide only part of the experience. Much of how you take in
a work is related to your surroundings, namely, the movie theater. Over the
next few weeks, I’ll be writing up some detailed info on New York’s best and
worst moviehouses in hopes of helping locals and tourists alike make informed
venue choices. Enjoy reading and feel free to add your own experiences in the
comments.</em></p>

<p>By all accounts, including programming, the AMC Loews Lincoln Square 13 is the
best movie theater in New York City. The gilded interiors invoke the movie
palaces of a bygone time, while the technical standards of each screen remains
unmatched. The upstairs lobby is home to black and gold palm trees as well as
goofy sketches of old time movie stars. There used to be shrines to particular
films (a glass encasement used to house props from <em>Legends of the Fall</em>, for
example), adding an almost religious aire to the place; something of a temple
to the gods of cinema.</p>

<p>A rarity in this 21st century, save for the three theaters in the basement,
this particular Loews has resisted the move to stadium seating. The result is
a more intimate experience. Even in the biggest theater, as the other audience
members feel a bit closer to you. I don’t mean in any claustrophobic manner,
rather the experience feels more shared. And if you’re worried that a tall
cowpoke in a ten gallon hat might sit in front of you, fear not, there isn’t a
bad seat in the house. The flattened seating is compensated for by the height
of the screen and the angle of the chairs.</p>

<p>AMC is known to be a bit more anal about projection than other chains, and
that is a very very good thing. Each screen at the Upper West Side theater, as
with most other AMCs in the nation, is set at then exact distance from the
projector for optimal picture. This is one of those things that is gotten
wrong time and time again in an effort to fit more seats into an auditorium.
When the projector is set back too far, the image loses color information and
can lose much of its sharpness. At movie theater screen sizes, a few inches is
all it takes to blow a great image. In terms of picture quality, I have never
been disappointed by the Lincoln Square Theater.</p>

<p>Thanks to audio branding like DTS, SDDS, and Dolby Digital, aural quality is
now less of an issue than it used to be. Still, many theaters are not
constructed well enough to deal with the added horsepower. In my experience, I
have never found myself in the awkward situation of sitting through a
tearjerker as an action hero gets blow’d up in the theater next to mine at the
Lincoln Square 13.</p>

<p>The popcorn is good (when it’s new), the sodas are huge, and the service is
slow, same crap you’ll find in all fifty states really. Obviously everything
is overpriced, but if you need some munchies, you are covered en masse.
Earlier I mentioned over the theaters in the basement. Avoid these if you can.
They are perfectly acceptable, but tiny, reminiscent of small screening rooms
at universities. The only fun part of going down there is the sweet film reel
ceiling over the escalator, seriously.</p>

<p>Regarding programming, the theater does not see many repertory films unless
they are part of a wider release, but they do cover an impressive cross-
section of mainstream and art house flicks. Again, for an arty film to make it
there it must open wide, but so many other theaters in the city scoff at such
fare. It’s nice to have such an advanced space showing smaller films. The
building also boast’s Manhattan’s only IMAX theater and has been home to a
number of world premieres.</p>

<p>To conclude, the AMC Loews Lincoln Square has everything a decent theater
should have, but it is the little things that make it the best. If you find
yourself in New York and need a good spot to check out the latest movie, this
should definitely be high on your list.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
