<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Cinema | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/cinema/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Magic, this Lantern]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/13/bordwell-on-lantern/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-13T17:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/13/bordwell-on-lantern</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>David Bordwell discusses <a href="http://lantern.mediahist.org">Lantern</a>, a new search engine for over 800,000 digital pages the <a href="http://mediahistoryproject.org">Media History Digital Library</a>, on his <a href="http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/2013/08/12/magic-this-lantern/">Observations on film art</a> blog:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I hate to pull a <a href="http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/2013/08/12/magic-this-lantern/">Grandpa Simpson</a>, but when I think of all the time and money and gasoline and air tickets I ran through over several decades to visit libraries holding a few issues of this or that journal . . . and then think about the hours I spent paging through them looking for certain names, terms, film titles . . . and then think about how I painstakingly copied what I wanted onto 3 x 5 cards (photocopy not permitted) . . . I think–Well, what do you <em>think</em> I think?! I think how damn lucky you (and I) are to have all this material so accessible now. For work <em>and</em> play.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Bordwell points to some gems in the treasure trove of material now accessible online, like <a href="http://www.archive.org/stream/internationalpho13holl#page/n71/mode/2up">this 1941 piece</a> by Gregg Toland in <em>International Photographer</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> in which the cinematographer offers this advice:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One of the greatest bugbears in Hollywood today, I think, is that the greater portion of all the creative workers—writers, directors, actors, cameramen and all the rest—are making pictures for the approbation of their fellow-workers.</p>

  <p>This is an unhealthy condition and leads nowhere except false values in pictures. Motion pictures should be made for the ultimate consumer, the audience. And the creative worker, should, in my opinion, make pictures for the audience and dare criticism of his fellow-workers. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>Damn lucky we are indeed.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>The opposite page features a nude lady. This is your NSFW warning.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Thoreau Poison]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/09/upstream-walden/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T10:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/09/upstream-walden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Caleb Crain <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/books/2013/05/the-thoreau-poison.html">at the <em>New Yorker’s</em> Page-Turner blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…leaving the theatre after “Upstream Color,” I felt reasonably confident that I understood what had happened, plotwise. “But what’s it about?” my husband asked. I felt much less sure about that, but as I thought it over in the days that followed, and as I pulled a few transcendentalist classics off the shelf, I began to wonder if I’d been watching a movie by the premier Thoreauvian of our time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is easily the best piece of writing on Shane Carruth’s film yet.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
