<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Music | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/music/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Apple Music Connect is Too Good to Waste on Artists]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/08/set-connect-free/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-08T18:27:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/07/08/set-connect-free</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/connect.jpg" title="Apple Music Connect" ></p>

<p>As soon as iOS 8.4 came out last week I downloaded it and signed up for my free trial of Apple Music. Yes, there are some problems, but overall Apple Music is everything I ever wanted in a streaming service. The near-perfect mix of streaming library mixed with music that clearly belongs to me.</p>

<p>I’d like to focus on one of the more maligned features of Apple Music: Connect. Here’s a small sampling of the  reactions to Connect out there, starting with <a href="http://leancrew.com/all-this/2015/07/for-you-perhaps-but-not-for-me/">Dr. Drang</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This is, to me, the least interesting part of Apple Music because I’m far too jaded to believe that anything put here is straight from the artists themselves.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://recode.net/2015/06/30/apple-music-first-look-rich-fluid-but-somewhat-confusing/">Walt Mossberg</a> tried to explain it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>[Connect] is a sort of social network for artists to reach their fans; the artists post photos, videos and more, and can receive comments from fans.</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://www.loopinsight.com/2015/06/30/first-look-apple-music/">Jim Dalrymple</a> wasn’t sure about it, but invoked the name of one of Apple’s biggest black eyes, Ping:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I’m not really sure what to think about Connect, Apple’s service that allows us to follow bands and musicians. To me, it seems a lot like Ping, but we’ll have to see how it works.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/07/02/technology/personaltech/apple-music-is-strong-on-design-weak-on-social-networking.html">Brian X. Chen</a> at the <em>New York Times</em> devoted an entire article to skewering it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The weakness of Apple Music is Connect, the social network for musicians, which allows artists to upload media, like postings about their concert dates or album releases. Fans can follow artists and “love” or comment on these posts.</p>

  <p>But the artists I followed, like Kings of Leon, Belle and Sebastian and Sonic Youth, used Connect as a portal to upload seemingly arbitrary photos and link to places where people could buy their iTunes albums. And they didn’t appear to be socializing with fans. That’s not a social network; it’s a broadcasting platform.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I actually agree with all of the above. Artists postings thus far have been less than stellar. I think Apple has made a <em>massive</em> mistake billing Connect as a place to follow musicians. Connect is actually a wonderful service being squandered by Apple. The things that Apple is expecting artists to post just aren’t that interesting. Links to their own music and original photos or videos are relatively weak sauce, and the posts have been few and far between for most artists.</p>

<p>However, Connect <em>is</em> great for sharing exactly what I came to the Music app for: music. The trouble is most artists aren’t posting music; they’re promoting themselves in a fairly bland manner. I’ve found the best people to follow are DJs and performers with shows on Beats 1, as well as Apple’s in-house “curators.”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>I follow not only Zane Lowe and Julie Adenuga, but the accounts for “The Pharmacy with Dr. Dre” and “St. Vincent’s Mixtape Delivery Service.” For good measure I started following Apple Music Jazz and Pitchfork.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> These and other accounts have made my Connect tab go from a wasteland to a vibrant, always updated landscape.</p>

<p>The Beats 1 show accounts are great because you can get playlists for a show you missed (or listened to and wanted to revisit). The other curator accounts surface other kinds of music and move that into my Connect feed, where I may end up finding my new favorite song.</p>

<p>Right now <a href="http://www.mcelhearn.com/how-to-share-apple-music-songs-albums-and-plalyists/">anyone can share playlists through Apple Music</a>. However, not anyone can get an account that can be followed. When that happens, I think Connect will be, unabashedly, the best music social network on the planet. The trouble right now is that Apple wants it to be a “a place where musicians give their fans a closer look at their work, their inspirations, and their world.” That’s not an interesting enough proposition.</p>

<p>Connect is dying to be a killer destination on my phone. I hope Apple sets it free soon. When they do, you can bet it will for would-be DJs what Instagram has done for photographers. The next Zane Lowe will be found in Connect, not on the airwaves.</p>

<h3 id="where-to-find-non-artist-accounts-in-apple-music">Where to Find Non-Artist Accounts in Apple Music</h3>

<p>There are two main places to look.</p>

<p>To find Beats 1 show accounts, go to the Radio tab and tap Beats 1. Scroll down past the “Upcoming Shows” schedule until you hit “Featured Shows.” There you’ll see album art for the current main rotation on Beats 1. Tap on a show and then tap “Follow.”</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/beats-1-accounts.gif" title="Where to Find Beats 1 Show Accounts" ></p>

<p>To find Apple’s genre and curator accounts, go to the New Tab and scroll down just a bit. Apple Editors Playlists will show you the accounts for every genre. Curators Playlists will show you accounts for Apple’s launch partner playlist makers. These include Complex, The Fader and other magazines. I hope these accounts will open up to anyone soon. There is so much music within Apple Music to unearth.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/07/curator-accounts.gif" title="Where to Find Curator Accounts" ></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>If ever there were an overused word…<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>It’s eternally annoying that there are non-artist accounts in Connect but you have to have to be a big-name media launch partner to land one.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Primer on Not Being a Music Hater]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/16/a-lot-of-listening/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-16T19:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/16/a-lot-of-listening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great piece by <a href="https://medium.com/@sixfoot6/getting-out-of-the-woods-a-primer-on-not-being-a-music-hater-fc4c46d4dde0">Ryan Gantz</a> on music listening that I think aptly applies to watching movies:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You should feel free to listen to whatever music <strong>speaks</strong> to you. I do.</p>

  <p>But the hard thing about music (and all types of art) is that <strong>speak</strong> can mean something different for every genre, artist, and album. The emotional, tonal, and verbal vocabulary of heavy metal is almost nothing like the vocabulary of jazz. The intention and cultural contexts differ. The listening experience goals for fans of hip-hop may be at odds with what a classical music-lover wants out of a great symphony.</p>

  <p>And that means that it often requires intellectual/emotional openness and very close listening (or, like, dancing) to understand what a piece of music is getting at, what language it’s speaking, what feelings it wants to evoke—even who its target audience might be—before we can fairly judge what’s successful or unsuccessful about it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Gantz articulates something I try to keep in mind whenever I watch a new film, especially one that exists well outside of my comfort zone.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://waxy.org/links/archive/2014/10/index.shtml">Waxy</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[“I want the power to create what is in my mind. That's my dream.”]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/23/mcqueen-interviews-kanye/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-23T20:09:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/23/mcqueen-interviews-kanye</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.interviewmagazine.com/music/kanye-west">Steve McQueen interviews Kanye West</a> for INTERVIEW Magazine and the result is just delightful. In response to how he makes beauty:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I just close my eyes and act like I’m a 3-year-old. [<em>laughs</em>] I try to get as close to a childlike level as possible because we were all artists back then. So you just close your eyes and think back to when you were as young as you can remember and had the least barriers to your creativity.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>On influence:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Well, influence isn’t my definition of success—it’s a by-product of my creativity. I just want to create more. I would be fine with making less money. I actually spend the majority of my money attempting to create more things. Not buying things or solidifying myself or trying to make my house bigger, or trying to show people how many Louis Vuitton bags I can get, or buying my way to a good seat at the table. My definition of success, again, is getting my ideas out there.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And then there’s this side-project:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I also shot a film in “surround vision,” where I had seven screens—three in front of the audience, one above, one below, one to the left, one to the right. This is after designing <em>Watch the Throne</em>—and I was putting my money towards it. I put the amount of free income that I could put into it, which went into the millions. I went around and showed people what I’d done and said, “Hey, I made <em>Watch the Throne</em>, I made this amount of music for the past 10 years, I have this level of visuals, this level of communication, I can sell this many albums, and I also have these new inventions. Will anybody help me out?” I met with 30 billionaires, 30 companies, and basically everyone said, “Fuck you.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As Glenn Kenny aptly put it <a href="https://twitter.com/Glenn__Kenny/status/426058636503556098">on Twitter</a>, “Clearly the problem with most Kanye West interviews up until now has been the interviewer.” Case in point: <a href="http://youtu.be/pGAqqjXPQP8">Jimmy Kimmel</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jim DeRogatis on R. Kelly and the Critic as Journalist]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/16/rogatis-on-journalism/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-16T19:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/16/rogatis-on-journalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>R. Kelly’s sexual predation has been underreported for over a decade. Jim DeRogatis, in conversation with Jessica Hopper at <a href="http://blogs.villagevoice.com/music/2013/12/read_the_stomac.php">The Village Voice</a>, explains how he approached the story from the beginning and why Kelly’s sins are not as easily forgivable as much of the music world would have you believe.</p>

<p>This bit is important:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>A lot of people who are critics are fans and don’t come with any academic background, with any journalistic background, research background. Now, nobody knows everything, and far be it from me to say you’ve got to be a journalist or you have to have studied critical theory in the academy. Part of what we do is journalistic. Get the names right, get the dates right, get the facts right. Sometimes, on a very rare number of stories, there’s a deeper level of reporting required.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You may not know how to report, but you should know how to read.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Amazon Has 20 Albums for $2 Today Only]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/02/26/amazon-album-sale/"/>
    <updated>2013-02-26T09:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/02/26/amazon-album-sale</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Amazon has some <a href="http://amzn.to/15NgHBI">great albums on sale for the ridiculous price of $2 today</a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> You really should get <a href="http://amzn.to/Yw08oH">Macklemore &amp; Ryan Lewis’ <em>The Heist</em></a> if nothing else.</p>

<p>On a related note, I just whipped my music library into shape and signed up for iTunes Match. Amazon’s MP3 downloader makes adding new tracks to iTunes dead simple, and with Match turned on my iPhone populates with the new tracks almost instantly.</p>

<p>It’s not as convenient as buying from iTunes, which auto-downloads new tracks to all my devices, but considering Amazon has albums at a $10 discount today, it’s worth the elbow grease.</p>

<p>Related: Andy Baio’s <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/01/31/baio-on-publishing/">aforelinked</a> “Indiepocalypse” <a href="http://waxy.org/2013/01/indiepocalypse/">piece from January</a> was the reason I bought <em>The Heist</em> recently. “Jimmy Iovine” is a great track, but I think “Wing$” might be my favorite.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Affiliate link. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
