<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Design | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/design/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The billionaire’s typewriter]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/17/the-billionaires-typewriter/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-17T17:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/17/the-billionaires-typewriter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://practicaltypography.com/billionaires-typewriter.html">Matthew Butterick</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>As a writer, the biggest poten­tial waste of your time is not ty­pog­ra­phy chores, but Medium it­self. Be­cause in return for that snazzy design, Medium needs you to re­lin­quish con­trol of how your work gets to readers.</p>

  <p>Tempt­ing per­haps. But where does it lead? I fear that writ­ers who limit them­selves to pro­vid­ing “con­tent” for some­one else’s “branded plat­form” are go­ing to end up with as much lever­age as cows on a dairy farm.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wanted to kick myself reading this only a few moments after publishing “<a href="https://medium.com/@poritsky/is-medium-what-comes-after-blogs-94e493ad65a0">Is Medium What Comes After Blogs?</a>” on (where else?) Medium.</p>

<p>Butterick<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> rather elegantly states thoughts that have been in my head <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/16/medium-confusion/">for over a year</a>. Yes, I’ve been writing on Medium, but I’m also acutely aware of the issues raised in Butterick’s piece. For example, it smarts that when <a href="http://thedissolve.com/news/4688-feb-4s-essential-film-writing/">linking to an article I wrote</a> <em>The Dissolve</em> referred to me as “Medium’s Jonathan Portisky.” I don’t work for Medium.</p>

<p>Or do I?</p>

<p>These thoughts are swirling around my head and require a deeper dive. It’s coming. Hopefully here, on the site I own and control.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/20/mission-impossible-typography/">Not an unfamiliar face.</a><a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Poster Children]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/24/poster-children/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-24T18:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/24/poster-children</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Layer Tennis is a design competition run by <a href="http://coudal.com">Coudal Partners</a>, spartan proprietors (along with <a href="http://www.draplin.com">Draplin Design Co.</a>) of <a href="http://fieldnotesbrand.com">Field Notes</a>, and presented by Adobe Creative Cloud. I don’t know how long it has been running and I don’t full well understand the rules or the state of play.</p>

<p>What I do understand is this lovely intro to today’s match <a href="http://www.layertennis.com/match/dkng-vs-delicious-design-league/#intro">from John Gruber</a>, today’s commentator:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Words, carefully chosen, can be precise in meaning. With emoji you lose that precision, but in exchange you gain a remarkable expressiveness for feeling. An emoji is seldom worth a thousand words, but depending on the moment, it can come close. In the way that email turned everyone into a writer, emoji turn everyone into a visual communicator. That’s something.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>As a fan of Coudal (by way of my favorite tiny notebooks) I’ve seen Layer Tennis pop up along my feeds for the past few weeks. I never got it. I still don’t. But I’m getting closer.</p>

<p>I’ll <a href="http://www.layertennis.com/match/dkng-vs-delicious-design-league/">watch today’s match, then</a>, and see where things go.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Fuckhead You Are Not a Storyteller]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/30/the-mantle-of-bullshit/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T17:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/30/the-mantle-of-bullshit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>That’s your story? That’s a fucking bullshit story. That’s boring.</p><footer><strong>Stefan Sagmeister</strong> <cite><a href='https://vimeo.com/98368484'>You Are Not a Storyteller</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/98368484 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>(via <a href="http://www.juxtapoz.com/design/no-fuckhead-you-are-not-a-storyteller">Juxtapoz</a> h/t <a href="https://twitter.com/TheJewishDream/status/494529096940924930">Rafi</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Helluva Quote from Erik Spiekermann]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/06/the-german-word-for-tight-ass/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-06T19:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/06/the-german-word-for-tight-ass</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Great reporting from Jason Fagone <a href="http://nymag.com/news/features/jonathan-hoefler-tobias-frere-jones-2014-6/#print">in <em>New York Magazine</em></a> on the dissolution of type juggernauts Jonnathan Hoefler and Tobias Frere-Jones. Halfway through the piece, though, type designer Erik Spiekermann, who is quoted earlier calling Frere-Jones “one of the two or three best type designers in the world,” steals the show with this tid-bit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>According to Spiekermann, who knows both Hoefler and Frere-Jones, Frere-Jones is “a cool kid” who “wants to make cool stuff,” whereas Hoefler is “the little nitty-gritty mean little bastard. He is a tight-ass, as we say in German.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I tried doing a search for how to say “tight-ass” in German. Um…don’t do that.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Warner Bros. Logo Design Evolution]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/25/wb-logos/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-25T15:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/25/wb-logos</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Christian Annyas <a href="http://annyas.com/screenshots/warner-bros-logo/">on the Warner Bros. logo</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I couldn’t find a good overview with all logos gathered in one place, so I started to collect them myself, in 2009. Now, five years later, I think I have enough to paint a picture of Warner Bros logo design evolution.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Comprehensive and gorgeous. I feel like I should have known (or even surmised, honestly) that Saul Bass designed the 1972-1984 logo (#10).</p>

<p>Set aside some time and mouse over the over 200 logos Annyas collected.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://coudal.com/archives/2014/02/warner_bros_log.php">Coudal</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
