<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Review | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/review/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extra Thoughts on Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T15:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a piece about Alex Gibney’s latest documentary, <em>Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine</em>, <a href="http://magazine.good.is/articles/the-rotten-side-of-apples-founder">for GOOD Magazine</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The film is by no means a comprehensive portrait of Jobs, though it features a number of interesting new interviews with those close to him, like the aforementioned [Chrisann] Brennan, iPod chief Jon Rubinstein, and Macintosh engineering head Bob Belleville. […] Mostly though, it seems Gibney set out to make a negative portrait of Jobs, and he succeeds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Audiences who know little about Jobs are certainly in for a shock. I heard plenty of gasps among the SXSW audience I watched the film with.</p>

<p>While I believe Gibney made this film to better understand his relationship with the technology that has conquered the world, I think he’s a bit cagey in his narration about how deliberately unsavory his portrayal of Jobs is. This is not a flat out biography. I’m not sure I’d call it a hit piece either, but it comes very close.</p>

<p>That said: it’s all true. Jobs had a very dark side that was never quite hidden, but surely overshadowed by his incredible successes.</p>

<p>I’m not sure why now, but the legacy of Jobs seems to be coming more to the fore this year. Besides <em>Man in the Machine</em>, which has been picked up by Magnolia Pictures and will probably see a release sometime this year, just this week we saw the release of Brent Schlender and Rick Tetzeli’s <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/book/becoming-steve-jobs/id936502684?mt=11&amp;at=11l5Fb"><em>Becoming Steve Jobs: The Evolution of a Reckless Upstart into a Visionary Leader</em></a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> That latest unauthorized biography of Jobs has been met with praise so far by the Mac blogging community and even Apple itself.</p>

<p>I haven’t read it yet, so I can’t speak to whether it looks at Jobs through rose-colored glasses (whereas Gibney’s glasses would be more ashen) or if it truly is a comprehensive investigation into Jobs’s life. If I had to guess, <em>Man in the Machine</em> will fade, just as the scandals rehashed in it have done over the years.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That’s an iBooks affiliate link. If Amazon is more your bag, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Becoming-Steve-Jobs-Evolution-Visionary/dp/0385347405?tag=thecandlerblo-20">here you go</a>. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jason Schwartzman's On-Screen Schmuckery in 7 Chinese Brothers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/19/7-chinese-brothers/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-19T15:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/19/7-chinese-brothers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Me, <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/chosen-film-jason-schwartzmans-on-screen-schmuckery-in-7-chinese-brothers/54447">for Heeb Magazine</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This year, at SXSW, we have the <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2015/events/event_FS18118">premiere</a> of Bob Byington’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3488184/?ref_=ttfc_fc_tt"><em>7 Chinese Brothers</em></a>, a film that showcases the lighter side of [Jason] Schwartzman’s on-screen schmuckery. He plays Larry, a fuck-up to be sure, but a fuck-up you can cheer for.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I enjoyed this one. If you’re a Schwartzman fan, <em>7 Chinese Brothers</em> should head to the top of your list.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extra Thoughts on Listen Up Philip]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/17/listen-up-philip-review/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-17T16:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/10/17/listen-up-philip-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/10/elisabeth-moss-still.jpg" title="Elisabeth Moss in Listen Up Philip" ></p>

<p>I <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/chosen-film-listen-philip/52662">reviewed <em>Listen Up Philip</em> for Heeb Magazine</a>. Initially I wanted to pan the film, but I sat down to re-watch it and discovered how special it actually is. It seems like a chronicle of a few horrible people, but actually it’s a film about how we deal with success.</p>

<p>One thing that irked me on first viewing was the film’s use of voice over. As I mention in my review, this is a knee-jerk reaction. Omniscient narrators are usually a lazy crutch used by writers who can’t build a complex character and structure a narrative at the same time. But that was an unfair assessment. Writer/director Alex Ross Perry’s narrator is there to streamline the narrative, not fix it. We meet our characters in situ and jump right into the meat of their lives. It makes the film almost uncomfortably fast-paced.</p>

<p>And so I came around on this one. I truly love Elisabeth Moss’s performance, though that may be linked to the fact that I feel the closest connection to Ashley, the character she portrays. She also happens to be the only character whose life seems better off by the end of the film, though that’s more a matter of opinion than fact. As I wrote for Heeb, the choice to prefer Ashley “is a personal one though, perhaps linked to my own views of success and artistic struggle.”</p>

<p>That’s the heart of what makes <em>Listen Up Philip</em> such a special work. It offers insight on success (and life) in a mature and introspective manner. I’m glad I didn’t dismiss it because I don’t like omniscient narrators (but generally I still don’t).</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Editorial for iPad: First Impressions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/19/editorial-first-impressions/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-19T17:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/19/editorial-first-impressions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/08/editorial-bold.png" title="Editorial for iPad" ></p>

<p>Last week Ole Zorn released <a href="http://omz-software.com/editorial/index.html" title="Editorial for iPad">Editorial</a>, a text editor for iPad loaded with all sorts of customizable automation workflows. Put on a pot of coffee or grab a growler of beer and spend some time with Federico Viticci’s <a href="http://www.macstories.net/stories/editorial-for-ipad-review/" title="Reinventing iOS Automation: Editorial Review">epic review over at MacStories</a> and/or Gabe Weatherhead’s <a href="http://www.macdrifter.com/2013/08/editorial-for-ipad-a-landmark-in-ios-text-editors.html" title="Editorial for iPad: A Landmark in iOS Text Editors">bescreencasted walkthrough at Macdrifter</a>.</p>

<p>Editorial is only <a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=Oajfc*AWWvY&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=146261.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=5573&amp;RD_PARM1=https%3A%2F%2Fitunes.apple.com%2Fus%2Fapp%2Feditorial%2Fid673907758" title="Editorial for iPad - iTunes Affiliate Link">$4.99 cheap so go get it</a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> Even before you go down the nerd rabbit hole and begin unleashing the power of Editorial it’s an awesome text editor worth well over a crisp Lincoln. I bought Editorial the moment it came out and have been playing with it a bit. I’m not sure yet if it’s going to replace the rest of the apps I’ve been using on iPad, but I wanted to share my first impressions on some of its core features.</p>

<h3 id="design">Design</h3>

<p>Editorial’s interface is surprisingly clean given the breadth of its features. Launching it will bring up the text editor; swipe left to reveal the file browser, swipe right to reveal a tabbed interface for Markdown preview, console, help documents and the built in Web browser.</p>

<p>But the real charm of Editorial’s design is just how deep it goes. Every button, every menu, every window is carefully considered. One of my favorites you have to see to appreciate is what happens when you Delete an action in the Edit Workflow window. It’s a two-tap process with very thoughtful animations.</p>

<p>Zorn gets extra bonus points for including the bold and italic versions of fonts for Markdown preview (both inline and in the preview window). He even included an italic version of Inconsolata.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> Most other Markdown apps I’ve used will simply render the standard typeface as needed, but adding a slant to a typeface does <em>not</em> make it truly italic. Small, deliberate decisions like that are sprinkled throughout, and they make Editorial a joy to use. </p>

<h3 id="dropbox-version-history">Dropbox Version History</h3>

<p>Editorial taps into Dropbox’s built in document version history allowing you to view a diff of any two versions of your file. From there you can restore an older edit. There is great potential for this to become a useful, perhaps even invaluable feature. In practice right now, though, it’s a bit clunky.</p>

<p>The main difficulty I’ve run into is that a document will continuously save while I’m working on it. I’m not sure if this is because the Dropbox app on my Mac is always running, thus always syncing even as I write on my iPad, but the result is a new version almost every minute. When choosing a version to view or revert to, there is no context for which version you want to view, just a timestamp.</p>

<p>This could be useful when a disaster happens, if you lose data or if you deleted something a day ago that you shouldn’t have. But, again, in practice this isn’t how I use version history. If there were a way to limit the amount of versions saved or a way to trigger a version at a specific point in time (akin to a git commit) then I could see this version viewer being much more useful.</p>

<h3 id="workflows">Workflows</h3>

<p>Workflows are the centerpiece feature of Editorial.  Federico and Gabe featured some great, downloadable examples in their aforelinked reviews, and Ole posted <a href="http://omz-software.com/editorial/workflows.html" title="Editorial for iPad – Workflows">a collection of some of the best on the app’s landing page</a>. The power of Workflows cannot be understated: there is no other iOS text editor that allows you to manipulate text the way that Editorial does (and there likely won’t be another for some time).</p>

<p>However, there is a very steep learning curve to crafting your own Workflows. Editorial comes with a wide array of actions to use on your text, but the most powerful Workflows involve Python scripting. Being that I don’t know Python (beyond <code>print "Hello world"</code> which I was rather proud of) diving into the Workflow editor is a bit slow and daunting for me.  I’ve no one to blame but myself, of course; if I want better workflows I’d better <a href="http://docs.python.org/2/tutorial/" title="The Python Tutorial">learn Python</a>.</p>

<p>Still, I can’t help but wish some of the functions performed by Workflows could have been built right into the app, like this excellent <a href="http://editorial-app.appspot.com/workflow/5144752345317376/CRuhgQSwL7U" title="Editorial Workflow — FindReplace">Find and Replace</a> Workflow Federico made. Editorial has great, built-in document search. Using a Workflow that relies on alert-style search boxes that don’t allow you to view the document or what you’re replacing while it runs feels too far out of place. That said: at least I can do it.</p>

<p>The possibilities are almost endless with Workflows and I’m excited to see a little community of Workflow sharing pop up. I just wish I knew more Python…<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> </p>

<h3 id="text-selection">Text Selection</h3>

<p>Here’s how Federico described Ole’s customized text selection in his review:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In most iPad apps, selecting text when the keyboard is shown and then dismissing the keyboard results in losing the selection; Editorial has a custom selection engine that allows you to select text as you normally would when the keyboard is shown, but also to dismiss the keyboard, keep the selection, and tap the dimmed selection again to bring up the keyboard without losing the selection at all. When the selection is dimmed, you can do anything that you can typically do with a non-custom selection, such as extend it and copy text. </p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a very cool feature in that it allows you to run Workflows on selected text even when the Keyboard is dismissed. This is most useful when you want to look up a URL in the browser from which to create a Markdown link. You can select your text then swipe over to the browser, dismissing the keyboard. Navigate to the URL you want, swipe back to the text editor and use Federico’s <a href="http://editorial-app.appspot.com/workflow/6258007868440576/-PjiU8b7VOw" title="Editorial Workflow — Links">Links</a> Workflow and, bam, you’ve got a link.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup></p>

<p>However, and this is a big however for me, Editorial’s custom text selection comes at a price: the standard iOS gestures for selecting text didn’t all make it into the app. In most iOS text editing apps, double tapping a word selects it; double tapping and dragging allows you to expand the highlighted selection either before or after the selected word and quadruple tapping will select the whole target paragraph. These selection gestures, <em>especially</em> double-tap-and-drag, are gestures I use daily when writing on iOS. Unless I have a bluetooth keyboard I’m lost without them.</p>

<p>In order to select more than one word of text in Editorial (today) you have to:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Select a single word by double tapping it</li>
  <li>Release the touchscreen</li>
  <li>Grab one of the holders on either end of the highlighted word and expand the selection</li>
</ol>

<p>In my experience so far the double tap to select gesture is somewhat of a mixed bag; sometimes I can’t get it to activate depending on what I’m trying to highlight. In those instances I need to:</p>

<ol>
  <li>Tap-and-hold to bring up the loupe tool</li>
  <li>Place the cursor on or near the desired word selection</li>
  <li>Release the touchscreen</li>
  <li>Wait for the pop-up selection menu to appear</li>
  <li>Tap “Select”</li>
  <li>Grab one of the holders on either end of the highlighted word and expand the selection</li>
</ol>

<p>Yes, listing the above steps may seem a bit extreme given that I’m only talking about a few seconds inconvenience, but this definitely adds much more friction to writing on iOS than I’m used to. It isn’t about the time, it’s about taking my mind off of my writing.</p>

<p>I’m honing in on and being critical of one (admittedly vital) aspect of text selection in Editorial, but I should mention one very neat addition. You can slide your fingers across the extra row of custom keys to move the cursor around. This is helpful when you only need to move around a few characters and don’t want to take your hands too far away from the keyboard. I thought it was a novelty at first but it’s growing on me.</p>

<h3 id="a-great-app-for-many">A Great App For Many</h3>

<p>I warmed to Editorial over the course of writing this post, which, yes, I wrote mostly in Editorial. Most of my writing is done in <a href="http://bit.ly/12dcIz4" title="Ulysses III - Affiliate Link">Ulysses III</a> on a Mac synced via iCloud to <a href="http://bit.ly/10RGWBf" title="Daedalus Touch - Affiliate Link">Daedalus</a> on iOS.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> In the past I’ve lost work synced On Dropbox, though more often I’d end up inundated with a folder full of “conflicted” copies of documents.</p>

<p>From the first moment I saw iCloud sync in use in <a href="http://bit.ly/10HJvJ3" title="iA Writer - Affiliate Link">iA Writer</a>, I knew it would be my preferred sync solution. Documents can be open everywhere and sync instantaneously. There is no worrying that a file may have been left open on another system, or that an edit made in one location caused a conflicted copy to appear in all locations. Dropbox sync works and it works well; in my experience iCloud sync simply works better. So it’s going to be hard to get me back into a Dropbox syncing text editor.</p>

<p>Still, in my testing Editorial works nicely (that is, if one is watchful of when and where documents are syncing) with the External Folders feature in Ulysses III which allows documents in a folder on the hard disk, in this case <code>~/Dropbox/Apps/Editorial/</code>, to be viewed and edited. There are some quirks to using this feature in Ulysses, but I can cover that in another post.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" rel="footnote">6</a></sup></p>

<p>Editorial is a great app for some forms of writing. Nowadays I prefer my apps have more file organization, which is why I tend to reach for Daedalus or <a href="http://click.linksynergy.com/fs-bin/click?id=Oajfc*AWWvY&amp;subid=&amp;offerid=146261.1&amp;type=10&amp;tmpid=5573&amp;RD_PARM1=https%3A%2F%2Fitunes.apple.com%2Fus%2Fapp%2Fvesper%2Fid655895325" title="Vesper - Affiliate Link">Vesper</a> lately.<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" rel="footnote">7</a></sup> I’ve moved past a folder full of text documents hosted on Dropbox, or at least right now it’s not my preferred method for keeping my writings in order.</p>

<p>That said, Editorial is one killer text editor that will only get better as more people experiment with new and interesting workflows. I can’t wait to see where the community takes this one.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Affiliate link. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>As far as I can tell <a href="https://github.com/MihailJP/Inconsolata-LGC">Inconsolata-LGC</a> (<a href="https://github.com/MihailJP/Inconsolata-LGC/downloads">download page</a>) is what’s in use. While we’re on fonts: in the future I hope to see Courier replaced with <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/courierprime/" title="Courier Prime - A Courier made for screenplays.">Courier Prime</a>, specifically because its italic glyphs are so nice to look at.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Working on it.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>You could also trigger the workflow right from within the browser, but I’m trying to move this thing along here. I’m barely scratching the surface of the many ways one can use Editorial.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Affiliate links both of them. All of the forthcoming app links are.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p>I touched on this feature in <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2013/04/09/ulysses-iii-review/" title="Mac App Review: Ulysses III">my review of Ulysses</a>, but there have been a few changes since then.<a href="#fnref:6" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p>Both allow for simple organization, the former with folders called “stacks,” the latter with tags.<a href="#fnref:7" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Mac App Review: Ulysses III]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/04/09/ulysses-iii-review/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-09T20:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/04/09/ulysses-iii-review</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In college I bought a copy of James Joyce’s <em>Ulysses</em>. <a href="http://amzn.to/10xoDmv">This stately, plump tome</a>, to be exact. I didn’t read it. I tried to, sure, but after a few weeks it became clear I needed to move on.</p>

<p>Every few years I start reading it again from the beginning, each time making it a bit further than my last attempt; never very far. Up until this latest release, <a href="http://www.the-soulmen.com">The Soulmen’s</a> text editor that shares a title with Joyce’s novel was only too aptly named for me. It never clicked. That’s all changed with <a href="http://www.ulyssesapp.com">Ulysses III</a>.</p>

<h3 id="getting-organized">Getting Organized</h3>

<p>I’ve <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/20/my-text-problem/">written before</a> about how most editors get in my way. In praising <a href="http://agiletortoise.com/drafts">Drafts</a>, <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/05/03/drafts-for-iphone/">I wrote this</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nearly every app I use on iOS utilizes the same basic “document” model. Whatever I write usually needs a name and/or tags so that it can be differentiated from the other documents. As such, I couldn’t open an app and start writing without feeling like I was <em>working on something</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The more writing feels like work, like a chore to me, the less I feel like doing it. On iOS, Drafts solved this problem. On the Mac, the closest thing to an app that allows me to just aimlessly write has been <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/projects/nvalt/">nvALT</a>. I use and love nvALT, but for notes, little snippets of information I may need access to later. I never launch it just to write.</p>

<p>Ulysses III puts writing front and center, doing away with the “document” model. Instead, you compose text in “sheets” which can be organized into “groups” (basically folders). A sheet doesn’t need a title, though you can add one with a Markdown header. There is an Inbox where you can compose loose bits of text for later organization or just get to writing.</p>

<p>All of this gets stored in the Ulysses database, which has its advantages. For one, you don’t need to clutter up your file system with snippets of text. By keeping your writing in Ulysses, you can add attachments to sheets, including photos, notes and keywords (or tags). These items follow your sheet no matter where you file it.</p>

<p>Filters allow you to create a search folder, similar to a smart mailbox in Mail. You can search the full text of documents in your entire Ulysses database, or limit the search to a single group by, say, keyword or modification date.</p>

<p>I’m using filters right now. I’ve got a few sheets for different sections of this review. Some sheets have the keyword <code>@first-draft</code> attached to them, some have <code>@second-draft</code> and some both. I’ve got filters limited to my Ulysses Review group for each keyword, so I can view each draft separately. By doing this, I’m able to edit the same sheet in both drafts, which jibes with my brain more than making multiple copies of the same text.</p>

<p>Ulysses III also makes the best use of OS X’s Versions feature I’ve seen in an organized writing app. Hitting ⌘S in any sheet will save a version of it in its current state. This again obviates making multiple copies of the same sheet, allowing you to simply go into the <a href="https://support.apple.com/kb/HT4753">Versions browser</a> to see previous edits. This is the first implementation of Versions I’ve actually wanted to use.</p>

<h3 id="editing-text">Editing Text</h3>

<p>Out of the box Ulysses ships with syntax highlighting for John Gruber’s original <a href="http://daringfireball.net/projects/markdown/">Markdown</a>, an extended syntax they’re calling Markdown XL<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and Textile<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup>. From there you can create your own syntaxes and set up your own highlighting color schemes and keyboard shortcuts.</p>

<p>Most of the highlighting is pretty basic (*italics* are <em>italic</em>, **bolds** are <strong>bold</strong>), but some elements become invisible. Link text, for example, is displayed with a colorful halo around it with the URL embedded, accessible in a popover. You can create a link by surrounding text with square brackets or with the keyboard shortcut ⌘L.</p>

<p>Ulysses III is stunning to look at. It’s not distraction-free-douchy, but it definitely gets out of your way to let you focus on writing. Have a look at it:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/04/ulysses-3.png" title="Ulysses 3 Screenshot" ></p>

<p>Ulysses 2 looks comparatively:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/04/ulysses-2.png" title="Ulysses 2 Screenshot" ></p>

<p>Each of the two panes on the left side of Ulysses III can be folded underneath the editor window, allowing you to only focus on the document at hand. It’s simple and delightful to watch the app animate into place, which you can quickly invoke with ⌘1 (all panes), ⌘2 (Editor and current group) and ⌘3 (Editor only). In each view, the app will grow from the center out as opposed to treating the sidebar panes as drawers. This feels logical, though it’s the first use of such an animation I’ve seen in any Mac app.</p>

<h3 id="the-kitchen-sync">The Kitchen Sync</h3>

<p>Where Ulysses III really wins me over is its sync implementation. The app offers three sync options: iCloud, Daedalus and External Sources. There is also an On My Mac mode which keeps documents on your Mac, un-synced, though I’ve turned this off for the time being. Each comes with its own set of caveats. Let me try to lay them out simply:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>iCloud:</strong> Mac-to-Mac syncing. Makes full use of the features described above as it syncs the entire Ulysses database.
    <ul>
      <li>Documents have to live in the Ulysses database, meaning they are not editable by other applications until you export them.</li>
      <li>Identical to On My Mac, except items are synced.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Daedalus:</strong> Mac-to-iOS syncing (via iCloud) for use with <a href="http://daedalusapp.com">Daedalus Touch</a>.
    <ul>
      <li>No support for custom syntaxes, only straight Markdown.</li>
      <li>No support for nested groups, attachments or filters (this makes some sense if you’re familiar with Daedalus’ interface).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>External Sources:</strong> Allows you to read and write documents from anywhere on your system, like your <a href="https://www.dropbox.com">Dropbox</a> folder.
    <ul>
      <li>No support for custom syntaxes, groups, filters or attachments.</li>
      <li>Will only parse Markdown text for documents with the extension <code>.md</code>; <code>.txt</code> documents need to be converted to <code>.md</code> to allow for syntax highlighting.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>If you prefer a Dropbox text editor on iOS like <a href="http://www.iawriter.com/ipad/">iA Writer</a>, <a href="http://bywordapp.com">Byword</a> or <a href="http://www.secondgearsoftware.com/elements/">Elements</a>, then you can use the external sources mode to edit your documents in Ulysses. However, this is the most stripped down experience you can have in Ulysses III. I think it’s a nice feature if you don’t use Daedalus Touch, but I think users trying to fit Ulysses into their workflow with it will end up being disappointed.</p>

<p>The sync with Daedalus Touch is phenomenal. I love being able to make edits on any device and have it stay in sync on all of them. In my experience iCloud does a much better job than Dropbox at keeping documents up to date. I can leave Ulysses open, even to the document I’m editing with Daedalus on my iPhone, and the changes will stay consistent, intelligently.</p>

<p>I’ve had varying degrees of success keeping sheet order in sync across devices. Right now if I reorder sheets in a stack on my iPad it will reorder the sheets on my Mac and iPhone, even while I’m looking at them. I’ve had less luck going the other way, though in my testing, like I said, I’m staring at my devices watching paint dry. Even from the last version of the beta I used sync has improved exponentially; I imagine edge case bugs like this will get squashed in future updates.</p>

<p>I’ve turned the On My Mac header off in the sidebar (you can also do away with iCloud and Daedalus, if you please). My thinking here is that I want to keep my documents in sync via iCloud. Technically my documents are still “on my Mac,” just in the Mobile Documents folder. There has been a lot of hubbub about iCloud being a terrible product, but I’m enamored of it for document syncing. I use CrashPlan to constantly back up my Mac, including the Mobile Documents folder, so I feel confident that, should something go awry, I’ll always be able to restore my Ulysses database. And for documents I’m extra worried about, I can always export them.</p>

<h3 id="whats-missing">What’s Missing</h3>

<p>Ulysses III is a 1.0 app. Since they wrote a brand new app from the ground up, some aspects of Ulysses 2 are missing. The biggest one you need to know about right now is universal search. You can search for text in a single sheet, but at present there is no way to search your entire database. The workaround right now is to create a filter with, but it’s not a real solution by any means.<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> The Soulmen have promised this is coming in the future updates.</p>

<p>There is currently no support for auto-pairing of most characters. While ⌘I will surround your cursor with  asterisks, Ulysses doesn’t intelligently pair parentheses or back-ticks. Square brackets, in addition, will create a link popover. If you want to use actual square brackets, you’ll need to escape them with backslashes (<code>\[Like so\]</code>), which <em>is</em> annoying, but in practice I rarely use square brackets outside of links, which Ulysses handles well.  You can create TextExpander snippets to trigger auto-pairs, or you can create keyboard shortcuts for elements of custom syntaxes.</p>

<p>Typewriter scrolling and line highlighting didn’t make the cut for 1.0. I’d like to see keyboard shortcuts for the attachments menu, which is currently only accessible with the mouse. This makes sense for images, which have to be dragged into the app, but I’d like quicker access to keywords and notes. And it would be nice if they implemented  something similar to TextMate’s <a href="http://manual.macromates.com/en/working_with_multiple_files#moving_between_files_with_grace">Go to File…</a> menu, which allows for quick search without ever taking your hands off the keyboard. These missing items may be deal-breakers for some, but I’m making do without them. What I get in sync-ability and organization more than makes up for it.</p>

<h3 id="wrapping-up">Wrapping Up</h3>

<p>I use Ulysses III for almost everything I write now. Long-form writing, aimless yammering, quick things I don’t want to forget; it’s all going into Ulysses or Daedalus. It’s solid, beautiful and simple. And it’s only going to get better.</p>

<p>The Soulmen have now completely reinvented themselves. Many established Mac developers have tried to make iOS versions of their biggest apps because users have been clamoring for it. When Daedalus launched in 2011, I noted in <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/06/02/daedalus-touch-brings-beautiful-text-editing-to-the-ipad/">my review</a> that they had actually been working on an app called Ulysses Mobile at the time. I applauded their resistance to shipping that product at the time, but I had no idea that Daedalus would in turn influence Ulysses.</p>

<p>Ulysses is <del>still on sale for $19.99 during their launch week event, but soon it will go up to</del> $39.99. <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ulysses-iii/id623795237?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Go grab it</a><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> and get back to writing.</p>

<h5 id="other-apps-mentioned-in-this-article">Other Apps Mentioned in this Article</h5>

<p>Purchasing any of the apps mentioned with the links below supports the candler blog. I thank you in advance:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Drafts: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/drafts-for-ipad/id542797283?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iPad</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/drafts/id502385074?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iPhone</a></li>
  <li>Daedalus Touch: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/daedalus-touch-text-editor/id406964546?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iOS</a></li>
  <li>iA Writer: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ia-writer/id439623248?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Mac</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ia-writer/id392502056?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iOS</a></li>
  <li>Byword: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/byword/id420212497?mt=12&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Mac</a>, <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/byword/id482063361?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iOS</a></li>
  <li>Elements: <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/elements-for-dropbox-markdown/id382752422?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">iOS</a></li>
</ul>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Which mainly add extended attachments and footnotes.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>And that’s the last time you’ll hear me talk about Textile. Since I’m a Markdown writer, as far as I’m concerned Ulysses is a Markdown editor.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Gabe Weatherhead explains this best <a href="http://www.macdrifter.com/2013/04/ulysses-3.html">in his review</a>. Be sure to check out the comments where Max from The Soulmen responds to him.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>I’ve also got another workaround I’ll be publishing soon.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Affiliate link.<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
