<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Awards | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/awards/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I Rather Liked the Oscars]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/02/27/oscars-2012/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-27T08:46:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/02/27/oscars-2012</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cynicism seems to be the prevailing theme among Oscar commentators the morning after the big event. The awards went to the wrong people, the ceremony was stale, Billy Crystal was too old and out of touch, etc. Yawn. What seems old and staid to me is this Monday morning bitching, the tropes of which haven’t changed since Crystal last donned tails and took the stage.</p>

<p>Overall I enjoyed the 84th Academy Awards show. I don’t begrudge Crystal for rehashing old bits, though I wish he could have breathed new life into some of them. The opening montage was able to eek out a few inspired edits (<em>Moneyball’s</em> baseball scouts as “young” writers), however it would have benefitted from a through-line plot better than “Should I host again?” Never mind that Crystal landed the gig on a technicality thanks to Brett Ratner’s big mouth, a fact never mentioned or mocked.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>The real crime of the show wasn’t creative, but technical. If anyone’s ears need rapping this morning it’s the sound crew. All night there was feedback from the microphones onstage, an annoying, echoed pitch that could be heard below everything. The stage mic even picked up Natalie Portman’s (admittedly misplaced) applauding fits as she presented the award for Best Actor. Worse, the sound was so horribly mixed that whenever there was music and speech at the same time, such as during Crystal’s medley or when the announcer shared facts about winners, dialogue was nearly inaudible. This is inexcusable. People can argue whether or not the show had any chops, but if you can’t hear the damn thing it doesn’t make a difference.<!-- more --></p>

<p>Part of what makes Billy Crystal such a great emcee is his ability to softly mock his targets, a fact that annoys his critics. They’d prefer he was edgier, but there is an art to what he does. Who else, for example, could have thrown so many potshots at Kodak without seeming like a jackass? Ricky Gervais has a similar talent for churlishness, but I couldn’t see him welcoming folks to the “Chapter 11 Theater” and getting a laugh.</p>

<p>As to the actual awards, I have no complaints. The critical community seems to have turned on <em>The Artist</em> as its reputation grew over these last few months, a phenomenon I’ll never understand. I keep hearing these excuses that it’s the easy choice; words like frothy and fluffy are being tossed about. Critics tend to concede that it’s good but only just so, an argument I can’t wrap my head around given how much crap is playing at theaters. Michel Hazanavicius is a master of cinematic impersonation, reviving styles of old with an impeccable attention to detail.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> <em>The Artist</em> is not a perfect film but it does what it does extremely well, and the world deserves more films from Michel Hazanavicius. You can bet we’ll get them now.</p>

<p><em>Hugo</em>, the film which took home the second most awards, was <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/12/16/best-of-2011/">my top pick of 2011</a>. I am happy that such a richly nuanced film took home so many technical awards. The reason it topped my list last year is because it is the kind of film that moves us forward as a community, with Scorsese teaching us how to use the newest technologies in tandem with cinema’s oldest conventions. The major gamble that was <em>Hugo</em> (Scorsese? Kids? 3-D?) paid off in spades for the creative people who worked so hard to bring the vision of the film to life. Very well deserved.</p>

<p>All told, this year’s show was solid and reliable. The Academy’s attempts to skew the show younger have been half-assed failures in the past, not only because of their host choices but because of how frightened they are to break with tradition. Maybe they’ll get it right next year<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup>, but in the meantime, I was only too happy to see Billy Crystal keep the stage warm.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Imagine the laugh if, in the opening sequence, Eddie Murphy made an appearance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>If you argue that <em>The Artist</em> uses styles from the 1940s and 1950s even though it takes place in the 1930s, you deserve a kick in the head.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>If I had to pick a host, I’d lean towards Conan O’Brien. Not only does he have a decent track record with the Emmys, but he also has an undeniable respect for the medium of television and a reputation for turning the glitz and glam of Hollywood on its head.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Going by Twitter, Globes Were a Big Hit]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/16/globes-a-hit-on-twitter/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-16T20:55:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/16/globes-a-hit-on-twitter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>The ratings for the Globes may have dipped slightly, but it was a robust presence on Twitter, where the Tweets-per-second (TPS) count reached 6,162 at its highest point, more than last year’s Super Bowl (4,064 TPS) or the royal wedding (3,966), though still less than the MTV Video Music Awards (8,868 TPS, which had the advantage of the Beyonce bump).</p><footer><strong>Melena Ryzik</strong> <cite><a href='http://carpetbagger.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/01/16/going-by-twitter-globes-were-a-big-hit/'>NYT - the Carpetbagger</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Oh Hollywood and their metrics. I suppose if this is a decent measurement of audience interest it’s only a matter of time before Twitter is entirely overrun by ads, publicists and spam-bots. I said <em>completely,</em> we’re about 90% there.</p>

<p>Also, did you <em>see</em> the memo about this?</p>

<iframe width="640" height="480" src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/Fy3rjQGc6lA" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Is Best Actress a Lesser Award?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/30/is-best-actress-a-lesser-award/"/>
    <updated>2011-11-30T08:05:19+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/11/30/is-best-actress-a-lesser-award</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Mark Harris for <a href="http://www.grantland.com/blog/hollywood-prospectus/post/_/id/38285/oscarmetrics-is-best-actress-a-lesser-award">Grantland</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There’s a problem here, but it’s a problem with the Academy Awards only insofar as the Oscars reflect a self-perpetuating catastrophe within the movie business: The belief that men star in movies, but women star in “women’s movies.” Treated as an irksome niche by their own industry, actresses have to settle for lower budgets and shakier financing, which means that the films for which they get nominated are more likely to be underdeveloped performance showcases than richly conceived and produced movies with top-of-the-line talent in all creative and technical areas.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I disagree with Harris’s take on some of the films he’s talking about, but this piece contains some fine data points regarding women in movies before it unravels into general awards season punditry. He fails to conclude anything, but rather leaves the question open to the rest of us.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Israel's Oscar Choice]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/10/21/israels-oscar-choice/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-21T14:55:29+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/10/21/israels-oscar-choice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I had the pleasure this past week of seeing two great new Israeli films, Nadav Lapid’s <em>Policeman</em> and Joseph Cedar’s <em>Footnote</em>. The latter is Israel’s entry for the Best Foreign Language Oscar this year and it also ran away with almost all of the 2011 Ophir Awards (the Israeli Oscar analogue). I’m not sure if <em>Policeman</em> ever came close to getting the nod for Oscar, but it was nominated for top honors alongside <em>Footnote</em> so I can’t imagine it wasn’t considered.</p>

<p>The task of selecting a film to represent a national cinema at the Oscars is a daunting one. On the one hand, you want to select a film that represents your country and the state of its film community. It is a statement, on some level, of national representation and values. On the other hand, you want to submit something that has a chance of getting nominated. Even if a film doesn’t win, the nomination helps promote a country’s movie business. So the question may as well be asked: between <em>Policeman</em> and <em>Footnote</em>, which is a better snapshot of Israel and its film community today?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p><em>Policeman</em> is a slow, haunting story that depicts the separate travails of both an anti-terrorism police officer and a small band of Israeli extremists. Through acts of violence, the one swears to protect what Israel stands for while the other vows to change it by any means necessary. The terrorists are outraged by the economic disparity in Israel, a point that should stick in any viewer’s gut when they look at the massive protests that took place in Israel this past summer and those that are ongoing on Wall Street today. It wouldn’t be such a stretch to say that Lapid’s film moved hordes of Israelis into the streets to speak out against policy they can longer abide by.</p>

<p>Cedar’s <em>Footnote</em> is a high-brow Talmudic comedy of errors, a smart take on Judeo-intellectualism and the state of modern discourse. It is a also a sweet, at times too sweet, story of a father and son. It tells the tale of two Professor Shkolniks, Eliezer and his son Uriel. Both are Talmud scholars at Hebrew University, but the son’s achievements outshine those of the father. Though its moving parts are of particular interest to a Jewish audience (there’s a nice flourish about the death of Judaism by way of Zionist machismo), its core is wholly universal. Moreover, <em>Footnote</em> doesn’t go near the ongoing military and political struggles of Israel. The only thing keeping this story in the holy land is its relationship to the Talmud. Of the two films, it’s certainly the more accessible one.</p>

<p>I think both are excellent films. In the end I have to wonder which film I would rather represent <em>me</em>, not as a Jew or on behalf of Israel, but which speaks to me and which I would like to share with others. And this is the predicament. On a technical level, I find <em>Policeman</em> the more interesting film for its deliberateness and its tackling of seemingly untouchable material. However, I wonder if I’m getting caught up in the zeitgeist of the Occupy Wall Street movement and economic unrest across the globe. In 20 years, which film will still be available and worth watching? I don’t know.</p>

<p>In the end, it is <em>Footnote</em> that the powers that be have chosen as a national champion. It’s a worthy competitor and it may well nab the Oscar spot. Make no mistake, though, <em>Policeman</em> is also a great representative of what is churning in the Israeli psyche. If you have to choose between the two films here is my advice: don’t. See both.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I should mention that I don’t know the inner workings of the selection of an Israeli film for the Oscars. The producers of <em>Policeman</em> may well have abstained.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Breakdown: 82nd Academy Awards]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/08/breakdown-82nd-academy-awards/"/>
    <updated>2010-03-08T12:11:49+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/03/08/breakdown-82nd-academy-awards</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/03/oscarglasses.png"><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/03
/oscarglasses-196x300.png" alt="Oscar the Groucho" /></a></p>

<p>The statues are all distributed, the corks are all popped, and now it is time
to talk about the 82nd Academy Awards in the past tense. We’ll get to who won,
but first off I’d like to talk about who lost: the viewing audience. This has
to be one of the worst awards broadcasts in recent memory. Overlong and
underwhelming, the only thing interesting in the show was actually finding out
who won, which is weird because that often takes a backseat to the rest of the
spectacle.</p>

<p>Steve Martin and Alec Baldwin were charming, albeit neutered, hosts. They
farmed the opening number out to Neil Patrick Harris, which was predictably
fine, but it seemed like a complete redux of his bouts as Tony and Emmy host.
On paper it sounds poignant, but in practice it felt stale. I long for the
days when Billy Crystal would superimpose himself into the top nominated
films. I can understand the new hosts wanting to move forward with an original
spin, only this felt like a step backwards.</p>

<p>I’m not going to dissect the interpretive dance number, or “Oscars 2: Electric
Boogaloo,” as I like to call it.</p>

<p>I always tune in for the interstitial montages. There were really only two
this year besides the traditional “In Memoriam.” The first was a John Hughes
tribute, which was accompanied by a flock of the kids he made icons gathered
on stage. The montage itself was probably the best part of the evening,
capturing the essence of Mr. Hughes’ momentous career. It didn’t, however, dig
any deeper than that, which is a shame. Back when Errol Morris was making
these things there was a sense of storytelling to the montages. Even further
back, Chuck Workman used to raise these clip-ups to another artistic level
completely. Ah, the good ol’ days. The other big montage was a celebration of
horror films. This was not nearly as successful as the John Hughes piece.
Whoever made it relied far to heavily on clips from <em>The Shining</em> to get them
out of creative ruts. Nonetheless, it was a fairly decent primer on horror
films, but I’m sure fanboys and fangirls out there will protest.</p>

<p>It turns out spending time showing us all ten Best Picture nominees wasn’t all
that much of a time-suck. The real gouge-your-eyes out moment came later in
the night, when the awards for Best Actor and Actress were given out. Each
nominee was treated to a celebrity pal toasting their careers and
performances. Considering actors, and really all nominees, are supposedly
being graded on a specific performance and not the breadth of their careers,
the mini-retrospective monologues came off more obnoxious than celebratory.
And let’s face it, four of the nominees are going to lose, so let’s move
things along and get to the meat.</p>

<p>As for that meat: it’s a strange world where Sandra Bullock wins an Oscar for
a mediocre performance in an even more mediocre film. All I can imagine is
that the rest of the actresses up for the honor split the vote so severely
that the safest bet, the middle of the road one, got the most votes. Mo’Nique
was completely deserving of the Best Supporting Actress honor. Her speech
featured a nice shout out to Hattie McDaniel, and this time it made a lot more
sense than when George Clooney invoked the actresses name in 2006. Jeff
Bridges looked like the happiest kid in the room, and Christoph Waltz still
scares me after <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>.</p>

<p>While some were a bit put off by Sandy Powell’s acceptance speech when she won
for Best Costume Design for <em>The Young Victoria</em>, I thought it was one of the
most refreshing moments of the evening. She praised the costume designers who
make non-period pieces, essentially imploring the Academy to vote in their
favor more often. This has long been a sticking point of mine: the more frill
and lace a film has the better chance it has of winning costume design. Modern
pieces require a careful hand as well, so she’s right; the Academy should
rethink who they give this award to.</p>

<p>I had Quentin Tarantino pegged for Best Original Screenplay, mostly because I
think <em>Inglourious Basterds</em> lives up to the award’s title so well. Mark Boal
brought us <em>The Hurt Locker</em> so the award is certainly well-deserved, however
I have a feeling it will be the kiss of death for him. I wouldn’t hold my
breath waiting for the next mind-blowing Boal penned script. <em>Precious: Based
on the Novel “Push” by Sapphire</em> is certainly an innovative adaptation, plus
its written lineage is right there it it’s ridiculously long title. Congrats
to Geoffrey Fletcher, on that note.</p>

<p>I’m skipping a lot, I know. They’re threatening to play me off…</p>

<p>Finally, we now live in a world where a woman has won an Oscar for Best
Director. Fourth time’s a charm. This truly was a momentous occasion. Ms.
Bigelow did a phenomenal job with a very difficult film. Unlike a
multi-(hundred)-million dollar spectacle like <em>Avatar</em> or a coming of middle-
age piece like <em>Up in the Air</em>, <em>The Hurt Locker</em> is a loose cannon. It could
have gone horribly wrong in another’s hands. There is very little story to the
film, no relatable antagonists, and the driving theme of modern masculinity
trickles out instead of bombarding the audience. The only thing that could
wrangle such an unstable project is the steady hand of a powerful director. It
is a cinematic achievement and deserving of all the honors it racked up last
night. Congratulations to all.</p>

<p>So there you have it: perhaps the worst Oscars in over a decade. They went for
glitzy but they landed on chintzy. It was long, it was boring, but dammit,
I’ll be back next year to tune in for another show, hoping against hope that
the broadcast will return to its former glory.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
