<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Baseball | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/baseball/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Craft Beer Line-Ups at All 30 MLB Stadiums]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/17/baseball-brews/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-17T16:14:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/17/baseball-brews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Khushbu Shah and Cynthia Correa have done yeoman’s work <a href="http://www.eater.com/2015/4/16/8340045/baseball-stadium-craft-beer-guide">over at Eater</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Nothing pairs better with <a href="http://www.eater.com/2015/3/31/8320083/baseball-stadium-food-smores-bacon-stick-fried-chicken-cones-hot-dogs">crazy, over-the-top stadium snacks</a> than an ice-cold beer while watching baseball on a hot summer day. Luckily, fans are no longer stuck forking over an arm and a leg for awful, run-of-the-mill beers. Instead, many stadiums have stepped up their craft beer line-ups, and are often sourcing brews from local breweries.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Philadelphia needs to up its game.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> I went to a game at the Twins’s Target Field last year and enjoyed quite a few local brews. Shocked to see they have more on offer than Colorado’s Coors Field.</p>

<p>Anyway, play ball and drink up.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Both in beer and in actually, you know, hitting and pitching.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baseball, 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/03/baseball-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T16:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/03/baseball-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/05/sports/baseball/baseball-2015-preview-in-a-pitching-rich-era-baseball-ponders-legal-ways-to-boost-offense.html">For <em>The New York Times</em></a>, Tyler Kepner on the state of baseball in 2015:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The areas of emphasis are changing, but teams, of course, will always seek ways to gain an edge. Players will, too, but the drug culture that once led to an offensive boom is mostly gone. Thousands of runs and homers have gone with it, but baseball — for now — can live with that.</p>

  <p>“You have to get rid of performance-enhancing drugs, because they are a threat to the integrity of the game,” [league commissioner Rob] Manfred said. “And whatever the game looks like with players playing clean is what the game looks like.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Strikeouts are up and homers are down. The game is evolving, but I say: good for the game. I grew up in the PED-fueled home run era. It was fun to watch, but now I look back on those years ashamed of what the game became. Baseball needs to move forward and if it’s a more defensive game, so be it.</p>

<p>Man, I’m so happy it’s Spring. Go, Phillies.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/04/phanatic-smaller.gif" width="700" title="Phanatic Dancing" ></p>

<p>Oh and <a href="http://m.phillies.mlb.com/news/article/116062924/ryne-sandberg-discusses-phillies-spring-struggles-praises-ryan-howard">speaking of my Phils</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They lost Thursday afternoon to the Rays at Bright House Field, 10-1, to finish 1-7-1 in their last nine games. They were outscored 72-27 in that stretch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Oof. Whatever. Go team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
