<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sponsor | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/sponsor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York Film Academy [Sponsor]]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/27/nyfa-sponsor/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-27T19:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/27/nyfa-sponsor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My thanks once again to the New York Film Academy for sponsoring the candler blog this past week.</em></p>

<p>Has the proliferation of documentaries, reality TV and faux-documentary television programming (e.g.,
NBC-TV’s The Office) in any way diminished the film-journalism genre?</p>

<p>It doesn’t appear to be the case. If anything, the appetite for non-fictional video narratives is on the
increase: No fewer than 20 top-tier cable television channels carry documentaries 24/7 in the U.S.,
while online cyber-docs and webisodes offer additional and unlimited distribution venues. The
spectacular success of documentary filmmakers Marilyn Agrelo, Michael Moore and Morgan Spurlock now
illustrate that big audiences like and respond to documentaries.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/documentary-school/" rel="nofollow">Documentary School</a> at the
New York Film Academy’s 6-week, one-year and Master of Fine Arts programs provide more than a vocational
education to its very international student body. Aspiring documentarians are exposed to some of the
biggest names in documentaries who visit the program, lecture and provide real-world learning
experiences for students. These budding filmmakers hear first-hand about the power that documentaries
have on <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/" rel="nofollow">education</a> and social change – launching
fulfilling careers, documenting the world as they see it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York Film Academy [Sponsor]]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/22/nyfa-sponsor/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-22T16:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/22/nyfa-sponsor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My thanks to the New York Film Academy for sponsoring the candler blog this week.</em></p>

<p>Do you think video games are all about smash, shoot, bash and run? If you do, please rethink.</p>

<p>Digital games are now used by at least 135 million Americans at least once a month. Many are in the
action thriller genre, but one-on-one and one-on-many games across all available digital formats –
including and especially mobile smartphones and tablets – have gone way beyond. The growth of games such
as Words With Friends and “serious” games used in schools, in workplaces and for military training are
the new explosion in gaming.</p>

<p>The <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/game-design-school/" rel="nofollow">Game Design School</a> at the New
York Film Academy is training the next generation of game designers. With degrees at the Associates,
Bachelors and Masters levels, as well as a one-year conservatory program, the school turns game
enthusiasts into game leaders.</p>

<p>Operated within a performing <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/" rel="nofollow">arts school</a>, the NYFA
game design program includes a class in improvisational acting. Why? Improv is much like interactive
game play.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York Film Academy [Sponsor]]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/22/nyfa-sponsor/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-22T14:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/22/nyfa-sponsor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My thanks again to The New York Film Academy for sponsoring the candler blog this past week.</em></p>

<p>Formerly confined to a few art house theaters and public television, documentary films have emerged as commercially successful ventures for a handful of filmmakers (including Michael Moore with <em>Fahrenheit 9/11</em>, Marilyn Agrelo with <em>Mad Hot Ballroom</em> and Morgan Spurlock with <em>Super Size Me</em>). Cable television channels are also providing a venue for distribution that brings additional capital to the industry.</p>

<p>The popularity of these films is attracting more producers and distributors—-as well as enthusiastic students who want to make <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/documentary-school/" rel="nofollow">documentary filmmaking</a> their life’s work.</p>

<p>The Documentary School at the New York Film Academy is well positioned for training future documentarists. Offering a range from 6-week workshops to one-year and two-year Masters of Fine Arts degree programs at the school’s New York and Los Angeles campuses, students learn from award-winning masters of the genre. They include Maryann DeLeo (<em>Chernobyl Heart</em>), Vanessa Roth (<em>Freeheld</em>) and Geof Bartz, supervising editor of documentary programming at HBO.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York Film Academy [Sponsor]]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/17/nyfa-sponsor/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-17T10:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/17/nyfa-sponsor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My thanks to the New York Film Academy for sponsoring the candler blog this week.</em></p>

<p>Anyone who thinks digital games are for kids is missing out on just how popular gaming has become. A full 40 percent of the total U.S. population plays one or more digital game at least once a month, which has turned it into a multibillion-dollar juggernaut.</p>

<p>Of course, there are those very avid players who play, on average, 18 hours per week on a digital game console, a personal computer or handheld device such as a smart phone or tablet. It is largely from this subset come the game developers of tomorrow, those attending the <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/game-design-school/" rel="nofollow">Game Design School</a> at the New York Film Academy.</p>

<p>Game designers are not necessarily computer programmers, although some attend the academy with that in their backgrounds. Students tend to be enthusiastic gamers, the kinds of people who enjoy the play and have their own ideas of games they would like to develop. Beyond the genre of World of Warcraft, Guild Wars 2, Runes of Magic and EverQuest II, “serious games” are a growing part of educational and business training.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[New York Film Academy [Sponsor]]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/24/nyfa-sponsor/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-24T14:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/24/nyfa-sponsor</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>My thanks once again to the New York Film Academy for sponsoring the candler blog this past week.</em></p>

<p>Has cinematographic technology made the art easier or harder in recent years?</p>

<p>The relative challenge of cinematography is of course dependent on the demands of the filmmaker, the producer, the director, funding sources and the cinematographer. Also, the nature of the film, whether shot in studio or on location, or involving green-screen computer-generated graphics, present their own unique challenges. Which helps illustrate the real question: Is the cinematographer trained to work in a broad variety of situations, able to adapt to the needs of any particular production?</p>

<p>The New York Film Academy offers a one-year Conservatory degree as well as a two-year Master of Fine Arts degree for the individual who is a serious <a href="http://www.nyfa.edu/cinematography-school/" rel="nofollow">school of cinematography</a> student. The program combines classroom study, self-directed projects, production workshops and collaborations involving NYFA students from other disciplines (producers and actors among them). The first challenge, therefore, for the cinematographer is perhaps the most difficult challenge of all: working with other people who are just as important as the quality of the photography.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
