<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Thoughts | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/thoughts/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Todd McCarthy, Welcome to the Ether]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/30/todd-mccarthy-welcome-to-the-ether/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-30T14:00:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/30/todd-mccarthy-welcome-to-the-ether</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Just wanted to jot down a few quick thoughts on Todd McCarthy’s recent
announcement that he is <a href="http://www.indiewire.com/article/welcome_todd_mccarthy/">joining the indieWIRE blog
network</a>. As you may
recall, <a href="http://blogs.indiew
ire.com/thompsononhollywood/2010/03/08/variety_lays_off_its_lifes_blood_critic
s_mccarthy_and_rooney/">Todd lost his job as Variety’s chief film critic</a> the day after the Oscars this year. As a result, the
press exploded with opinions on the death of film criticism, with the usual
culprit being the online blogger/critic. Now, Todd has found a home online,
the very land that supposedly caused his undoing.</p>

<p>Bet you idiots feel pretty stupid now.</p>

<p>There really is no better fit for Mr. McCarthy than indieWIRE, a network that
has defined and redefined the online cinema magazine/trade publication time
and time again. The real loser here is Variety, who has taken nearly every
misstep possible in the age of internet journalism. Their pay wall will
eventually be their undoing, but by literally handing their golden boy to the
free competition, Variety seems to have put the nail in their own coffin.</p>

<p>Mainly, I would like to say welcome, Todd; the ‘net is happy to have you. I
have no doubt that you will enjoy an online career as exciting as <a href="http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/">Roger
Ebert</a> or <a href="http://www.davidbordwell.net/blog/">David
Bordwell</a>. Film journalism, and especially
criticism, is not dead but alive and well online. If ever we see a weakening
in the art of film writing, we can only blame ourselves. The internet has
nothing to do with it.</p>

<p>(If you’ve been wondering where I am, all my film writing is at <a href="http://candlerblog.com">the candler
blog</a>, but you can also see my work peppered on
<a href="http://guru.greencine.com">Greencine Guru</a>, <a href="http://www.heebmagazine.com">Heeb
Magazine</a>, and
<a href="http://www.nachosny.com">NachosNY</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
