<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Film | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/film/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Spalding Gray, depression, and the Big Fish connection]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/24/spalding-gray-big-fish/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-24T21:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/24/spalding-gray-big-fish</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://johnaugust.com/2015/spalding-gray-depression-and-the-big-fish-connection">John August</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Real people aren’t fictional characters. They don’t follow a plot. None of us wakes up in the morning with the aim of advancing our narrative or reinforcing our core themes. Instead, we simply live, pursuing our interests while adapting to the changing circumstances around us. It’s messy. It’s unwritten.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extra Thoughts on Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T15:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a piece about Alex Gibney’s latest documentary, <em>Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine</em>, <a href="http://magazine.good.is/articles/the-rotten-side-of-apples-founder">for GOOD Magazine</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The film is by no means a comprehensive portrait of Jobs, though it features a number of interesting new interviews with those close to him, like the aforementioned [Chrisann] Brennan, iPod chief Jon Rubinstein, and Macintosh engineering head Bob Belleville. […] Mostly though, it seems Gibney set out to make a negative portrait of Jobs, and he succeeds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Audiences who know little about Jobs are certainly in for a shock. I heard plenty of gasps among the SXSW audience I watched the film with.</p>

<p>While I believe Gibney made this film to better understand his relationship with the technology that has conquered the world, I think he’s a bit cagey in his narration about how deliberately unsavory his portrayal of Jobs is. This is not a flat out biography. I’m not sure I’d call it a hit piece either, but it comes very close.</p>

<p>That said: it’s all true. Jobs had a very dark side that was never quite hidden, but surely overshadowed by his incredible successes.</p>

<p>I’m not sure why now, but the legacy of Jobs seems to be coming more to the fore this year. Besides <em>Man in the Machine</em>, which has been picked up by Magnolia Pictures and will probably see a release sometime this year, just this week we saw the release of Brent Schlender and Rick Tetzeli’s <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/book/becoming-steve-jobs/id936502684?mt=11&amp;at=11l5Fb"><em>Becoming Steve Jobs: The Evolution of a Reckless Upstart into a Visionary Leader</em></a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> That latest unauthorized biography of Jobs has been met with praise so far by the Mac blogging community and even Apple itself.</p>

<p>I haven’t read it yet, so I can’t speak to whether it looks at Jobs through rose-colored glasses (whereas Gibney’s glasses would be more ashen) or if it truly is a comprehensive investigation into Jobs’s life. If I had to guess, <em>Man in the Machine</em> will fade, just as the scandals rehashed in it have done over the years.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That’s an iBooks affiliate link. If Amazon is more your bag, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Becoming-Steve-Jobs-Evolution-Visionary/dp/0385347405?tag=thecandlerblo-20">here you go</a>. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[SXSW 2015 Preview Podcast]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/12/sxsw-2015-preview-podcast/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-12T15:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/12/sxsw-2015-preview-podcast</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I joined my pal Ryan Gallagher (of CriterionCast fame) to talk about this year’s SXSW Film lineup. I can’t wait to see so many of these films. <a href="http://criterioncast.com/podcast/sxsw-2015-preview-podcast">Give a listen</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The War Against 35mm]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/25/war-against-35mm/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-25T07:54:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/25/war-against-35mm</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>The view from the gutter, that is from those tortured souls for whom an integral part of the cinema experience is watching a film screened from a print (and, perhaps more importantly, have no interest in Avatar), is that the industry invariably views serious cinephiles as cranks, dilettantes and dreamers with no real concept of the fiscal realities of contemporary distribution. Yet one puckish tweet cuts straight to the heart of the matter: “Hey guys, it’s cool, we’ve got paper. No more need for canvas.”</p><footer><strong>-Richard Jenkins</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.littlewhitelies.co.uk/blog/bad-rep-the-war-against-35mm-17746'>Little White Lies</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>It feels like other industries have done very well by “cranks, dilettantes and dreamers.” Music, publishing and gaming come to mind. That you can buy new albums on vinyl but won’t be able to see a 35mm print soon is beyond me.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NYC's Production Growing Pains]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/17/nyc-production-growing-pains/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-17T07:24:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/17/nyc-production-growing-pains</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>“It’s just not fair because businesses are temporarily being shut down to accommodate filming,” said Joseph Conley, chairman of Community Board 2 in Queens, which represents Long Island City, Sunnyside, Woodside and a portion of Maspeth. Contrary to what City Hall says, Mr. Conley sees little evidence of an upside.</p></p><p><p>“Production crews don’t localize, so there’s no benefit to the community,” he said, pointing out that when it comes to meals, for example, the crews bring in their own outside catering companies.</p><footer><strong>-Marine Cole</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.crainsnewyork.com/article/20120115/REAL_ESTATE/301159997'>Crain’s New York Business</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>I see this issue from both sides. New York City is lucky to have as many productions as it has and could use a lot more. On the other it can be extremely annoying to have a film production on your block for even a day.</p>

<p>Every once in a while I get a film shooting near my apartment. The last one had its camera village camped out near my stoop. The crew couldn’t have cared less that I was trying to get in and out of my building. I gave them a pass because I know how gruelling a day on a film set can be. Other residents didn’t seem so pleased.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>The gist of this Crains article is actually quite positive. People tend to view New York City as monolithic and overpowering, worth putting up with only so long as you need to. In reality it’s a place like any other and the locals need to be wooed and taken care of like anywhere else. It looks like efforts are coalescing to help make this relationship better for everyone. That can only be a good thing.</p>
<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>This set in particular was very poorly run. It was never clear to me where I should and shouldn’t be, felt like I was walking through shots sometimes. Worse, there was glass all over the sidewalk leftover from a car accident they were shooting. The sidewalk was completely open and I walked through it.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
