<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: History | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/history/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How WWI Made Wristwatches Happen]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/04/wwi-and-the-wristwatch/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-04T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/04/wwi-and-the-wristwatch</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Linda Rodriguez <a href="http://boingboing.net/2015/03/04/how-wwi-made-wristwatches-happ.html">writing for Boing Boing</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“The problem with the pocket watch is that you have to hold it,” explained Doyle. That wasn’t going to work for the officer at the Western Front – when an officer lead his men “over the top”, leaving the relative safety of the trenches for the pock-marked no man’s land in between and very possible death, he had his gun in one hand and his whistle in the other. “You haven’t got another hand in which to hold your watch.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I came across similar histories to this piece when researching my <a href="http://magazine.good.is/articles/apple-smartwatch-history">“Smartwatch through History” article for GOOD Magazine</a>. Rodriguez offers a great, conciese refresher on the history of the wristwatch.</p>

<p>We’re on the precipice of another wave of wristwatch innovation. Hopefully it won’t take another war to push the state of the art forward.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Truths Behind ‘Dr. Strangelove’]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/23/stop-worrying/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-23T15:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/23/stop-worrying</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Eric Schlosser <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/newsdesk/2014/01/strangelove-for-real.html">for The New Yorker</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Half a century after Kubrick’s mad general, Jack D. Ripper, launched a nuclear strike on the Soviets to defend the purity of “our precious bodily fluids” from Communist subversion, we now know that American officers did indeed have the ability to start a Third World War on their own. And despite the introduction of rigorous safeguards in the years since then, the risk of an accidental or unauthorized nuclear detonation hasn’t been completely eliminated.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Chilling. If you think <em>Dr. Strangelove</em> is a farce just read Schlosser’s piece. Here’s another bit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Although the Air Force now <a href="http://complex.foreignpolicy.com/posts/2014/01/20/exclusive_air_force_insists_it_never_used_painfully_simple_nuke_code" title="denies">denies</a> this claim, according to more than one source I contacted, the code necessary to launch a missile was set to be the same at every Minuteman site: 00000000.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Oh and just wait until the part on who’s in charge of the US’s nuclear arsenal today.</p>

<p>(h/t <a href="https://twitter.com/elivalley/status/426381957627273216">Eli Valley</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[In living memory]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/28/in-living-memory/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-28T20:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/28/in-living-memory</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tim Carmody <a href="http://kottke.org/13/08/in-living-memory">for kottke.org</a> on the fiftieth anniversary of the March on Washington for Jobs and Freedom:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Everything that happened there, from the arrival of more than 100,000 people through all the speeches, all of the songs, all the signs painted, all the 80,000 cheese sandwiches made, distributed, and eaten, and every one of those moments, happened in <em>one day</em>.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
