<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Books | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/books/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Party Like a President]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/20/party-like-a-president/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-20T11:19:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/20/party-like-a-president</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/02/party.jpg" title="Party Like a President" ></p>

<p>A few celebratory links for my pal Brian Abrams whose book, <a href="http://www.partylikeapresident.com"><em>Party Like a President: True Tales of Inebriation, Lechery, and Mischief From the Oval Office</em></a>, came out last week.</p>

<p>Helluva week, Brian’s having. For one, his book holds the top two positions in Amazon’s “Party Cooking” rankings (and the number three spot in “Culinary Biographies &amp; Memoirs”). On Wednesday, <a href="http://brianabrams.tumblr.com/post/111442716412/book-was-mentioned-on-fallon-tonight">Jimmy Fallon name-dropped the book</a> to set up a so-so joke. Hopefully the exposure will help him knock Anthony Bourdain off his Culinary Biographies &amp; Memoirs throne.</p>

<p>The highlight for me, though, was <a href="http://filmdrunk.podbean.com/e/239-wetlands-with-party-like-a-president-author-brian-abrams/">Brian guesting on the Filmdrunk Frotcast</a>. Honestly I haven’t listened to the show in a few years even though I subscribe to it. I’m glad Brian gave me a kick in the pants to queue it up again. It’s excellent. Note that your monocle may fall out if you’re opposed to naughty language and lots of talk about butts.</p>

<p>Brian talks with Vince Mancini and the gang about bacchanalian presidents, the German film <em>Wetlands</em> and even the future of media on the web. Seriously. Give the whole thing a listen.</p>

<p>Mazel tov to Brian on publishing a book on dead trees. Order <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0761180842/ref=as_li_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0761180842&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thecandlerblo-20&amp;linkId=JIIHKMUXHXQXJLWB"><em>Party Like a President</em> on Amazon</a> and I’ll get a little kickback. I’ve been flipping through it and can confirm it’s full of hilarious bits. (I haven’t read it cover to cover yet; what am I, a professor?)</p>

<p>Oh and while you’re on Amazon maybe give his book a review. This one star review is something special:</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/02/one-star.png" title="Party Like a President" ></p>

<p>I don’t know if it’s the misspelling of “its” or the affected, bubbie-like phrasing of “caused me such nausea” that cracks me up more.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Limits of American Cinephilia]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/01/22/vogel-and-cinephilia/"/>
    <updated>2015-01-22T15:41:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/01/22/vogel-and-cinephilia</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.newyorker.com/culture/richard-brody/limits-american-cinephilia">Richard Brody on the late Amos Vogel</a> and, by extension, the film communities of New York and Paris:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Vogel’s screenings and seminars primed the pump and stimulated interest in a broad range of filmmakers, but it didn’t launch a generation. The Cahiers critics-turned-New Wave directors and their American acolytes, including Richard Roud, Peter Bogdanovich, and Andrew Sarris, did.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Brody’s jumping off point is the publication of <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Be-Sand-Not-Oil-FilmmuseumSynemaPublications/dp/3901644598?tag=thecandlerblo-20"><em>Be Sand, Not Oil: The Life and Work of Amos Vogel</em></a>, a new book of essays by and about the film programmer and teacher.</p>

<p>Vogel, I’ll admit, is someone I have heard of but know little about. The aforelinked piece is illuminating and I’d like to know more. I’m adding his 1974 <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Film-Subversive-Art-Amos-Vogel/dp/0394732073?tag=thecandlerblo-20"><em>Film as a Subversive Art</em></a> to my must read list.</p>

<p>(via <a href="https://mubi.com/notebook/posts/the-noteworthy-the-limits-of-american-cinephilia-coens-in-cannes-soderberghs-2001">MUBI Notebook</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[François Truffaut by Lillian Ross]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/10/truffaut-pocket-book/"/>
    <updated>2014-06-10T22:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/06/10/truffaut-pocket-book</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>New limited edition pocket-sized book <a href="http://thefilmdesk.com/lillianross/">from The Film Desk</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This volume of 40 pages contains five <em>New Yorker</em> Talk of the Town pieces by Lillian Ross, each of which follow François Truffaut during five visits to New York between 1960 and 1976, on occasions of the New York Film Critics Circle Awards and New York Film Festivals.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I went ahead to put in my order before I even finished <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/movies/2014/06/lillian-ross-and-francois-truffaut.html">Richard Brody’s post</a> announcing it to the world. Can’t wait.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[David Cronenberg on Kafka's The Metamorphosis]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/24/cronenberg-on-kafka/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T16:04:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/24/cronenberg-on-kafka</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From David Cronenberg’s introduction to <a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/0393347095/ref=as_li_ss_tl?ie=UTF8&amp;camp=1789&amp;creative=390957&amp;creativeASIN=0393347095&amp;linkCode=as2&amp;tag=thecandlerblo-20">Susan Bernofsky’s translation of Franz Kafka’s <em>The Metamorphosis</em></a>, republished <a href="http://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2014/01/17/the-beetle-and-the-fly/">at <em>The Paris Review</em></a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>When <em>The Fly</em> was released in 1986, there was much conjecture that the disease that Brundle had brought on himself was a metaphor for AIDS. Certainly I understood this—AIDS was on everybody’s mind as the vast scope of the disease was gradually being revealed. But for me, Brundle’s disease was more fundamental: in an artificially accelerated manner, he was aging. He was a consciousness that was aware that it was a body that was mortal, and with acute awareness and humor participated in that inevitable transformation that all of us face, if only we live long enough.</p>
</blockquote>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Thoreau Poison]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/09/upstream-walden/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-09T10:53:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/09/upstream-walden</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Caleb Crain <a href="http://www.newyorker.com/online/blogs/books/2013/05/the-thoreau-poison.html">at the <em>New Yorker’s</em> Page-Turner blog</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>…leaving the theatre after “Upstream Color,” I felt reasonably confident that I understood what had happened, plotwise. “But what’s it about?” my husband asked. I felt much less sure about that, but as I thought it over in the days that followed, and as I pulled a few transcendentalist classics off the shelf, I began to wonder if I’d been watching a movie by the premier Thoreauvian of our time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is easily the best piece of writing on Shane Carruth’s film yet.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
