<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fountain | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/fountain/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fountain in Ulysses]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/08/fountain-in-ulysses/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-08T16:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/08/fountain-in-ulysses</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/05/fake-fountain.jpg" title="Fake Fountain in Ulysses" ></p>

<p>Jennifer Mack figured out <a href="http://jennifermack.net/2015/04/29/faking-fountain-with-ulysses/">how to use Fountain in Ulysses</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Sadly, Ulysses doesn’t speak fountain as one of its markup styles. But I found a way to fake it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I wouldn’t recommend Mack’s “Fake Fountain” to anyone new to the syntax. It’s a complete customization and will require a lot of tweaking to go from <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/ulysses/id623795237?mt=12&amp;at=11l5Fb">Ulysses</a> to any other tool that recognizes <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain</a>. Markup for character names and parentheticals will need to be removed, for example. Through Mack’s <a href="http://styles.ulyssesapp.com/bundle/Fake+Fountain+-+Dramatic/5541af566fbeb3fd238c123c">custom PDF style</a>, however, you can export a formatted screenplay right from Ulysses.</p>

<p>Since I do almost all of my writing in Ulysses, her point later in her explanation is well taken:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Why bother when I could just use another app like Slugline or Highland? Because I like writing my first drafts in Ulysses and having those drafts in the its document library.[sic]  Also users of Ulysses for iPad might find this useful.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The point of Fountain has always been to bring screenwriting into any app. I wish Ulysses had support for Fountain that didn’t require a custom syntax to force it, but it’s nice to know it’s possible.</p>

<p>One note Mack doesn’t mention in her piece. After you create the Fake Fountain markup (or whatever you choose to call it) in Ulysses, you will need to change the document’s markup to recognize the new syntax. To do so, once you’re in a new sheet, go to Edit &gt; Convert Markup &gt; Fake Fountain. From then on all new sheets will have the Fake Fountain markup, so you’ll need to do this again to get back to Markdown, Markdown XL or your preferred syntax.</p>

<p>If you’re a Ulysses user, by the way, I found Mack’s markup through the excellent <a href="http://ulyssesapp.com/blog/2015/05/rich-text-beauty-queen/">Ulysses blog</a>. The team at The Soulmen have done a great job of building a community around their app.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fountain and (cont'd)]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/25/fountain-contd/"/>
    <updated>2015-02-25T15:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/02/25/fountain-contd</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://johnaugust.com/2015/is-automatic-contd-a-bug-or-a-feature">John August digs into</a> the thought process behind how his app, <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/highland/">Highland</a>, and, by extension, <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain</a> as a whole, deals with  <code>(cont’d)</code> in screenplay formatting. The whole piece is interesting, but I especially like this bit:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The screenwriter is always the best judge of whether the dialogue is continuous, so you can just type it yourself.</p>

  <p>That’s sort of the philosophy of Highland and Fountain: your script is exactly what you type, nothing more, nothing less.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I love that Fountain thrives. Part of the reason it does is August’s careful and considered stewardship.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Weekend Read]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/11/weekend-read/"/>
    <updated>2014-02-11T22:16:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/02/11/weekend-read</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John August and the team at Quote-Unquote apps have done it again. <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/weekendread/">Weekend Read</a> reformats screenplays and other text files to fit comfortably on an iPhone screen. PDFs, Fountain, Markdown, Final Draft. Dark mode, four fonts and text resizing. And a brilliant file browser to boot. (Oh and character highlighting because why stop there?)</p>

<p>Free for iPhone. $9.99 In-App Purchase to unlock unlimited library storage. <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/id502725173">Go get it</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Marked 2 and Fountain]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/09/26/marked-2-and-fountain/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T16:44:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/09/26/marked-2-and-fountain</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/09/marked+fountain.png" title="Marked 2 and Fountain" ></p>

<p>Late last night <a href="http://brettterpstra.com/2013/09/26/marked-2-launched/">Brett Terpstra</a> unveiled <a href="http://marked2app.com">Marked 2</a>. It’s a huge update to one of my favorite Mac apps from one of my favorite Mac people. So, yeah, I’m excited.</p>

<p>I haven’t put it through its paces completely quite yet, but I have done a bit of testing of the biggest new feature (for me, at least) that Brett has long teased: <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain</a> preview is now built right into Marked. To test it out just open up any <code>.fountain</code> document in it. Brett has added a slew of new tricks that were never possible with the original <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/02/08/fountain-for-marked/">Fountain for Marked</a> package, like pagination preview and solid print output. And because Brett has good taste Fountain preview defaults to using <a href="http://quoteunquoteapps.com/courierprime/">Courier Prime</a>. Wise choice.</p>

<p>I do want to point out a few differences between the way Fountain in Marked 2 works compared to other apps.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>The first thing is the pagination. Brett’s pagination implementation is very elegant. Any Fountain document opened in Marked 2 will have a continuous scrolling page of text with a thin gray line denoting a page break. To the right of the gray line will be a page number. It gets out of your way but is still visible enough to give you an idea of where you are in your script. Printing will stick to these exact page breaks.</p>

<p>In my minimal testing, I’ve noticed that Marked 2 has slightly different pagination from <a href="http://slugline.co">Slugline</a> and <a href="http://www.quoteunquoteapps.com/highland/">Highland</a>, which both provide identical output. The discrepancy seems to come from the width of action blocks, which are slightly more narrow in Marked 2. As a result some action blocks appear longer, e.g. a four line block spills over to a fifth line.</p>

<p>This is an extremely minor difference, but for now, I’d go with printed output from either Slugline or Highland. That said, pagination is more important for producing a film than writing one; if you just want to write a screenplay then Marked does a bang-up job of previewing formatting for you. Quit whining about page numbers (, Jon,) and write your damn movie.</p>

<p>Marked 2’s Fountain support, out of the box, doesn’t support non-script elements, such as notes, sections and synopses. All of these elements get stripped when the document is opened in Marked. This makes a lot of sense since Marked provides final output preview, however I also think there is some value in seeing inline notes and structure. A toggle to see them would be nice, or at the very least have them parsed so that sections are navigable in the Table of Contents view.</p>

<p>As far as I can tell there are only two bits of the Fountain syntax that are currently unsupported: dual dialogue and centered text. Dual dialogue, I should mention, is technically supported in Marked 2’s built in Fountain parser, however it displays improperly. Try it. I’m sure this will get fixed in an update.</p>

<p>The biggest change I’d like to see to Marked 2’s Fountain implementation is for it to be more customizable. Custom CSS loading gets turned off when you load a <code>.fountain</code> document. If you want to see, say sections and synopses, or you want to turn off bold slug lines in Marked, the only way to do it right now is to load your script with <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/02/08/fountain-for-marked/">Fountain for Marked</a>. And the only way to do that is to rename your document’s extension to anything other than <code>.fountain</code>. Or keep using the original version of <a href="http://markedapp.com">Marked</a>, which is still available and supported.</p>

<p>One other customization niggle is the way Marked 2 loads Courier Prime. The app includes the regular and bold versions of the font, but neither the italic nor the bold italic versions. Italic text is rendered in Marked but it doesn’t load the beautiful italic glyphs designed by Alan Dague-Greene. There is no option to look for the font locally, which would be nice. But I’m weird.</p>

<p>Brett’s Fountain implementation is extremely sophisticated and an excellent addition to the plain text screenwriter’s tool belt. I’ve said nothing of the rest of the advantages Marked 2 has to offer, like deep analysis of word usage, keyword search and readability statistics. There are a million reasons you should <a href="http://marked2app.com">go give Brett $12</a> for his app right now. Fountain is but one of them.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I still think it’s nuts that Fountain has an app ecosystem as big as it does these days.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Fountain Characters in Editorial]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/09/03/fountain-characters-in-editorial/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T15:13:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/09/03/fountain-characters-in-editorial</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My pal Gabe Weatherhead <a href="http://www.macdrifter.com/2013/09/fountain-characters-with-editorial-sprinkling-in-python.html" title="Fountain Characters with Editorial: Sprinkling in Python">came through</a> when I asked if it would be possible to make an <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/editorial/id673907758?mt=8&amp;uo=4&amp;at=11l5Fb">Editorial</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> workflow to make typing characters in <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain</a> easier:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In Fountain, character names consist of a single line in all caps following a new empty line. Jonathan wanted a workflow that would capture a characters name as a snippet so it could be easily reused after the first time it was created. I came up with this workflow to create something similar.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Come for the workflow, stay for the workflow building and Python tutorial. Gabe is great at explaining code in plain English.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Affiliate link. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
