<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Messages | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/messages/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Five Years]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/04/02/five-years/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-02T15:25:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/04/02/five-years</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/SB6ogwU8Nys "></iframe></div></p>

<p>Five years and change ago, <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2009/03/23/welcome-to-the-candler-blog/">I launched <em>the candler blog</em></a>, my home for “movie reviews, cinema essays, personal rants and the like…” This wasn’t my first crack at a blog, but it’s the one that stuck. And what a ride it’s been so far.</p>

<p>I’ve <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2009/08/07/film-anxiety-and-legalese-an-interview-with-andrew-bujalski/">interviewed filmmakers</a>, <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2011/10/11/drives-judaism/">sparked debate</a> and even helped a few people <a href="http://candlerblog.com/projects/">better use Mac productivity apps</a> along the way. This site allowed me to become involved in the <a href="http://fountain.io">Fountain plain-text screenwriting project</a>. This site is how I landed a gig at <a href="http://heebmagazine.com"><em>Heeb Magazine</em></a>. <em>The candler blog</em> of today is nothing I could ever have imagined five years ago.</p>

<p>Let me also mention the contributors who helped make the site what it is: my friends <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2011/01/10/the-sunrise-12-of-10/">Sunrise Tippeconnie</a> and <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2009/09/17/two-well-oiled-machines-an-interview-with-filmmaker-henry-jaglom-on-editing-and-the-digital-revolution/">Daniel Kremer</a>. At the beginning I thought the candler blog would be a full-fledged outlet, with a staff of writers covering a range of topics. Over time I turned it into my personal blog, but their contributions still mean the world to me.</p>

<p>A trap that I often fall into is viewing each of the site’s milestones as a victory. When traffic is high, for example, I always get this silly feeling inside that I’ve “arrived.” When a writer or outlet I admire links to me, I think I’ve accomplished something. But that’s all bullshit. Achieving small successes is easy; maintaining the site is hard. I bring this up here merely to point out (mostly to myself) that five years is nothing. I am sentimental and proud, but there is so much more to be written (and so much I regret <em>not</em> writing over the years). There is plenty of work ahead.</p>

<p>So I wanted to just say thank you. Thank you for sticking with <em>the candler blog</em>. Thank you for your patience. Here’s to the next five years.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dispatches from OKC: Day 5]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/15/dispatches-from-okc-day-5/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-15T11:11:17+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/15/dispatches-from-okc-day-5</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The internet has been touch and go the past two days, and I’m on a friend’s
computer instead of my own, so I can’t add the usual flair you have come to
know and love to this post. Even with the fest completed, this continues to be
an intensely film-related vacation. After a buffet breakfast at a place called
Ingrid’s Kitchen, I headed over to the best bookstore in Oklahoma City, Full
Circle. Designed with all kinds of nooks and crannies and rolling ladders, it
is a store whose selection is not only Okie specific, but wide ranging. It’s
design encourages discovery and their staff are super friendly. No one paid me
to say that, seriously.</p>

<p>I went to Full Circle because my friend, Sunrise Tippeconnie, was signing a
book in which an essay of his is featured. The book is <em><a href="http://www.fortysixthstarpress.com/?page_id=265&amp;c
ategory=1&amp;product_id=5">Sooner Cinema:
Oklahoma Goes to the Movies</a></em> and I’m in the process of reading it. Quite
interesting. This state has a long history of making movies and being
portrayed in them. Which brings me to my next point.</p>

<p>The talk of the town right now is Michael Winterbottom’s <em>The Killer Inside
Me</em>, which is shooting here right now. The film has brought stars Casey
Affleck, Jessica Alba, and Ned Beatty. During the final day of deadCENTER they
had blocked off streets downtown and filled them with 1950s cars. Last night I
headed to Cookie’s, a tiny bar with a lot of heart, for the Cast and Crew
more-than-halfway-through-production party. It was a nice time with some
wonderful karaoke singers. The only celeb to show up was Mr. Beatty, and he
was a gentleman.</p>

<p>I love hanging out with film crews. They are so much more tolerable than
filmmakers because they rarely want to talk about movies. After the bar I went
straight to a Sonic for the second time today. For those of you who don’t know
about Sonic, well, you just have to drive until you find one. I got an Ocean
Water Slushie and some onion rings. They tasted delicious after drinking a
Pacifico cerveza.</p>

<p>We are off to the Wichita Mountains now, probably no more film to deal with
today. I still owe you all some reiews and you’ll get them, but probably not
until I’m back in New York. Poke around the site in the meantime, there’s a
lot going on here.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[welcome to the candler blog]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/03/23/welcome-to-the-candler-blog/"/>
    <updated>2009-03-23T09:21:01+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/03/23/welcome-to-the-candler-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>My great grandfather was an egg candler in Philadelphia. The job was
relatively simple. Hold an egg up to the light and determine its health. Some
eggs would be healthy enough to incubate and hatch while others would end up
in omelets and vaudeville acts. There was more to it, of course. Candlers like
my great grandfather had to have a finely tuned eye to make an informed
decision thousands of times a day.</p>

<p>We here at <strong>the candler blog</strong> try to apply the same methodology and care to
popular culture. We will do our best to hold anything that comes across our
radar up to a candle, so to speak. Looking at something on the surface is
rarely enough to determine its place in the world; instead we will try to
dissect it, see through it, understand it.</p>

<p>At least, this is the hope for <strong>the candler blog</strong>. For now, we will stick to
what we know: movies. Movie reviews, cinema essays, personal rants and the
like will be our bread and butter for the time being. We encourage your input
and want to make this an open space for all aspiring candlers out there.</p>

<p>We’ll let you know more about who we are and what our goals are in the weeks
to come, but for now, enjoy reading what we have. See you soon.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
