<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: humor | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/humor/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Original SPIDER-MAN!!! Eisenstein's OCTOBER!! BABY BOOM!! Only $11.53 each for 24 hours in the JercVAULT!!]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/01/jercvault-201/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-01T10:27:32+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/01/jercvault-201</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/dvdstack.png"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/dvdstack.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>Jerc here, and you heard right. Every movie in Amazon’s Library is available
today only at $11.53 per disc! You just have to buy them all at once.
$783,429,041.00 gets you every movie ever!!! That’s over a 70% savings. Amazon
is even throwing in their entire VHS library ABSOLUTELY FREE. I wouldn’t be
telling you about it if it weren’t true, obviously, so go get it now.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/raiders_of_the_lost_ark_government_warehouse2.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/raiders_of_the_lost
_ark_government_warehouse2.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<h1 id="stock-up-for-weddings-christenings-purim-and-the-end-of-days-70-off-for">Stock up for weddings, christenings, purim and the end of days!! 70% off for</h1>
<p>24 hours only!!!!!</p>

<p>You get everything in this package. No film is left behind.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/img4832181.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/img4832181.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.c
om/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/B00001U0E1.01.LZZZZZZZ.gif.jpeg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-cont
ent/uploads/2010/04/B00001U0E1.01.LZZZZZZZ.gif.jpeg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/ewokadventure0gl.jpg"><img src="http://www.
candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/ewokadventure0gl.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/514A2F31GFL.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog
/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/514A2F31GFL.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/clue-dvd.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/clue-dvd.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/october.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/october.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/419HM2NJ8XL.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/419HM2NJ8XL.jpg" alt="" /></a><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com
/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/5150VDWPNJL._SL500.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/5150VDWPNJL._SL500.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The only film you don’t get in this deal is the finest piece of Americana we
have. The greatest American movie ever made is the only disc left out of this,
but you probably already own it anyway. Christopher Nolan’s masterpiece, <em>The
Dark Knight</em>, will not be included in this deal because Amazon assumes every
American already got is as a gift last hanukkah.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/DarkknightDVD.jpg"><img src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/DarkknightDVD.jpg" alt="" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Revewe: Clash of the Titans]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/01/revewe-clash-of-the-titans/"/>
    <updated>2010-04-01T08:17:40+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2010/04/01/revewe-clash-of-the-titans</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.candle
rblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2010/04/rememberthetitans_pg01.jpg"><img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-
content/uploads/2010/04/rememberthetitans_pg01-300x150.jpg" alt="Not Clash of the Titans - Happy April Fools" /></a>Move over
<em>Avatar</em>, there’s a new king of 3D in town and his name just happens to be
Persius. Where else can you see Sam Worthington jumping onto CG birds? Not in
that $500 million film. Support independent filmmaking and definitely give a
click to Louis Leterrier’s greatest film since <em>Hulk</em>. <em>Clash of the Titans</em>
is a mile a minute thrill ride that sucks you in early and never lets go. How?
Because it’s 3 frickin’ D.</p>

<p>The film opens in the heavens, just like all Greek mythology films should. As
we whip around space and time, our eyes are vacuum sealed to every frenetic
movement. In plain old 2D, we would never get the full Greek effect, but since
this film adds the real-time additional graphics, our minds get blown right
away. It is truly the most amazing film I’ve seen this quarter, so far.</p>

<p>The team behind this film met the daunting task of a remake quite well. Though
the original film, directed by Ray Harryhausen, is regarded by many as an
untouchable classic of the cinema, the problem with that 1963 film was that
they hadn’t yet invented 3D. It looks dumb now looking back on it, but for
it’s time it really was a major advancement. Except for the 3D, this is
basically a shot for shot remake, except Hercules is completely written out of
the plot. The only place where they lose points is for completely stealing the
look and feel of <em>300.</em> Maybe it is meant as an homage to Zack Snyder, whose
unrelenting artistry compels filmmakers around the world.</p>

<p><em>Sam Worthington is truly the actor of our times, especially for his ability
to jump  onto birds. I don’t know how he does it, but I head he trains parkour
about three hours every day. Liam Neeson brings his godly charm to the role of
Zeus. His brother, Hades, is portrayed with scathing accuracy by Josef
Fiennes, who is reunited with Liam for the first time since _Schindler’s
List</em>. It’s weird how they’re both type cast again as good guy and bad guy. Do
these guys have another note?_</p>

<p>Finally, I want to mention all the animosity that has been brewing about this
film. A lot of people are talking about how they added the 3D after they shot
the film in 2D, as if this somehow cheapens the effect. This is total
bullcrap. This movie looks absolutely amazing in 3D. Wah wah wah, you need to
pay an extra 10 or 12 dollars to see it 3D. Go back to your trust funds and
live a little. After all it’s a just a movie so who really cares about it
anyway? You should, that’s why you pay the extra price to see an amazing 3D
movie. The titles practically fly right at your face! I hope Jim Cameron
didn’t see this because he’s gonna be pissed that Zeus stole his thunder,
literally.</p>

<hr />

<h4 id="april-fools">April Fools’!</h4>

<p>If you are a new reader to the candler blog, then I welcome you and I hope you
take a poke around. If you are a regular then I hope you quickly realized that
something was up the second you laid eyes on this post.</p>

<p>The above post is a parody of the worst film writing I have seen out there.
Besides the typos, incomplete (or overlong) sentences, and misinformed facts,
the real trouble with this review is that it doesn’t really say anything. That
means it isn’t criticism at all, it’s just a rant.</p>

<p>I believe that the film writing we do here, most of the time, goes beyond the
rantings and ravings of a film-loving lunatic. There’s a time and a place for
that, but it doesn’t always lead somewhere you want to be. Click around the
candler blog and see what you find. I hope you find that critical writing is
alive and well…on the internet…on a blog.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Great Movie Blogger Spoof]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/17/great-movie-blogger-spoof/"/>
    <updated>2009-04-17T08:31:06+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/04/17/great-movie-blogger-spoof</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Oh SNL, you rib us bloggers so perfectly. I love this because of how
frighteningly accurate it is of so many snarks out there on the interwebs. And
for my latest takes on movies and such, check out my new site, <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/">the canler
blog</a>. It’s rarely written while clutching an
iced latte, but I think you’ll like it nonetheless. Enjoy.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
