<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: News | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/news/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Final Word on #pointergate]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/11/14/hodges-for-president/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T15:21:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/11/14/hodges-for-president</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Minneapolis Mayor Betsy Hodges, who rose to national fame last week after a local news station claimed she threw a gang sign while working to get out the vote, gets <a href="http://mayorhodges.com/2014/11/13/pointergate/">the last word on #pointergate</a> (emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One frightening implication of the KSTP story and police union President Delmonico’s support of that story is their implicit assumption that I should use stereotypes to assess with whom I should or should not meet or stand or talk. As The Onion once satirically wrote, “Stereotypes are a real time saver.” It is not a good basis for decision-making, however. <strong>It blunts the humanity of the person making the judgment and creates unnecessary separation between two people in a world where more, rather than less, human connection is needed for us to move forward as a community.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hodges for President.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Joan Rivers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/09/05/joan-rivers/"/>
    <updated>2014-09-05T18:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/09/05/joan-rivers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/09/dad-with-joan.jpg" title="Joan Rivers with my Father, 1991" ></p>

<p>I’ll miss Joan Rivers, who <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2014/09/05/arts/television/joan-rivers-dies.html">passed away yesterday</a>. I can’t really accept, yet, that she’s gone. The thing that really gets me is this: Rivers would have garnered some incredible material from her own death.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> The sadness of losing a legend is compounded by that fact that only her wit could make us laugh about it.</p>

<p>In 2010 I had the great pleasure of attending a roundtable question-and-answer session with her as part of the press blitz for the documentary <em>Joan Rivers: A Piece of Work</em>.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> It immediately became clear that she was “on,” performing for us in the small hotel conference room on the Upper East Side. She clarified that point, as I noted in my <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/joan-rivers-everyones-favorite-dirty-grandmother-talks-about-her-new-documentary/13016">resulting piece for <em>Heeb Magazine</em></a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“I’m a performer. A girlfriend of mine just told me she spent three weeks in Venice taking cooking classes. I thought, ‘I’d fucking kill myself.’ I’d rather go and perform.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That was Rivers. A comedian to the end. Another <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/chosen-film-_joan-rivers-a-piece-of-work_/5497">choice quote from the film</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“When a young comedienne comes up to me and says, ‘You paved the way for me’. . . Paved? Paved?!’ You want to say, ‘Go fuck yourself, I’m <em>still</em> paving it.’”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>There are so many great Joan moments that others have posted, but one of my personal favorites is still this clip from the documentary, where she takes the viewer into her card catalog of jokes.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/87yztkvEsIk "></iframe></div></p>

<p>There are funnier and more groundbreaking clips, for sure, but what always impressed me was Rivers’ tenacity. Joke-telling is hard work and she became a master not through magic but through sheer grit. She worked incredibly hard to make us laugh for decades. I, like most, had hoped to get a decade more.</p>

<p>That picture up top, by the way, is of <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=10204832414276895">my father’s band with Joan in 1991</a>. My dad is on the right. They served as the backup band for two nights for the Jewish Federation in Philadelphia. He has nothing but good things to say about the experience, which he still remembers like it was yesterday. This has been a common refrain in eulogies, obituaries and remembrances. No matter how poisonous her tongue may have been while performing, off stage she was nothing but charming. There’s a lesson there, I’m sure.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Imagine, if you will, what she would have done with the incredible correction in her aforelinked <em>New York Times</em> obituary: “An earlier version of a label that appeared with this obituary on the home page of NYTimes.com misstated the year of Ms. Rivers’s death. It was 2014, of course, not 1914.”<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>As part of my coverage of the film, I also recorded a <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2010/06/14/candlercast-17-talking-joan-rivers-with-ricki-stern-and-anne-sundberg/">podcast with the filmmakers Ricki Stern and Anne Sundberg</a> discussing Joan Rivers.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What I Wrote to Congress]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/16/letter-to-congress/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-16T01:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/16/letter-to-congress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>I have no idea what strikes a note with sitting Senators and representatives. But I know what I feel. Here’s what I sent to my representatives in Washington. Be my guest to copy this template.</em></p>

<p>Dear <strong>__</strong>_____,</p>

<p>I am writing you to ask that you take the necessary steps to end gun violence in the United States.</p>

<p>I am haunted by the imagery and the stories coming out of Newtown, Connecticut. This massacre is a moment of national mourning. But it also points to a grave national failing. We, collectively, failed the students at Sandy Hook Elementary. It is time to end the ongoing violence in this country. Only elected officials like yourself, <strong>__</strong>_____, can right this injustice.</p>

<p>I was in junior high school when the shootings at Columbine High School took place. That event rocked the nation and forced children, like myself at the time, to confront the very real dangers of the world. The similarities between Columbine and the school I attended growing up in Pennsylvania were daunting. If it could happen there, it could happen anywhere.</p>

<p>[Sir or Madam], that was over thirteen years ago. Nothing has changed.</p>

<p>I can no longer abide this destruction, this bloodbath being perpetrated on American soil. I put it to you, <strong>__</strong>_____, and your colleagues in Washington to save us from ourselves; to protect us from the killing machines that have taken too many lives in this country this year alone.</p>

<p>The time for complacency is over. The time for feints and denialism and bickering has passed. You must act now to make it more difficult for anyone to get a gun. You must act to limit the firepower available on the market. You must end the illegal gun trade that goes on in the US and regulate the legal sale of weapons so that killers cannot perpetrate these mass shootings anymore.</p>

<p>As a child I thought that there could never be an event more tragic than Columbine. How many more times must I be proven wrong? How many lives will it take before congress stands up and demands that something be done to stop this senseless violence.</p>

<p>I beg of you to effect change, <strong>__</strong>_____. I ask you to save the lives of countless Americans with your vote. End gun violence now.</p>

<p>Sincerely,</p>

<p>Jonathan Poritsky</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Recognizing We Have a Problem]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/14/we-have-a-problem/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-14T14:12:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/14/we-have-a-problem</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>By now I assume most readers have heard of the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/15/nyregion/shooting-reported-at-connecticut-elementary-school.html">tragic shooting</a> at Sandy Hook Elementary School in Newtown, Connecticut. Just after 9:30am today an adult gunman opened fire throughout the school. As of this writing, 27 are reported dead, 18 of them children.</p>

<p>The incident has clogged all of my social feeds, with people, myself included, offering condolences, prayers, opinions, ruminations and the like. Beneath all of it, though, is a sort of backlash against those who bring up politics. Either it’s too soon or too opportunistic or too ghoulish to talk about such things at this juncture.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<p>Fuck that.</p>

<p>Wake up.</p>

<p>Americans are being slaughtered. Coast to coast. Regardless of age, race, religion. At schools, movie theaters, houses of worship and on city streets. We have, to put it mildly, a big problem.</p>

<p>So let’s figure it out.</p>

<p>The most important thing for us to do today, as a nation, is to recognize that we have a problem, that there have been a string of senseless murders that have made 2012 a depressingly bloody year. And recognizing that we can and must do something to prevent them.</p>

<p>That’s not being political. That’s being an adult.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I’m not going to link any specific tweets or posts. I’ll bet I don’t need to; most peoples’ social circles probably run a similar gamut of what I’m seeing.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Racist Teens Forced to Answer for Tweets]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/09/hate-tweets/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-09T14:20:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/09/hate-tweets</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Tracie Egan Morrissey <a href="http://jezebel.com/5958993/racist-teens-forced-to-answer-for-tweets-about-the-nigger-president">for Jezebel</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>There was an abundance of <a href="http://jezebel.com/5958490/twitter-racists-react-to-that-nigger-getting-reelected/gallery/1">hate speech on Twitter</a> after Obama’s reelection, with people hurling violent and racial epithets. Many of those tweeters were teenagers whose public Twitter accounts feature their real names and advertise their participation in the sports programs at their respective high schools. Calls were placed to the principals and superintendents of those schools to find out how calling the president—or any person of color, for that matter—a “nigger” and a “monkey” jibes with their student conduct code of ethics.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I am conflicted about Morrissey’s piece. It’s one thing to publicly shame dumb tweeters, as BuzzFeed, Reddit and the like do on nearly a daily basis. Hell, <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/tweets-about-drakes-re-bar-mitzvah/35389">I’ve even done it</a>. It’s another thing entirely to go after each one personally and make sure their educators know about their transgression. As if adults in general weren’t already an angst-inducing force, now the media comes a-knockin’ to tattle?</p>

<p>I’m not trying to excuse these pissants, but two lessons come to mind.</p>

<p>First off, I am part of the last generation to have grown up with a modicum of Internet privacy. My first experiences with the Web involved obscuring my identity while living large publicly by way of various usernames. Of course, that’s all changed, with online identities basically being opt-out privacy-wise.</p>

<p>As our lives move online, the whole world becomes fair game, even idiotic (and disgusting) teenage ramblings. Nearly all of the kids described in the article have since deleted their accounts. Perhaps Eric Schmidt’s <a href="http://online.wsj.com/article/SB10001424052748704901104575423294099527212.html">creepy 2010 prophecy</a>, that young people dicking around on social media will eventually have to change their names, will come to fruition sooner rather than later.</p>

<p>The other lesson is that, now that the ugliness of the election has passed, we need to come together as a nation whether we like it or not. The numbers and the tweets exposed by Jezebel don’t lie: a great deal of the United States is virulently, unapologetically racist. Morrissey’s solution, a public drubbing, won’t make a dent in the ideologies of the millions of Americans who still cannot accept a black man as President; in fact it will likely push them further out to sea.</p>

<p>If nothing else the article could serve as a means for discussion, and if people are confronting racism head on we just might have a shot of licking it. Or at least of helping a few kids change their ways.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
