<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Television | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/television/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[James Burrows on Bullseye]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/06/james-burrows/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-06T15:51:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/06/james-burrows</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>James Burrows isn’t a household name, but his work sure is. His groundbreaking direction on <em>Cheers</em> (which he co-created with Les and Glen Charles) set the tone for most of the successful sitcoms of the 80s and 90s. To this day his fingerprints are all over pretty much any three-camera television show.</p>

<p>Jesse Thorn interviewed Burrows <a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/bullseye/bullseye-jesse-thorn-james-burrows-future-islands">on this week’s <em>Bullseye</em></a> and it’s just a phenomenal listen. He’s quite modest about his work, but also very exacting about what it is that sets him apart.</p>

<p>Here is my favorite part, from <a href="https://overcast.fm/+lVXnMbRo/22:32">around 22:30</a>. Burrows is discussing his work on <em>Taxi</em> (he directed seventy-five episodes).</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You had Judd [Hirsch] who had his mind on a hundred other things, which is how Judd works. We called him “the piddler,” because he was always thinking about stuff. But when he got…when the show was on, he was unbelievable. He and Teddy Danson are two of the greatest centers you’ve ever seen in a show.</p>

  <p>Judd, you know, didn’t have a lot of funny stuff on <em>Taxi</em> but his facial reactions when he was dealing with the weirdos are unbelievable. You could always cut to him. And the same with Ted.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That precise knowledge about one actor’s face is what sets Burrows apart. Go give the <a href="http://www.maximumfun.org/bullseye/bullseye-jesse-thorn-james-burrows-future-islands">whole episode</a> a listen.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Obama on Letterman and What I’ll Miss in Late Night Television]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/05/letterman-the-interviewer/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T16:58:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/05/letterman-the-interviewer</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/05/obama-letterman.jpg" title="President Obama on Letterman" ></p>

<p>A little over two weeks ago, <em>Conan</em> staff writer Andrés du Bouchet got himself in a bit of trouble by <a href="http://uproxx.com/tv/2015/04/state-of-late-night-comedy">whining about the state of late night comedy on Twitter</a>. Since deleted, here’s what the tweets amounted to:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Comedy in 2015 needs a severe motherfucking shakeup. No celebrities, no parodies, no pranks, no mash-ups or hashtag wars. I’m fat. … and shove your lip-synching up your ass.</p>

  <p>Prom King Comedy. That’s what I call all this shit. You’ve let the popular kids appropriate the very art form that helped you deal. Fuck. None of the funniest stuff ever involved celebrity cameos.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>The tweets were in poor taste, but they struck a chord with me. The target of the criticism was surely Jimmy Fallon, but Jimmy Kimmel seems just as guilty. I don’t think it’s fair to necessarily call either host “the popular kids,” but “Prom King Comedy” rings true. Which is to say not really comedy at all, just dress up skits.</p>

<p>I can’t watch Fallon’s <em>Tonight Show</em> because I simply have no interest in the snackable, made-for-YouTube look-at-what-I-can-do bits. His show may be fun, but I don’t find it funny and, generally speaking, I wouldn’t really call it a comedy show. The sketches feel like a crutch, propping up the host to keep him from interviewing guests.</p>

<p><em>The Tonight Show</em> today is wildly popular, and I don’t begrudge anyone for enjoying it before bed (or, more likely and by design, at work the next day). But to me it’s not a late night talk show. It’s a different thing than what I grew up with; a different thing than what I want in the evenings. And that’s fine. Perhaps the comedy talk show is done for. Maybe we’ve moved on from a format that worked for decades to something else.</p>

<p>Which brings me to <a href="http://gothamist.com/2015/05/05/obama_letterman_goodbye.php">David Letterman interviewing Barack Obama last night</a>. Letterman, the elder statesman of late night television, is closing in on his final show. He’s stacking the deck with high profile guests and longtime friends on each outing. Having the President come on seems appropriate for the occasion.</p>

<p>It has been common for politicians to stop in on comedy shows for decades now to show off their softer side. These shows appeal to a younger, often-times not-politically minded crowd. The hosts are often friendly and welcoming in a way that makes it easy to get your agenda out in front of the public. Plus you get to be funny and appear soft and relatable. Everyone wins.</p>

<p>But it’s always been different with Letterman. He is a brilliant comedian, but an even better broadcaster. He has an extra muscle that allows him to know what makes great television, and he’s never been afraid to use those skills in front of the camera. On Letterman’s stage, no guest, no matter how powerful can outsmart him.</p>

<p>Perhaps the most famous example of Letterman’s broadcasting (and, arguably, political) prowess occurred on September 24, 2008, when John McCain, then deep in his failed campaign for president, canceled a <em>Late Show</em> appearance so he could go back to Washington to work on the faltering economy. Letterman’s response was to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aR5FGkpfsbM">tear into the presidential hopeful</a>. His master stroke was broadcasting the CBS News live feed of McCain, still in New York at the time of the taping, getting his makeup put on in preparation for an interview with Katie Couric. As Bill Carter puts it in his excellent  <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/book/the-war-for-late-night/id386084654?mt=11&amp;at=11l5Fb"><em>The War for Late Night</em></a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The event became part of the news cycle in the race. McCain had stiffed Letterman, and Dave made him pay. He got more licks in on McCain for several nights after, and McCain ultimately had to make a date in his otherwise packed calendar to return to New York (a state he was hardly going to win) on October 16 to formally seek Dave’s pardon.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>It’s  hard to think of any other late night host, past or present, who could have pulled off such a stunt. McCain went head-to-head with Letterman and lost. Today we think of our television personalities, even many of our news anchors, as lightweights, fluffy sounding-boards against which any candidate, analyst or celebrity can speak rehearsed talking points. That’s never been Letterman.</p>

<p>His interview with Obama last night certainly wasn’t hard hitting. The President rolled out a few obviously scripted zingers and Letterman tried to lighten the mood. But for the most part the conversation was deeply serious. They discussed poverty, race relations, policing, riots and how to help disabled veterans when they come home.</p>

<p>Where Letterman is a deft broadcaster, Obama is a staunch politician. And so almost none of what comes out of his mouth is off the cuff. Yet there is something so refreshing about seeing him asked about specific, major issues of the day.</p>

<p>Letterman is so good at getting to the heart of big questions, the conversation seemed like it could go in any direction. I wondered while watching, for example, if Letterman might ask the president to explain his sweeping drone strike strategy. Only a week and a half ago a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/24/world/asia/2-qaeda-hostages-were-accidentally-killed-in-us-raid-white-house-says.html">contrite Obama admitted to the accidental killing</a> of American and Italian hostages. Though Letterman didn’t go there, he could have, and he could have done it in a way that no other broadcaster today could.</p>

<p>And that’s what I’m going to miss when he’s off the air. Letterman holds court in the Ed Sullivan theater. He can mete out truth from his guests while keeping them comfortable enough to have a few laughs. That mix of off-the-wall comedy (earlier in the show Will Ferrell reprised his SNL Harry Caray impersonation from the audience) and plainspoken talk show is what makes late night television such a fertile and interesting space.</p>

<p>All of that is a long-winded explanation not only of why I’ll miss Letterman, but, ultimately, why I don’t like Fallon’s <em>Tonight Show</em> and its ilk. As Obama explained to his questioner the state of race relations in our country today, I turned to my girlfriend and asked if she could ever imagine Fallon doing an interview like this. She laughed.</p>

<p>“No way. They’d be playing the dunce game by now,” referring to a trivia sketch that ends when either the guest or Fallon, each in a pointy dunce cap, pops a water balloon positioned over his or her head. Fun, but funny?</p>

<p>There is room for so many types of shows and hosts, but I hope that we don’t lose the format that has been a cornerstone of American broadcasting for so long. As the powerful get savvier, so too must our interviewers find ways to break down the barriers to honest conversation. Letterman is the best at it. Hopefully soon someone else will be.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I actually think Stephen Colbert, Letterman’s successor, is great at precisely this type of interview. His learning curve on CBS will be whether or not he can be likable up against the likes of Fallon, whose populism, I don’t know if I’ve made clear, has clouded his ability to be much more than friendly face.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[HBO In Talks With Apple To Be Launch Partner For ‘HBO Now’]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/04/hbo-now-question-mark/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-04T17:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/04/hbo-now-question-mark</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Big scoop from Michael Learmonth <a href="http://www.ibtimes.com/hbo-talks-apple-be-launch-partner-coming-web-service-hbo-now-exclusive-1835882">over at the International Business Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>HBO is in talks with Apple to make Apple TV one of the launch partners for its highly anticipated streaming service when it debuts next month. HBO and streaming partner Major League Baseball Advanced Media are working to have the standalone service, called “HBO Now,” ready to launch in April in conjunction with the premiere of the fifth season of “Game of Thrones,” according to sources familiar with their plans.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>$15 a month. No cable subscription required.</p>

<p>Maybe we’ll hear just a bit about this on Monday when Apple has its Apple Watch event. If Apple landed an exclusive launch window it would be <em>huge</em> for the Apple TV. If for even just a few weeks into the latest season of <em>Game of Thrones</em> Apple TV is the only device you can get standalone HBO on, they would sell a bundle without updating the hardware.</p>

<p>Time will tell.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Junk Netflix Reporting at Variety]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/08/07/junk-numbers/"/>
    <updated>2014-08-07T18:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/08/07/junk-numbers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/08/hoc-fu.jpg" title="Frank Underwood’s Cufflinks" ></p>

<p>This morning Todd Spangler, <em>Variety’s</em> New York Digital Editor, published a piece with the juicy headline, “<a href="http://variety.com/2014/digital/news/netflix-originals-house-of-cards-orange-is-the-new-black-watched-by-fewer-than-half-of-subs-study-finds-1201277702/">Netflix Originals ‘House of Cards,’ ‘Orange Is the New Black’ Watched by Fewer Than Half of Subs, Study Finds</a>.” Two things jump out at me: Netflix does not release viewership and half of all subscribers is a whole lot of people. Oh, and also “Study Finds” feels like a big red flag.</p>

<p>But I’ll bite. What’ve you got, Spangler?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Despite high awareness, fewer than half of Netflix users have ever watched one of the company’s two big originals, according to a new study from research and consulting firm Centris Marketing Science. Centris found that 44% of Netflix members have ever watched “OITNB,” while 31% said the same for “House of Cards.” Among Netflix subs, 94% have heard of “OITNB” and 89% have heard of “HoC” (while 72% of non-subscribers said they were aware of either series). For the study, Centris polled 562 U.S. households from July 17-20.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a small sample and a short time period. Good on Spangler for at least publishing as much. It’s strange though, that there is no link provided to this “new study,” or even to Centris’ site.</p>

<p>So I put in some elbow grease and found that the “study” is actually <a href="http://centris.com/NetflixOriginals.html">just an infographic</a> Centris made. Every so often I get form emails from junk marketing companies asking me to publish an infographic that <em>the candler blog’s</em> readers might be interested in. This Centris infographic smacks of that desperation.</p>

<p>Let’s dispense with this right now: the Centris numbers are meaningless. The time period is too small to tell us anything meaningful. It’s an embarrassment that <em>Variety</em> even published them.</p>

<p>What’s <em>more</em> annoying, though, is that Spangler doesn’t even take his bunk conceit and run it against readily available numbers from Netflix. The company puts out detailed and highly readable quarterly reports on their <a href="http://ir.netflix.com">investor relations page</a>, the most recent of which <a href="http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/NFLX/2745669999x0x769748/9b21df7f-743c-4f0f-94da-9f13e384a3d2/July2014EarningsLetter_7.21.14_final.pdf">came out on July 21st (PDF)</a>, a date that lines up almost perfectly with the Centris “study.”</p>

<p>Netflix reports 36.52 million domestic streaming subscribers. Centris claims 44% of Netflix subscribers have viewed <em>Orange is the New Black</em> and 31% have viewed <em>House of Cards</em>. That would mean <em>Orange is the New Black</em> has been seen by over 16 million subscribers; <em>House of Cards</em> by over 11 million. Here’s Spangler again:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Both “HoC” and “OITNB” recently launched second seasons. By comparison, season two of “Game of Thrones” had an average gross audience of 11.6 million viewers across linear TV, DVR, on-demand and HBO Go. That would represent in the neighborhood of 41% of HBO’s total subscriber base, meaning Netflix’s “Orange Is the New Black” may actually be outperforming “GoT” relatively speaking.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is a nonsense comparison. Streaming has expanded a great deal in the two years since the second season of <em>Game of Thrones</em> premiered. For example, Netflix only (<em>only</em>) had <a href="http://files.shareholder.com/downloads/NFLX/2745669999x0x562104/9ebb887b-6b9b-4c86-aeff-107c1fb85ca5/Investor%20Letter%20Q1%202012.pdf">22.02 million streaming subscribers (PDF)</a> back then. Spangler at least admits that <em>Orange is the New Black</em> might actually be a hit. What I don’t get is why the Netflix subscriber numbers aren’t brought up.</p>

<p>Also, why is the headline and the tone of the whole article so negative? If you’re going to make the foolhardy decision to believe the Centris numbers, I don’t see how they point to anything other than great news for Netflix. 16+ million viewers, even if it’s only for part of a single episode, is astonishing.</p>

<p>I think I know what happened here. Centris’ silly infographic paints the viewership numbers as a bland net negative: “Despite high awareness, fewer than half of Netflix subscribers have watched each show.” Wait a second, doesn’t that sound <em>exactly</em> like a sentence in Spangler’s piece? “Despite high awareness, fewer than half of Netflix users have ever watched one of the company’s two big originals…“</p>

<p>Basically <em>Variety</em> published the opinion of a market research firm, copying the lede word for word. <a href="https://www.wordnik.com/words/boffo">Boffo</a> journalism, folks.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[That time when Toronto television did the movies right]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/30/saturday-night-at-the-movies/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T16:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/30/saturday-night-at-the-movies</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Ed Conroy <a href="http://www.blogto.com/film/2013/08/that_time_when_toronto_television_did_the_movies_right/">for blogTO</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Long before time-shifting VCRs, DVDs, Pay-TV and Netflix allowed movie lovers us to mainline with all the ease of turning on a tap to get water, TVOntario treated Toronto denizens to double helpings of film classics on Saturday nights, doled out generously by the most perfectly employed man in the history of television - <a href="http://www.cbc.ca/news/arts/story/2011/07/22/obit-elwy-yost.html">Elwy Yost</a>, the movie host with the most.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This is the first I’ve heard of Elwy Yost, but, from the clips Conroy collected, it looks like Torontonians were spoiled during his tenure.</p>

<p>Yost hosted <a href="http://snam.tvo.org"><em>Saturday Night at the Movies</em></a> from 1974 to 1999 and passed away in 2011. The show will air its final episode tomorrow night.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
