<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Filmmaking | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/filmmaking/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A Brief History of PG-13]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/04/brief-history-of-pg-13/"/>
    <updated>2015-05-04T14:52:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/05/04/brief-history-of-pg-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Cute video from <a href="https://thedissolve.com/news/5588-and-now-a-very-special-video-essay-about-the-histo/"><em>The Dissolve</em></a>.</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/IKpJIWGNvLc "></iframe></div></p>

<p>See also: Chris Klimek’s December 2014 <a href="http://thedissolve.com/features/movie-of-the-week/839-the-ongoing-failure-of-the-pg-13-rating/">“The ongoing failure of the PG-13 rating”</a> and, if you have a bit more time, Kirby Dick’s 2006 <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0493459"><em>This Film Is Not Yet Rated</em></a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[No Fuckhead You Are Not a Storyteller]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/30/the-mantle-of-bullshit/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-30T17:05:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/07/30/the-mantle-of-bullshit</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>That’s your story? That’s a fucking bullshit story. That’s boring.</p><footer><strong>Stefan Sagmeister</strong> <cite><a href='https://vimeo.com/98368484'>You Are Not a Storyteller</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/98368484 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>(via <a href="http://www.juxtapoz.com/design/no-fuckhead-you-are-not-a-storyteller">Juxtapoz</a> h/t <a href="https://twitter.com/TheJewishDream/status/494529096940924930">Rafi</a>.)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Defining Cinematography]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/03/05/defining-cinematography/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-05T11:49:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/03/05/defining-cinematography</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/03/gravity.jpg" title="Sandra Bullock in Gravity" ></p>

<p>When <em>Gravity</em> took home awards for both cinematography (to Emmanuel Lubezki) and visual effects (to Timothy Webber, Chris Lawrence David Shirk and Neil Corbould) at the Oscars this past weekend, it got me thinking about the relationship between these two intertwined art forms. One can’t do most (though soon I would modify that to some) effects work without a camera, and, increasingly, one can’t shoot a film without the help of a skilled effects team. Are cinematography and visual effects actually that separate anymore?</p>

<p>So I poked around the old <a href="http://awardsdatabase.oscars.org/ampas_awards/BasicSearchInput.jsp">Oscar database</a>. Here are all of the films ever to win an Oscar for both cinematography<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> and visual effects:</p>

<ul>
  <li><em>Gravity</em> (2013)</li>
  <li><em>Life of Pi</em> (2012)</li>
  <li><em>Hugo</em> (2011)</li>
  <li><em>Inception</em> (2010)</li>
  <li><em>Avatar</em> (2009)</li>
  <li><em>The Lord of the Rings: The Fellowship of the Ring</em> (2001)</li>
  <li><em>Titanic</em> (1997)</li>
  <li><em>The Longest Day</em> (1962)</li>
  <li><em>Ben-Hur</em> (1959)</li>
  <li><em>The Thief of Bagdad</em> (1940)</li>
</ul>

<p>Ten films. Five of them in the last five years. This, to me, looks like a trend.</p>

<p>According to the Academy’s current bylaws, cinematography <a href="http://www.oscars.org/awards/academyawards/rules/86/rule08.html">isn’t narrowly defined</a>. Visual effects, on the other hand, <a href="http://www.oscars.org/awards/academyawards/rules/86/rule22.html">are</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Achievements shall be judged within the parameters defined by the executive committee and on the basis of:</p>

  <blockquote>
    <p>a. consideration of the contribution the visual effects make to the overall production and</p>

    <p>b. the artistry, skill and fidelity with which the visual illusions are achieved.</p>
  </blockquote>
</blockquote>

<p>And later on:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Visual effects, as an achievement or a craft, shall be determined by the Visual Effects Branch Executive Committee.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>No such dictum is directed at the Cinematographers Branch. Cinematography is just…cinematography.</p>

<p>I think it’s becoming clear that we <em>should</em> be questioning what is and what isn’t considered cinematography. In the case of <em>Gravity</em>, a film whose illusion is so closely tied to its plot, it’s fair to ask how much of that movie magic comes from the camera, how much comes from special effects. Would it even be possible to award one and not the other? How could Lubezki’s camera work possibly hold up without the stunning work of the effects team?</p>

<p>Another question: why not make animated features eligible in the cinematography category? Regardless of how, technologically, a film is animated, there is always a “camera” that has to be positioned, moved and controlled. As visual effects and cinematography coalesce, why shouldn’t animation and cinematography as well?  </p>

<p>For good measure, here’s how the Academy <a href="http://www.oscars.org/awards/academyawards/rules/86/rule07.html">defines an animated feature</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>An animated feature film is defined as a motion picture with a running time of more than 40 minutes, in which movement and characters’ performances are created using a frame-by-frame technique. Motion capture by itself is not an animation technique. In addition, a significant number of the major characters must be animated, and animation must figure in no less than 75 percent of the picture’s running time.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>That’s a good definition for now, but it will soon become more difficult to make the distinction between effects-laden work and an animated film. As the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncanny_valley">uncanny valley</a> shrinks, our perception of “what is filmmaking?” will only get broader. Perhaps the Academy’s definitions should broaden as well.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>From 1940 through 1967 (the 12th through 39th Oscar ceremonies) the Academy gave out two awards for cinematography, one for color and one for black-and-white. This had already become de rigeur for the Academy, which had given special awards out for color cinematography three years in a row before bestowing the first “Best Cinematography, Color” award upon Ernest Haller and Ray Rennahan for their work on <em>Gone With the Wind</em>.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Black Betty, A Camera With a Mac Mini Inside]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/29/black-betty/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-29T21:47:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/08/29/black-betty</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Joe Marine <a href="http://nofilmschool.com/2013/08/black-betty-si-2k-mini-digital-cinema-camera/">over at nofilmschool</a> reveals the Black Betty camera:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Black Betty is much more than a camera. It’s a complete cinema solution utilizing an Apple Mac Mini computer with a Silicon Imaging SI-2K Mini for the imager. It also happens to be the first single unit camera in existence capable of shooting, editing, and posting footage online, without the need for any other hardware.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I think Joe and the Black Betty team are over-playing this “shoot and edit” capability. Basically the video is recorded to the Mac Mini, so technically you could plug a monitor into it and cut away, but that sounds inconvenient.</p>

<p>However, Joe’s interview with the camera’s creators Adam Van Voorhis and Mike Szegedithey hints at some of the things one <em>could</em> do with the Black Betty, which is where things get interesting. </p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Adam: […] There’s nothing stopping you from taking Bluetooth keyboards and Bluetooth mice, and using them to do things like trigger the camera remotely. I’ve triggered the camera from hundreds of feet away with a Bluetooth mouse and it works, and that’s damn cool.</p>

  <p>Mike: Since it’s an Apple device, you could probably use Apple devices to trigger it.</p>

  <p>Adam: Sure. Anything that you can do with a Mac Mini, you can do with the camera.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Wi-Fi. Bluetooth. This is starting to sound like a camera that could make my old <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/05/google-wave-for-filmmakers-a-concept/">Google Wave for Filmmakers</a><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> concept possible.</p>

<p>Mac Minis turn up in so many creative places; it may be one of Apple’s best devices simply in terms of the scope of the projects it has made possible.</p>

<p>(via <a href="http://www.engadget.com/2013/08/29/black-betty-2k-camera-mac-mini/">Engadget</a>.)</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>Google Wave may be dead, but my original proposal was for a collaborative online hub where a project’s XML file could be cut by multiple editors. Proxy videos could be shot straight to shared storage so an editor could start cutting instantly miles away.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Goodbye, Roger]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/04/04/goodbye-roger/"/>
    <updated>2013-04-04T16:13:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/04/04/goodbye-roger</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2013/04/siskel-and-ebert.jpg" title="Gene Siskel and Roger Ebert" ></p>

<p>Sad news: <a href="http://www.suntimes.com/news/metro/17320958-418/roger-ebert-dies-at-70-after-battle-with-cancer.html">Roger Ebert has passed away</a>.</p>

<p>Writing on the Web had no greater champion than Ebert. He was encouraging, generous and humble. He didn’t care about the masthead under which your writing appeared. He would share anything he came across and enjoyed. He took joy in using his celebrity to shine light on the work of others and make film criticism an ever-expanding field.</p>

<p>I was once the recipient of his generosity. On January 22, 2012, Roger posted two links to the candler blog on Twitter and Facebook. As if that weren’t enough of a gesture, he very kindly <a href="https://www.facebook.com/RogerEbert/posts/284875718232348">said some nice things about me</a>. After that there was no going back for me; like it or not I was a writer online. Roger said so.</p>

<p>I bring up that experience because I know that he inspired many thousands as he did me. That may even be an understatement.</p>

<p>Besides his <a href="http://blogs.suntimes.com/ebert/2008/10/eberts_little_rule_book.html">little rule book</a>, there is one piece of wisdom of his that is always in my mind. From his foreword to Nicholas Jarecki’s <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Breaking-In-Directors-Their-Start/dp/0767906748"><em>Breaking In: How 20 Film Directors Got Their Start</em></a>, which I read at a very impressionable age:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It doesn’t matter if you go to film school or not, or which film school, or what you study. It doesn’t matter if you work on film or video, or what kind of camera you use. It doesn’t matter if you write in the morning, or at night, or on yellow pads or on a Macintosh. It doesn’t matter if you work as an intern or an apprentice, in Hollywood or Austin or anywhere else. It doesn’t matter what movies you watched or what books you read—as long as the answer is “a lot of them.” What matters is that you called yourself a movie director, and you made a movie.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Thank you, Roger. Your mark will be felt for generations to come.</p>

<p><em>Further Reading:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>I heard Roger speak in 2011. As ever, he was an inspiration: <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2011/09/28/ebert-last-night/">“Don’t be the next Roger Ebert, be the first you.”</a></li>
</ul>

<p>(photo via <a href="https://www.facebook.com/photo.php?fbid=586881327991537&amp;set=a.166962229983451.39817.162770253735982">Roger’s Facebook page</a>)</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
