<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Essay | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/essay/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Racism in Avatar: The Outer-Body Solution to Cultural Tensions]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/20/avatar-the-problematic-outer-body-solution-to-cultural-tensions/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-20T02:41:05+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/20/avatar-the-problematic-outer-body-solution-to-cultural-tensions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/avatar-teaser-trailer-4.jpg" title="Avatar Still" ></p>

<p>The use of 3D and advanced imaging/animation techniques allows for not just a technological advance, but serves as a racially problematic metaphor for <em>Avatar’s</em> narrative.</p>

<p>While the use of his technology has a tendency to impress simply in skin textures, and facial gestures, James Cameron’s real success has less to do with animation and compositing techniques and more to do with the over looked 3D technique of weight. The most impressive moment is when protagonist Jake Sully dashes through the forest, chased by a large predator at high speeds, only to find himself jumping over a cliff into a waterfall down below. While this is nothing new in any narrative of a similar type, what is new is the technology’s ability to draft the weight of the character through these different physical environments, and the manipulation of time, we are able to get closer to feeling these moments than in any other film for the simple fact that the camera has been placed, panned, and paced in the appropriate positions to allow for the most tactile understanding of air rushing at one’s body, as well as the initial slowing-down of energy once it submerges within water. While neither the scene nor the tools are necessarily anything new, the careful placement of vantage point is what allows for a very effective use beyond the normal 3D tricks.</p>

<p>While the surface imagery remains effective today, in a couple years we will be stunned by some new partial animation experiment. In that way <em>Avatar</em> is almost repetition of <em>The Phantom Menace</em>, and is perhaps a novelty in these areas. Both films share much in the way of technology advancements, animation production schedules and techniques, and excessive use of these abilities in a manner that overwhelms visuals on the screen at the expense of a scene’s narrative clarity. This animation approach, common for any special-effect heavy fantasy, consistently feels in antithesis to the conventional film production approach, which these films attempt to replicate. In normal film execution, the production team attempts to eliminate elements that are uncontrollable and distracting to the audience, so that the story and narrative of a scene are what is the focus. In such fantasy pictures there is a tendency to neglect this fact and add as much as possible to any given frame to replicate the multifaceted movement and imagery of the real world. The result for me are mixed feelings, as I expect to be able to focus on the scene’s emotional and narrative clarity only to find that this information is in constant conflict with busy environment the animation has rendered possible. Half way through the film, I removed my 3D glasses, and actually found the film to be more relaxing. I was able to focus on performance and story with much more focus.</p>

<p>Beyond the immediate response to the technology, Cameron’s attempt to comment on the experience of viewing becomes a narrative subtext. Jake is able to maneuver among creatures alien to his own body via the “avatar” body of the title, which allows him to integrate well into this foreign society so much that they accept him as their own. As the narrative progresses, he falls in love with one of this society which initiates the conflict: even though his emotional connection exists beyond his avatar body, the recognition of it will pull his relationships apart. What Jake learns is that this society is threatened by a human military-corporation (via a complete homage to Cameron’s own <em>Aliens</em> which includes Sigourney Weaver) that wishes to destroy their home to obtain natural resources. Because of his advantage of understanding both sides of the situation, Jake is placed in a position to mediate between sides. The society of which he’s become a part, discovers he is not of their world and they begin to distrust him, which becomes the driving force for the narrative conflicts in the second and third acts. The ability for Jake to view this new world through eyes that are similar to those of the society alien to his own, it suggests a means to comprehend and understand the problems and beliefs of that world. Just as Jake is able to “view” this new world via his avatar body, the audience is also able to “view” this world via their 3D glasses, supporting a strong character-identification.</p>

<p>I have no initial problems with this setup, yet when looking closer to the characterization of this foreign society, I find the metaphoric 3D experience to suddenly imply some racially problematic issues.</p>

<p>At first the narrative seems justified, even when the film serves as a dialog between Cameron and science-fiction cinema past, yet it’s the details that imply a false comprehension of “tribal” societies. Jake first comes into contact with a female inhabitant of this society, Neytiri, who introduces him to her world. While she wears minimal clothing made from natural materials and her dialog and gestures suggest a pre-colonized society, when she returns to her village the concept of a “tribal” society really kicks in with the “whoop and holler” that is reminiscent of “Indians” from American westerns in the 1950s. As Jake learns more of this society, it becomes quite apparent these people are a composite of several minority cultures and pre-colonial societies. As the narrative progresses, we find that Jake is able to learn the ways of these people and eventually serves as a leader to resist against the military-corporation from which he came.</p>

<p>This suggests that those unfamiliar with these cultures can possible understand them if they strap into an “avatar” experience (the “body,” in case of the narrative proper, or the 3D glasses/movie screen, in the case of the audience). The suggestion that this can provide a solution for racial or cultural clashes is overly reductive, and in that way very dangerous. What the film does not take into consideration are the subtleties in a culture that cannot be learned through physical repetition, recall of facts, or the physical replication of body. Speaking only as a Comanche native, there is a mindset and there are cultural nuances of belief that are not translatable via conversation, and cannot be learned by those whohave grown up in a Western thought-process.</p>

<p>To suggest that a dialog can occur if cultures simply put on the other’s shoes and all problems can be resolved, is overlooking real differences in thought process. To really understand the world-view of a non-Western peoples one must be born to those people and learn via ways of believing and understanding that do not quantify, analyze, and deconstruct in the similar ways. For example, traditional American Indian thought often does not place so much emphasis on facts and proof in the way Western thought expects in any day-to-day conversation. Assuming the priorities are the same in a conversation, the Westerner might expect a reason for something while the American Indian would think it unnecessary and irrelevant. Neither point of view is better than the other, but without understanding the difference is a result of a basis of belief that influences complex communication will result in a repetition of a question without a common language or reasoning to respond progressively.</p>

<p>Avatar’s simplistic design does not allow for the rendering of these ideas, and implies that any conflict between cultures is resolvable through discussion, or “induction” into a culture, rather than “birth” into a culture. So a sequence in which Jake Sully proficiently performs tasks of the foreign society is merely an external repetition, and when the society accepts him because he does well, the film makes a fatal error. While Jake can learn about what they believe to be sacred, it does not mean he understands the logic behind why the belief works. The film makes the assumption that all logic works under the same Western thought principles without acknowledging the previously mentioned building blocks of a cultural thought process might be different. In the end Jake is able to prove himself physically able to defend these people against his own military-corporation culture, but that is only as far as he is able to integrate. In reality, Jake Sully would simply be a physical simile in this society, where he would continue to struggle with comprehending what is natural to this culture.</p>

<p>In the end, the fact that the film experience renders 3D a means to understand cultural differences that dominant American culture finds incomprehensible is overly simplistic and damaging to real political negotiations. As the film also suggests, for any colonial oppressed culture, it is a Westerner that will resolve all problems and their pains will be heard. The final sub-textual problem implies that any non-Western culture cannot resolve it’s own problems, and that if it simply waits for a Messiah-like figure from Western culture they will be saved. This insults the integrity of any oppressed culture, as the film clenches its final racist tendencies.</p>

<p>While the nature of voyeurism is well discussed, the result of the film’s conclusion remains quite problematic and should not be taken as a basis for true intercultural analysis. The anticipated response from those of a non- Western culture is “what’s the big deal, it’s a film about aliens,” refuses to acknowledge the nature of the film’s exploration as an influence (conscious or not) on future cultural interactions. Whether we are watching aliens in the theater, we will only interact with other real people beyond it, and whether it’s conscious or not, applying what we have learned from this film is negligent. Further, it is dismissive of the true problems of living through an “avatar” body.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Watching Inglourious Basterds in a Room Full of Jews]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/17/watching-inglourious-basterds-in-a-room-full-of-jews/"/>
    <updated>2009-12-17T12:23:51+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/12/17/watching-inglourious-basterds-in-a-room-full-of-jews</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://www.poritsky.com/thecandlerblog/wp-content/uploads/2009/12/inglourious-basterds-may13photo-03.jpg"></p>

<p>Last night, the Jewish Theological Seminary (JTS, the primary higher educational institution of the Conservative Movement) hosted a screening and panel on <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>. (To catch up on how the candler blog feels about the film, you can check Sunrise Tippeconnie’s essay, <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/08/21/once-upon-a-time-in-violence-occupied-cinema-an-analysis-of-inglourious-basterds/">Once Upon a Time in Violence Occupied Cinema</a>, which was written for the film’s theatrical release.) Though an appearance by Quentin Tarantino was promised, the auteur was a no show claiming a sore throat (he gets the benefit of the doubt from me). Luckily, the producer of the film, Lawrence Bender, one of QT’s hebraic guides on the project, was in attendance to discuss the topic of “Jewish Persecution and the Fantasy of Revenge” alongside Dr. Amy Kalmanofsky, a bible and horror film scholar, and Rabbi Jack Moline, a pulpit Rabbi in Virginia whose Kol Nidre sermon about <em>Inglourious Basterds</em> sparked the institution’s interest in hosting such an event. Also, leading the panel was the school’s Chancellor, Arnold M. Eisen. Phew, now you have all the details, so how was it?</p>

<p>This was my third public screening of the film, though the first one on video. I have to say, if you missed this movie on film, you pretty much missed it. But that’s neither here nor there. This was an academic event so I gave some leeway on projected quality, though I will say I’ve seen much worse in other college auditoriums. Unsurprisingly, watching the film in a room full of mostly Jews, mind you months after the film had been unleashed on the masses, was barely different from watching the film in a room full of gentiles. Duh. A great fry cook once said “peoples is peoples”, of course, these are the chosen people watching their greatest enemies slaughtered on screen with great flair. There must be something different.</p>

<p>Well, let’s see, the audience wasn’t quite as “in” on the jokes that a room full of film critics would be in on. There are points in the film at which I was the only one laughing hysterically, usually violent scenes, but again that happened at my other screenings. While there were no great cheers as Hitler’s corpse gets the Swiss cheese treatment, which Mr. Bender says there were at the Israeli premiere, the audience did seem to get a kick out of some of the Nazi-killing gore. “Say aufedersein to your Nazi balls”, for example, got everyone quite excited. Just as I felt at the film’s release, this is an altogether human story, not one of Jewish redemption. But don’t tell the curators of this event, because they brought up some really interesting points about the film in the context of modern (and ancient) Jewish thought.</p>

<p>Dr. Kalmanofsky, no stranger to Judeo-Chrisitian-pop deconstruction, opened the discussion with some fascinating points about the concept of the revenge fantasy, positing that the Jewish bible, specifically the story of the exodus from Egypt, indulges the concept of violent revenge. Besides the ten plagues brought down against their aggressors, arguably deserved, the Israelites break out in song and dance after they cross the parted Sea of Reeds, which closes and drowns the entire Egyptian faction that was chasing them. This punishment goes well beyond the tit-for-tat measures of the plagues, and remorse is not really discussed until the Rabbinic era of Judaism several hundred years after the fact. In other words, while the modern Jew may be morally inquisitive and emotionally conflicted, in the bible, living out the revenge fantasy was something very real.</p>

<p>Rabbi Moline proffered that the Jewish people have become mired in thought for so long that the idea of physical redemption has been lost. The saying “two Jews, three opinions” comes to mind on this point. As the concept of Talmudic discourse has proliferated, especially in the wake of the Holocaust (Why did this happen to us? Is it our fault?), Jews may have lost the instinct of revenge, which Moline points out is in fact a basic human instinct. The film provides that for a generation of Jews who view the holocaust in a new light. <em>Inglorious Basterds</em> represents a voice for that generation.</p>

<p>Producer Lawrence Bender’s input, obviously the most cinematic in this crowd, was quite interesting. After telling a story about Tarantino calling actors by their characters’ names on set which resulted in more than a few awkward moments with Martin Wuttke, the actor who portrays Hitler in the film, he joined in on Rabbi Moline’s generational perspective of the film. Looking to a specific arc from the last twenty years, he mentioned that we go from <em>Schindler’s List</em> to <em>Life Is Beautiful</em> to <em>Inglourious Basterds</em>. Another way to put it is from drama to comedy to fantasy. This is a concept I could write volumes about, but I’ll spare you for now. Another interesting point Mr. Bender brought up is that in both the Israeli and German premieres of the film, the audiences felt a sense of personal redemption. In both cases, the press mentioned that only a non-German/non-Jew could pull off such a film. I’m not sure that there is any validity to this point, however the fact remains that a non-German/non-Jew <em>did</em> make this film.</p>

<p>All in all it was a fascinating evening. Kudos to JTS for putting together such a relevant program. I don’t really believe that there is all that much specifically Jewish about the film, but Rabbi Moline kept harping on the fact that the film has awoken something in the Jewish community. Not a call to arms, but a call to deconstructing the meaning of the inner vengeance of a people. Polemics have always been an important pillar of Rabbinic discourse, but visceral nature is something often pushed to the side in favor of academics. Perhaps, says the Rabbi, it is a time to finally confront that urge we have to murder Hitler, to root out our enemies. Not to indulge it, but to question it.</p>

<p>Hell, if one little film can bring out all that from the leaders of one of the world’s major religions, it must be doing something right. What say you, readers? Fill up the comments with your thoughts on the matter.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[deadCENTER Liveblog, June 13]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/13/deadcenter-liveblog-june-13/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-13T16:00:21+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/13/deadcenter-liveblog-june-13</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>3:58:55 PM</strong>: Settling in at the Kerr Auditorium for Our Spirits Don’t Speak English, narrative doc.<br />
<strong>4:00:11 PM</strong>: Just like the last film I saw in this space, it’s pretty sparsely populated. There are a lot of documentaries this year, I’ve noticed.<br />
<strong>4:03:43 PM</strong>: This film is also getting started a few minutes late. It’ll be tight for me to hit the next program up.<br />
<strong>4:04:05 PM</strong>: Oooookay, only late by 3 minutes. I take of back.<br />
<strong>4:04:48 PM</strong>: More wimgo stella cox!<br />
<strong>4:07:08 PM</strong>: Filmmaker Steven Heape: “dark side of American history that you haven’t been taught.”<br />
<strong>4:08:06 PM</strong>: <a href="http://richheape.com">http://richheape.com</a> for any questions. Check it kids.<br />
<strong>4:08:30 PM</strong>: Shhhhh, time to watch ads.<br />
<strong>5:34:52 PM</strong>: Steven R. Heape is actually the Executive Producer of Our Spirits Don’t Speak English. Sorry about that.<br />
<strong>5:35:32 PM</strong>: Film was very moving and educational. The producer was right, this is. Dark period in our colllective history, as humans.<br />
<strong>5:40:51 PM</strong>: Some inferestig comments are coming in on my Triangle of Death review. <a href="http://bit.ly/yxKRL">http://bit.ly/yxKRL</a><br />
<strong>5:52:03 PM</strong>: After a great deal of back an forth on re matter, I have decided to go to the Comedy Shorts instead of Yveete.<br />
<strong>5:56:31 PM</strong>: I’ve decided to sit in the back of the theater for the comedy shorts so I can look at the back of peoples’ heads.<br />
<strong>6:03:31 PM</strong>: Nice sized crowd for comedy shorts. This space is kinds huge so it is decieving.<br />
<strong>7:37:32 PM</strong>: Some of those shorts were actually pretty funny. Some not so much. Alsost all were crowd pleasers.<br />
<strong>7:38:34 PM</strong>: And now, do I see Barking Water or do I get a bit before a long night ahead of me? I’ll think on that for a few.<br />
<strong>10:11:44 PM</strong>: Awards over, Wavy Gravy movie screening now. Weather Girl Best Narrative Feat. Official Rejection best Doc. Feat. More to come tom.<br />
<strong>10:12:36 PM</strong>: I’m going to sign off for now. I know I didn’t stay true to my word on starting a new thread for awards.<br />
<strong>10:13:17 PM</strong>: I’ll break down awards tomorrow, let you know all about the fest too.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[deadCENTER Liveblog, June 12, Evening]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/12/deadcenter-liveblog-june-12-evening/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-12T20:59:18+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/12/deadcenter-liveblog-june-12-evening</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>8:53:43 PM</strong>: Started a new live post to try to keep the live action fresh. I’m waiting dr Weather Girl screening to start up.  </p>

<p><strong>8:54:27 PM</strong>: I completely forgot to eat. No time to shove a sandwich down my throat before screening. I really need to learn from this tomorrow.  </p>

<p><strong>9:04:24 PM</strong>: Weather Girl is about to start. Nice sized crowd, they’re pretty jazzed. I’ve managed to stay in the exact same venue all day.  </p>

<p><strong>9:04:51 PM</strong>: Gotta love this Wimgo.com commercial AGAIN. I dot even know what this does  </p>

<p><strong>9:05:32 PM</strong>: Good to see I’m not the only only iphone addict while these commercials are up.  </p>

<p><strong>10:43:12 PM</strong>: Weather Girl lights up. Blayne talking onstage.  </p>

<p><strong>11:17:14 PM</strong>: Alright. Finally time for food. Signing off. Check back tomorrow for reviews of today’s viewings. Goodnight candlerers.  </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[deadCENTER Liveblog, June 11]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/11/deadcenter-liveblog-june-11/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-11T18:09:02+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/11/deadcenter-liveblog-june-11</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>6:07:58 PM</strong>: Triangle of Death Screening. Shhhhhh. Thoughts after.  </p>

<p><strong>7:40:38 PM</strong>: Finished Tringle of Death, war doc for the XBOX set. Lots of interviews, fascinating soldier footage. Too many topics covered.  </p>

<p><strong>7:52:23 PM</strong>: While you’re here, read my #deadcenter dispatch about getting here last night. <a href="http://bit.ly/11BNLj">http://bit.ly/11BNLj</a>  </p>

<p><strong>8:39:49 PM</strong>: Next up is the film Pearl. I just heard that the film is sold out. Local narrative feature, people here are pretty jazzed about it.  </p>

<p><strong>8:42:27 PM</strong>: Pearl is the story of Pearl Scott Carter, youngest US Aviator in history. My friend just nabbed one of the last tix.  </p>

<p><strong>8:55:44 PM</strong>: Packed house, sitting right up in the second row. Not too close….just right. Nice screening space. Roll film please!  </p>

<p><strong>8:57:03 PM</strong>: I should give a shout out to Ecstasy of Gold, which I’m missing to see Pearl. Hope to check that one at a later date.  </p>

<p><strong>9:09:50 PM</strong>: Okay, Pearl is starting, radio silence for a bit.  </p>

<p><strong>11:12:00 PM</strong>: Standing ovation for Pearl.  </p>

<p><strong>11:43:58 PM</strong>: Great period piece on video. Built a great set of wonderment. Huge success in front of this crowd.  </p>

<p><strong>12:05:38 AM</strong>: Movie over, party time now. Signing off until tomorrow. Check @poritsky on Twitter if you need me.  </p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
