<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Politics | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/politics/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Against the Rage Machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/24/we-are-a-hair/"/>
    <updated>2014-01-24T16:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/01/24/we-are-a-hair</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://nplusonemag.com/rage-machine">The editors of n+1</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Right and left, tech corporations beg you to say your piece for the sake of content-generation, free publicity, hype, and ad sales. America’s speech is so free, it pays—just not you. Even when we don’t opine, just clicking around, we’re like cilia on the tracheal lining of some gross beast, and our small work of enthusiasm, liking or passing along or reiterating or linking, is like the wriggle of a hair, pushing the story down the throat of the culture, filling its lungs so that it may breathe. We can accept this. We are a hair.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>And later:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The point is that there are microworlds of controversy everywhere—as regionally specific and pervasive as gossip, but bizarrely impersonal—and they torment everyone, and we’re all unhappy, drinking too much iced coffee, hating the haters, meta-hating.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Speaking of meta-hating:</p>

<p><div class="embed-video-container"><iframe src="http://www.youtube.com/embed/GH68bSJXGE8 "></iframe></div></p>

<p>And around we go.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Big Bird Jokes Aside...]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/10/04/pbs/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-04T19:07:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/10/04/pbs</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>I’m sorry, Jim. I’m going to stop the subsidy to PBS. I’m going to stop other things. I like PBS. I love Big Bird. I actually like you too. But I’m not going to—I’m not going to keep on spending money on things to borrow money from China to pay for it.</p><footer><strong>-Mitt Romney</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.npr.org/2012/10/03/162258551/transcript-first-obama-romney-presidential-debate'>October 3, 2012</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Mitt Romney’s PBS rejoinder<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> has quickly become the most talked about soundbite from last night’s Presidential debate. It seems as though everyone has a Big Bird joke or critique to share today, quipping that the avian celebrity has been fired or some other nonsense.</p>

<p>But let’s be serious about this. The PBS volley is a stunning bit of political theater; a calculated and workshopped line designed to do exactly what it has done: spread like wildfire. While the wonks break down his many dubious claims, Mitt Romney has thrown the rest of us some gristle. He fit a pop culture reference into a direct threat against the event’s moderator, Jim Lehrer. LOL!</p>

<p>Beneath the fun,<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> however, there is something very cynical and dangerous brewing. There is nothing funny about cutting subsidies to Public Broadcasting Systems. The comment that spawned a few <a href="http://www.buzzfeed.com/stacylambe/big-bird-responds-to-mitt-romney-on-twitter">comedic Twitter accounts</a> should be seen as a signifier of the stark differences between these two candidates.</p>

<p>I believe in the arts and the media. I believe, with every fiber of my being, that no nation can become or stay great without investing in its most creative citizens. After all, without culture, what are we? <em>Who</em> are we?</p>

<p>So I find it baffling that politicians are constantly willing to put arts and media funding on the chopping block, but I find it more disturbing that we tend to get strong-armed into believing that they’re right. America is hurting, Mitt Romney tells us, therefore we shouldn’t be pouring millions of dollars into a puppet show. And people believe him because, with everything going on in all of our lives right now, they can’t bring themselves to tell him he’s wrong.</p>

<p>I find it highly unlikely that a Mitt Romney administration will actually be able to de-fund PBS or other endeavors that generally live in fear like the National Endowment for the Arts.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup> It’s more likely that this rehearsed “zinger” is a feint intended to keep us abuzz with talk of how slick and collected the Republican contender looked and hope we don’t notice some of his more gross misstatements from the evening. Still, it’s indicative of the kind of cynicism we can look forward to if Romney is elected.</p>

<p>It’s true that the economy is weak. Many of us are out of work or underpaid. Benefits that we once enjoyed have shriveled up. States are barely getting by. There’s growing unrest in the Middle East and we still can’t get out of Afghanistan, troubles we all have to foot the bill for. But I’ll be damned if I let that get it the way of my support for publicly financed television. We have already given up so much; must we give up on Big Bird too?</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>A response to the question, “how you would go about tackling the deficit problem?”<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Another memorable moment came when a grinning Romney said of the longwindedness of the debate process, “It’s fun, isn’t it?”<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>Even Ronald Reagan came around and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1988/05/15/arts/book-discloses-that-reagan-planned-to-kill-national-endowment-for-arts.html">found some value in the National Endowment for the Arts.</a><a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[PROTECT IP Vote Postponed]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/20/pipa-postponed/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-20T10:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/20/pipa-postponed</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>Senate Majority Leader Harry Reid announced today that he is postponing Tuesday’s procedural vote on the Protect IP Act (PIPA), the <a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-57360665-503544/sopa-pipa-what-you-need-to-know/">controversial anti-piracy bill</a> that inspired thousands of websites on Wednesday to go dark.</p><footer><strong>Stephanie Condon</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.cbsnews.com/8301-503544_162-57362675-503544/pipa-vote-postponed-in-the-senate/'>CBS News Political Hotsheet</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Very happy to hear this news, but this is still only the beginning. SOPA and PROTECT IP aren’t going away, they’re just being put off until Hollywood’s lobbyist can find a more convenient time to push this through.</p>

<p>Make sure your Senators and Representatives know <strong>there is no convenient time to break the Internet</strong>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Dodd on the Ropes]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/20/dodd-on-the-ropes/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-20T07:59:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/20/dodd-on-the-ropes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><blockquote><p>“This is altogether a new effect,” Mr. Dodd said, comparing the online movement to the Arab Spring. He could not remember seeing “an effort that was moving with this degree of support change this dramatically” in the last four decades, he added.</p><footer><strong>-Michael Cieply and Edward Wyatt</strong> <cite><a href='http://www.nytimes.com/2012/01/20/technology/dodd-calls-for-hollywood-and-silicon-valley-to-meet.html?_r=1&amp;pagewanted=all'>The New York Times</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>One of the key points of contention I have with a lot of the mainstream coverage of the anti-SOPA/PIPA movement is that many outlets refer to it as the “anti-SOPA lobby” or something like that. What I think is lost on Chris Dodd and his cohorts is that there is no lobby. It’s not the MPAA vs. Google; it’s the interests of a few corporations vs. the voices of the American people. And I think we’ve made it clear where we stand on this issue.</p>

<p>The whole article, which is a great read on a smarmy character, will make you hate politics.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>Under legislation passed in 2007, Mr. Dodd is barred from personally lobbying Congress for two years after leaving office. Hired as the consummate Washington insider to carry the film industry’s banner on crucial issues like piracy, Mr. Dodd ended up being more coach than player. He helped devise a strategy that called for his coalition to line up a strong array of legislative sponsors and supporters behind two similar laws — the Stop Online Piracy Act in the House, and the Protect I.P. Act in the Senate — and then to move them through the Congress quickly before possible opposition from tech companies could coalesce.</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Lobbying is against the rules, yet “everything but” is just fine. The legislation in question, the <a href="http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/PLAW-110publ81/content-detail.html">Honest Leadership and Open Government Act of 2007</a> is clearly useless.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What is the MPAA?]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/19/what-is-the-mpaa/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-19T08:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/01/19/what-is-the-mpaa</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="the-motion-picture-association-of-america-mpaa-is">The Motion Picture Association of America (MPAA) <em>is</em>…</h3>

<ul>
  <li>…a political advocacy group (aka lobbyists).</li>
  <li>…beholden to the needs of its six members:
    <ul>
      <li>Walt Disney Studios Motion Pictures</li>
      <li>Paramount Pictures Corporation</li>
      <li>Sony Pictures Entertainment Inc.</li>
      <li>Twentieth Century Fox Film Corporation</li>
      <li>Universal City Studios LLC</li>
      <li>Warner Bros. Entertainment Inc.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>…a <a href="http://www.mpaa.org/about">self-stated</a> “champion of intellectual property rights, free and fair trade, innovative consumer choices, freedom of expression and the enduring power of movies to enrich and enhance people’s lives.”</li>
  <li>…run by former US Senator Christopher J. Dodd, who took the job on March 17, 2011 two months after leaving office. Under the Honest Leadership and Open Government Act of 2007 (<a href="http://www.gpo.gov/fdsys/pkg/PLAW-110publ81/content-detail.html">Public Law 110-81</a>) Senators must wait two years before lobbying Congress in an official capacity.
    <ul>
      <li>It should also be noted that Dodd repeatedly made clear that he <a href="http://www.ctmirror.org/story/7485/lawmakerlobbyists">would not lobby</a> once he left office.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>…the organization that administers American film ratings.</li>
  <li>…the organization that administered the <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Motion_Picture_Production_Code">Hays Code</a>.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="the-mpaa-is-not">The MPAA <em>is not</em>…</h3>

<ul>
  <li>…a government organization.</li>
  <li>…a labor union.
    <ul>
      <li>Officially it is a trade organization.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>…elected.</li>
  <li>…the voice of the filmmaking community at large.</li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
