<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Productivity | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/productivity/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instapaper Highlighting]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/instapaper-adds-highlighting/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T22:06:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/instapaper-adds-highlighting</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/05/instapaper-highlight.png" title="Instapaper Highlighting in Action" ></p>

<p>You would have no way of knowing this, but I’ve been trying to write more about movies around here. That means <em>reading</em> more about movies too. Which in turn means my usual screwing around with apps and workflows and things…</p>

<p>I’ve been trying to write a piece that involves pulling together the disparate strands of a number of things other folks have written in the past little while. No foolin’: earlier this week I spent an hour or two trying to find a quick and easy way to organize highlights from my Instapaper account. I cobbled together a number of tools and gave up, assuming it was hopeless.</p>

<p>Then today <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/app/instapaper/id288545208?mt=8&amp;at=11l5Fb">Instapaper</a> pushed out a <a href="http://blog.instapaper.com/post/85125160146"><em>huge</em> update</a> to their apps and web backend, including integrating highlighting. What luck!</p>

<p>Highlights do just what they say on the tin and then some. Select text in an article, click highlight, and voila, the text turns into a different color. Highlights also get their own section in Instapaper, allowing you to quickly see all the highlighted text across folders in one view. Plus you can set Instapaper to automatically trigger an action when you highlight text. More on that in a moment.</p>

<p>Before I go any further I should mention a point that has already kicked up some dust in the Instapaper Blog comments. In order to get unlimited highlights across Instapaper, you need to have a subscription. Otherwise, you get 5 free highlights per month.</p>

<p>Instapaper subscriptions have long been a confusing point of contention for some users who think an app that costs money shouldn’t have additional costs. According to <a href="https://www.instapaper.com/faq">Instapaper’s FAQ</a>, for $1 a month (really $3 every 3 months) you get:</p>

<blockquote>
  <ul>
    <li>Full-text search</li>
    <li>Unlimited highlighting</li>
    <li>Third-party API access</li>
    <li>Better Kindle functionality</li>
    <li>Ads removed from website</li>
  </ul>
</blockquote>

<p>That third-party API access is key for me since I <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/31/readkit-2-and-rediscovering-instapaper/">love using ReadKit</a> to organize articles. Honestly, now with highlighting, an Instapaper subscription is a steal at twice the price. But it’s an important point: without a subscription you’ll want to use highlighting sparingly.</p>

<p>Back to highlighting tricks.</p>

<h3 id="highlights-to-evernote">Highlights to Evernote</h3>

<p>Any sharing account you have set up in Instapaper (like <a href="https://twitter.com">Twitter</a>, <a href="https://www.evernote.com/referral/Registration.action?uid=236765&amp;sig=c3f3f41ea30c00be54920d4456371862">Evernote</a> or <a href="https://pinboard.in/">Pinboard</a>) can automatically share out a highlight in the background. So if you’ve set up Evernote to “Post Highlights” every time you highlight text, a new note will be created in your default notebook with the article title as the note title and the highlighted text and url as the note content.</p>

<p>Here’s a tip: save a search in Evernote for <code>author:no-reply@instapaper.com</code>. This will filter out only notes emailed to Evernote from Instapaper, which in my case will only be highlights.</p>

<h3 id="highlights-to-pinboard">Highlights to Pinboard</h3>

<p>Right now I have everything I save to Instapaper going to Pinboard as a sort of firehose backup of all my links. Now that highlighting adds the ability to post to Pinboard, with the highlighted text going into the description field, I’m thinking of changing that setup. This way only articles I have enough of an interest in to highlight some text will make their way to Pinboard. Even better: highlighting text is much, much faster than using Instapaper’s sharing panel to send articles to Pinboard.</p>

<p>I’ve long used Instapaper and Pinboard alongside one another, but that relationship has become fraught over time. Ideally Instapaper is my “hot” storage while Pinboard is my “cold,” or deep, storage. However, more or less the Instapaper links clutter up Pinboard. Highlighting with background sharing, I hope, should help the bring out the best of both services. I’ll give it a go and report back.</p>

<h3 id="other-goodies">Other Goodies</h3>

<p>I also really like that the article view includes a small, conspicuous flag letting you know if an article has highlights and how many it has. In daily use this may not seem important, but when I’m doing deep research on a topic in folders, this could be a huge boon.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2014/05/instapaper-highlight-flag.png" title="Instapaper Highlighting Flag" ></p>

<p>All this gushing about highlighting and I haven’t even mentioned the major redesign of the web app (pictured in screenshots above) with drag and drop organization, plus subtle but important tweaks to the iOS apps. And they’ve even got a brand new logo from Kris Sowersby, the typographer behing my <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/29/dancing-couriers/">preferred monospaced</a> font, <a href="https://klim.co.nz/blog/tag/fonts-in-use/pitch/">Pitch</a>.</p>

<p>Though the rest of these features play second fiddle to highlighting today, I’m interested to see how they change the way I think about Instapaper. For so long it has been an app for <em>reading</em> content. Today’s updates prove that it’s no slouch when it comes to <em>organizing</em> content. Mostly, though, I’m excited to see how ambitious all of these updates are. It’s nice to know there are people working, iterating and making a service and app you love better.</p>

<p>Anyway, I’ve got to get back to marking up all of these articles in Instapaper so I can get back to writing about movies.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[DuckDuckGo Next and an Updated Alfred Workflow]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/duckduckgo-next/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-08T16:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/duckduckgo-next</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in March of 2013 I whipped up a little <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com">Alfred 2</a> workflow for <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/03/18/alfred-duckduckgo-search-with-suggest/">searching DuckDuckGo by way of Google Suggest</a>. In short: you get all the benefits of Google’s auto-completions right from Alfred while using a <a href="https://next.duckduckgo.com/about">search engine</a> that <a href="http://dontbubble.us">doesn’t bubble you</a>.</p>

<p>As noted <a href="http://www.macstories.net/news/the-next-duckduckgo/">by Chris Herbert at MacStories</a>, the folks at DuckDuckGo recently launched <a href="https://next.duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo Next</a>, a beta of a massive overhaul of both the design and functionality of the upstart search engine. I really love the way DDG Next looks and works. They’ve done an amazing job of offering context-specific results without obscuring more general ones.</p>

<p>For example, searching for “chicken recipes” on both DuckDuckGo Next and Google brings up two very different pages.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="http://f.cl.ly/items/122Z2u3k1Y3o3R1V0c45/ddgn-v-big-g-tween.gif" title="DuckDuckGo Next vs. Google" ></p>

<p>In a browser window that was originally 935 x 1013 px, DuckDuckGo offers nine results and a single ad. Four of those nine are to specific recipes, accompanied by a photo and a brief ingredient list. Even better, the recipes up top can scroll horizontally, where a total of thirty-five recipes can be seen without leaving the page. In the same size window, Google returns six ads and six results, two of which are filed under “News for <strong>chicken recipes</strong>.” In this instance, one of these search engines is an order of magnitude more helpful than the other.</p>

<p>The first I heard about DuckDuckGo Next was actually in the comments section of my Alfred workflow. It turns out there are quite a few regular users of the workflow. A few started asking for an update that pointed to DuckDuckGo Next. I whipped one up, <a href="http://cl.ly/VQR0/download/Google%20Auto%20Complete%20to%20DDG%20Next.zip">available for download now</a>.</p>

<p>The workflow still relies on Google Suggest for autocomplete. If and when I can figure out how to switch that over to DuckDuckGo’s new autocomplete I will make the change. Until then, enjoy searching the lovely DuckDuckGo Next from the comfort of Alfred.</p>

<p><a href="http://cl.ly/VQR0/download/Google%20Auto%20Complete%20to%20DDG%20Next.zip">Download <code>Google Auto Complete to DDG Next.zip</code></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OmniFocus 2 Theme for OmniFocus 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/16/omnifocus-2-theme/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-16T14:42:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/16/omnifocus-2-theme</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Jon de la Vega <a href="https://github.com/deadsunrise/Omnifocus-modernize-theme">on his Github project page</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>I like the look of Omnifocus 2 but it’s not ready for everyday use so I decided to make a theme for OF1 with the renewed look.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’ve had access to the OmniFocus 2 “private test” for about a month, but right now it’s not usable on a daily basis (for me, at least). This theme <em>really</em> dresses OF1 up like OF2 in a way that is, surprisingly, nice. If you want to get a feel for where Omni is taking the design but retain the functionality you’re used to, this theme works quite nicely.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Alfred 2 Workflow to Search DuckDuckGo by Way of Google Suggest]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/03/18/alfred-duckduckgo-search-with-suggest/"/>
    <updated>2013-03-18T21:56:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/03/18/alfred-duckduckgo-search-with-suggest</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="http://f.cl.ly/items/0H1A0M2O2h262v142e0Q/Screen%20Shot%202013-03-18%20at%207.48.55%20PM.PNG" title="DuckDuckGo via Google Suggest" ></p>

<p>Here’s a quickie workflow for <a href="http://www.alfredapp.com">Alfred 2</a>. David Ferguson, a nerd who works on Alfred, has been building some excellent extensions for the launcher/so-much-more app. His <a href="http://dferg.us/google-suggest/">Google Suggest workflow</a> caught my eye, only I don’t particularly like using Google for my Web searches anymore. Luckily it’s easy enough to modify workflows in Alfred 2.</p>

<p>Google’s suggestions are a great feature. I use them all the time in Safari<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> even though I’ve set the default search engine for the location bar to <a href="https://duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo</a>. I like DuckDuckGo’s commitment to privacy and the simplicity of their bang (!) searches. If I <em>want</em> to search on Google, I just type my string and add “!g” to do so. But they don’t offer a suggestion feature. That’s where David’s workflow (and my modification) comes in. <del>(Download it here.)</del> <em>See update below.</em></p>

<p>I set the shortcut in Alfred to “s” for “search.” Launch Alfred,<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> type “s” and then the start of a search string. Google suggestions will come up, selecting any of them and hitting Enter will take me to DuckDuckGo results. Selecting a result and hitting tab will put the cursor after the selected phrase, allowing me to add whatever bang I please, like !imdb or !a for Amazon.</p>

<p>I’m happy I got an Alfred Power Pack, which unleashes the power of workflows. I’m excited to see what else this little app can do.</p>

<p><strong>Updated May 8, 2014:</strong> Changed plugin to support the new (and if you ask me, superior) <a href="https://next.duckduckgo.com">DuckDuckGo Next</a>. More info <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2014/05/08/duckduckgo-next/">here</a>.</p>

<p><del><a href="http://poritsky.com/phpatm/index.php?action=downloadfile&amp;filename=Google%20Auto%20Complete%20to%20DDG.zip&amp;directory=&amp;">Download <code>Google Auto Complete to DDG.zip</code></a></del></p>

<p><a href="http://cl.ly/VQR0/download/Google%20Auto%20Complete%20to%20DDG%20Next.zip">Download <code>Google Auto Complete to DDG Next.zip</code></a></p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I really couldn’t tell you if that’s stock behavior or a plugin I installed.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>^+Space for me.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Pinboard to OmniFocus via Mail Drop]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/10/pinboard-to-omnifocus/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-10T14:08:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/10/pinboard-to-omnifocus</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2012/12/pb-to-of.png" title="Pinboard to OmniFocus via Mail Drop" ></p>

<p>This morning I got a happy little email informing me that my <a href="https://manage.sync.omnigroup.com">Omni Sync Server</a> account now has an access to the <a href="http://forums.omnigroup.com/showpost.php?p=118013&amp;postcount=1">Mail Drop beta</a>. David Sparks gave a <a href="http://macsparky.com/blog/2012/12/the-omnifocus-mail-drop-1">nice intro</a> to it over the weekend.</p>

<p>In short: you send an email to your Mail Drop address and poof, it’s in your OmniFocus inbox. The company has offered a “Send to OmniFocus” service for a some time now, but it required you to receive an email back from a server and tap a link to move into OmniFocus on your iOS device. Now it all happens on the server; send once and done.</p>

<p>I decided to revisit an old failed experiment of mine today: sending <a href="https://pinboard.in/">Pinboard</a> bookmarks to OmniFocus by way of <a href="https://ifttt.com/">IFTTT</a>. With The Omni Group taking care of the heavy lifting now (as opposed to me keeping my Mac at home sucking in emails) it seems to be a more viable workflow.</p>

<p>You can start using my IFTTT recipe <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/69609">by going here</a>. Once you set it up with your super-secret Mail Drop address, any public bookmark you tag “toof”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> (or whatever you choose) will get moved over to your OmniFocus inbox. In my experience the IFTTT recipes trigger about every 15 minutes, and so far OmniSync’s Mail Drop has been seemingly instantaneous.</p>

<p>Now <em>why</em> would you want to use this?</p>

<p>It’s true that there are already a number of ways to get things into OmniFocus even on an iOS device. Alex Popescu’s <a href="http://jots.mypopescu.com/post/9353259803/a-generalized-omnifocus-bookmarklet-with-support-for">bookmarklet</a> does an excellent job of flipping you from Safari to OF on any platform, for example. <a href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/08/24/mr-reader-update/">Mr. Reader</a>, my iPad RSS reader of choice, has great OmniFocus integration. The thing about those implementations is that they all require me to stop what I’m doing and open up OmniFocus.</p>

<p>Generally, I send URLs to OmniFocus that I either want to read later<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> or write up here on the candler blog. With this recipe I can go about my RSS reading, find a cool article, send it to Pinboard with my incredibly clever “toof” tag and continue reading. Better still, I can now send the item to <em>both</em> Pinboard (my cold storage) and OmniFocus (my hot plate).</p>

<p>If you use OmniFocus on more than one platform, I highly recommend the free <a href="https://manage.sync.omnigroup.com">Omni Sync Server</a> service; I would have even before the addition of Mail Drop. Once you’ve got Mail Drop up and running, you can give the <a href="https://ifttt.com/recipes/69609">Pinboard to OmniFocus via Mail Drop</a> IFTTT recipe a try. Happy pinning.</p>

<p><strong>Note:</strong> I used IFTTT’s Gmail channel because their stock Email channel adds a bit of branding to the email. It’s not terribly annoying, but it will end up in your OmniFocus note as text. If you don’t use Gmail just whip up a similar recipe using the Email channel. </p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>As in “to OmniFocus,” not “Ow, I have a toofache.”<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>Sometimes sending to Pinboard or Instapaper isn’t enough of a reminder.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
