<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Photography | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/photography/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[“…armed with two cameras and a cigarette.”]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/09/two-cameras-and-a-cigarette/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-09T18:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/12/09/two-cameras-and-a-cigarette</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>To say nothing of the fur coat. Great pic over at <a href="http://livelymorgue.tumblr.com/post/69487212433/a-nov-28-1973-article-described-a-40-percent">The Lively Morgue</a>.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[The Leica M9, as a pro-hobbyist photographer]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/28/marcos-leica-experiment/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-28T23:23:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/28/marcos-leica-experiment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.marco.org/2012/12/28/leica-m9">Marco Arment</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The Leica M9 is disappointing, especially for $6,500, and clearly not a good fit for our purposes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Once upon a time I had access to some amazing camera gear including a <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leica_M8">Leica M8</a>, the company’s first digital camera. I was so mystified by its abilities I plunked down money for my very own <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Leica_CL">Leica CL</a>, a camera I sold with all of my other film gear a few years back.</p>

<p>I hope Marco gives the rangefinder system another try sometime. It’s a bitch to get the hang of and absolutely terrible for capturing fleeting moments, especially of a child. However, once you get the hang of it, you start seeing photos without holding the camera up to your eye. The whole world becomes a set of images waiting to be captured.</p>

<p>With an SLR I always feel like I’m exiting the moment to hide behind my camera; with my Leica I could see the framelines in the world around me, and in turn find the right moments to capture as they unfolded. This, I imagine, is why rangefinders are a staple of street and war photography.</p>

<p>But they’re tough as hell for capturing fast-moving kids.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instagram Backs Down, Or Speaks in Round Terms to Make You Think it Has]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/20/obfuscatstagram/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-20T22:36:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/20/obfuscatstagram</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Kevin Systrom of Instagram infamy, <a href="http://blog.instagram.com/post/38421250999/updated-terms-of-service-based-on-your-feedback">again</a> (emphasis his, actually):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p><strong>Because of the feedback we have heard from you, we are reverting this advertising section to the original version that has been in effect since we launched the service in October 2010.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yayhooray! No ads! Unless…</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Going forward, rather than obtain permission from you to introduce possible advertising products we have not yet developed, we are going to take the time to complete our plans, and then come back to our users and explain how we would like for our advertising business to work.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Whoa whoa whoa. I had to read that sentencegraph a few times over because at first blush it’s too grammatically hilarious to tell whether or not it’s patronizing. Turns out it is.</p>

<p>Let’s start with Systrom’s fantasy that Instagram tried to “obtain permission” from us to introduce “possible advertising products.” In my mind, asking permission usually constitutes asking someone for permission to do something, not slipping out a legal document one afternoon that millions would passively agree to if no one had, you know, read it. And that possible advertising product sounded pretty damn actual on paper.</p>

<p>So then: rather than doing something Instagram didn’t actually do, what does Systrom propose? Why, they’re going to take time to work on their “plans” and then explain it to the users when they’re ready. Here’s the thing, Kevin, <em>you already did that</em> and everyone hated it.</p>

<p>My Instagram account is still up but I’ll be deleting it once I know all my pictures and metadata are in order after the holidays.</p>

<p>I just <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/poritsky/">renewed my Flickr Pro account</a> and I have to say there isn’t much I miss about Instagram, not even the people as it seems my small photographic network has made the jump as well. And, you know, I pay them so they don’t clutter up my feed with ads. Win-win, it seems.</p>

<p>Systrom and Instagram (and social overlord Facebook) are on damage control this week, but make no mistake about this latest blog post: there is nothing that will stop Instagram from becoming the cluttered ad network users roared over this week. They’ve got investors’ mouths to feed, after all. I say get out now, while you still can.</p>

<p>By the way: here I am being a pro back in 2007. I honestly didn’t think I’d be back on Flickr in 2012, but here we are.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/poritsky/2368684808/" title="T-Shirt Shopping, Self-Portrait by poritsky, on Flickr"><img src="http://farm4.staticflickr.com/3088/2368684808_ea22d2c4e1_z.jpg" width="640" height="426" alt="T-Shirt Shopping, Self-Portrait" /></a></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Out While I Can]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/18/instagone/"/>
    <updated>2012-12-18T15:31:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/12/18/instagone</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="center" src="/images/2012/12/instagram.jpg" title="Instagram" ></p>

<p>Instagram’s <a href="http://instagram.com/about/legal/terms/updated/">new Terms of Use</a> went live yesterday (they take effect January 16th) and, well, everyone is up in arms. Nilay Patel has a great piece over at The Verge<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> on what the terms <a href="http://www.theverge.com/2012/12/18/3780158/instagrams-new-terms-of-service-what-they-really-mean">do and don’t mean</a>.</p>

<p>Though everyone’s talking about the paragraph on how they plan to use users’ photos to generate ad revenue, I’m more interested in the lines that precede it. Let me break it up (emphasis mine):</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Instagram does not claim ownership of any Content that you post on or through the Service.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hooray!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Instead…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Instead?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Instead, you hereby grant to Instagram a non-exclusive, fully paid and royalty-free, transferable, sub-licensable, worldwide <strong>license to use the Content that you post on or through the Service, except that you can control who can view certain of your Content</strong> and activities on the Service as described in the Service’s Privacy Policy, available here: <a href="http://instagram.com/legal/privacy/">http://instagram.com/legal/privacy/</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>All that worldwide, sub-licensable, royalty-free mumbo-jumbo is pretty common.<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" rel="footnote">2</a></sup> It means that you give the company license to use your work on their service.</p>

<p>What <em>is</em> weird about Instagram’s terms, though, is that it doesn’t make clear what the limits of this license are as some other companies do.</p>

<p>Here are <a href="http://www.apple.com/legal/icloud/en/terms.html">Apple’s iCloud Terms of Service</a>, which includes use of Photo Stream:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Except for material we may license to you, Apple does not claim ownership of the materials and/or Content you submit or make available on the Service.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hooray again?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>However…</p>
</blockquote>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/N5nD7PDQXWY?t=47s">Whatever</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>However, by submitting or posting such Content on areas of the Service that are accessible by the public or other users with whom you consent to share such Content, you grant Apple a worldwide, royalty-free, non-exclusive license to use, distribute, reproduce, modify, adapt, publish, translate, publicly perform and <strong>publicly display such Content on the Service solely for the purpose for which such Content was submitted or made available</strong>, without any compensation or obligation to you.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>By my armchair reading, this stipulation gives users a bit of a cudgel should Apple suddenly decide it wants to get (deeper) into the ad business. Apple only has the right to do with your photos whatever you ask it to.</p>

<p>Yahoo!, which owns Flickr, <a href="http://info.yahoo.com/legal/us/yahoo/utos/utos-173.html">takes a similar tone</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>With respect to photos, graphics, audio or video you submit or make available for inclusion on publicly accessible areas of the Yahoo! Services other than Yahoo! Groups, the license to use, distribute, reproduce, modify, adapt, publicly perform and publicly display <strong>such Content on the Yahoo! Services solely for the purpose for which such Content was submitted or made available.</strong></p>
</blockquote>

<p>Plus Flickr makes it simple for you to <a href="http://www.flickr.com/help/photos/#87">set a license on your photos</a>.</p>

<p>Google, whose <a href="https://picasaweb.google.com">Picasa</a> is basically a Google+ front-end nowadays, injects <a href="http://www.google.com/intl/en/policies/terms/">plain english into their terms</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>You retain ownership of any intellectual property rights that you hold in that content. In short, what belongs to you stays yours.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Then the same ol’ royalty-free gobbledygook for a few lines before this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This license continues even if you stop using our Services (for example, for a business listing you have added to Google Maps).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>When you’re a jet, <a href="http://youtu.be/exGJsv6ZNlo?t=20s">you’re a jet all the way</a>.<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" rel="footnote">3</a></sup></p>

<p>By contrast Apple and Yahoo! explicitly state the license is terminated once you remove your photos from the service. Instagram? It’s less clear to me:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If we terminate your access to the Service or you use the form detailed above to deactivate your account, your photos, comments, likes, friendships, and all other data will no longer be accessible through your account (e.g., users will not be able to navigate to your username and view your photos), <strong>but those materials and data may persist and appear within the Service</strong> (e.g., if your Content has been reshared by others).</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Followed immediately by:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Upon termination, all licenses and other rights granted to you in these Terms of Use will immediately cease.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Licenses granted <em>to you</em>. I’m no lawyer, but it sounds like that license you granted <em>to Instagram</em> stays put even after you delete your account.</p>

<p>That is, unless you delete your account before January 16, 2013. That’s exactly what I plan to do once I get all of my photos off of the service. I’ve already downloaded my photos through <a href="http://instaport.me/">Instaport</a>,<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" rel="footnote">4</a></sup> but that service doesn’t pull down your caption or metadata. I don’t know if Instagram’s API even allows for full metadata extraction, but I’m on the prowl for a tool that gives me a more complete version of my files.</p>

<p>I don’t begrudge Instagram their efforts to monetize their service, nor Facebook’s attempt to get a bit of money back on their billion dollar investment.<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" rel="footnote">5</a></sup> That doesn’t mean I need to be a part of it though.</p>

<p>And so I’m moving to Flickr. Their new <a href="http://www.flickr.com/iphone">iOS app</a> is slick and has renewed interest in the social photo-sharing service. I’ve been an on-again-off-again Pro user for years. Soon I’ll start tinkering again on what was once one of my favorite online communities. Perhaps it will be again.</p>

<p>I don’t know what Instagram under the new terms will be like. Maybe I’m being irrational, but I don’t think so. The truth is I don’t want to have to worry about whether my photos will be used to sell products. That is unless I’m getting a cut.</p>

<p>So if you want to check out my pics, <a href="http://www.flickr.com/photos/poritsky">I’ll be over on Flickr</a>, snapping away. </p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>I <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2012/09/07/done-with-the-verge/">know</a>, I <a href="http://candlerblog.com/2012/09/10/topolsky/">know</a>. No one beats Nilay when it comes to step-off-the-ledge legalese parsing, though.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p>If you’ve ever been in a television audience, they make you sign a waiver granting the producers permission to broadcast your likeness anywhere in the universe. At least if you move to Mars you can wriggle free of these cloud licenses.<a href="#fnref:2" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p>This, by the way, is why I don’t use Google Docs anymore.<a href="#fnref:3" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p>They’re receiving unusually heavy traffic right now so be patient.<a href="#fnref:4" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p>Okay, <a href="http://dealbook.nytimes.com/2012/08/20/how-instagram-could-have-cut-a-better-deal/">$735 million</a>. Who’s counting?<a href="#fnref:5" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Three Photographers Recall a 1996 Fall]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/02/falling-dole/"/>
    <updated>2012-11-02T10:30:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2012/11/02/falling-dole</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>John Leland <a href="http://lens.blogs.nytimes.com/2012/11/02/catch-the-shot-or-the-candidate/">recounts a 1996 tumble</a> by Bob Dole from the perspective of the photographers who witnessed it:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>One caught the candidate, saving him from possible injury, while another caught the brunt of the falling banister, fracturing several bones in his foot. And one got the shot that captured the <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/11/08/us/how-bob-dole-s-dream-was-dashed.html">essence of a campaign</a> that was starting to fall flat for a 73-year-old candidate whose age was already turning into a <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/1996/07/21/weekinreview/his-hipness-bob-dole-s-done-there-been-that.html">campaign issue</a>.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Great story. And there’s also this:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>It was the first year that campaign photographers used digital cameras, which meant they could transmit pictures to the East Coast in time for the next day’s newspaper.</p>

  <p>“If I’d been shooting film, those pictures would’ve been 12 hours later, and maybe never seen the light of day,” Mr. Wilking said.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Amazing.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
