<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Deadcenter | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/deadcenter/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Ready for deadCENTER]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/04/getting-ready-for-deadcenter/"/>
    <updated>2009-06-04T15:02:35+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2009/06/04/getting-ready-for-deadcenter</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>[caption id=”attachment_777” align=”alignright” width=”241” caption=”Still
from Saint Misbehavin’: The Wavy Gravy Movie”]<img src="http://www.candlerblog.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/06
/wavygravy-1024x823.jpg" alt="Still from Saint Misbehavin':
The Wavy Gravy Movie" />[/caption]</p>

<p>Alright candler readers, get ready to tune in next week for coverage from the
9th Annual deadCENTER Film Festival. I’m pretty excited to head out to
Oklahoma City for the fest. I’ll be doing my darndest to keep the site up to
date daily, so you’d better check back. I’m also working out the kinks in a
liveblogging system so you may even be able to see what I’m thinking
instantaneously. Sound exciting? You bet your ass it is. 6 days and counting.
Here are some highlights from the official press release, but there will be
much much more to come. For more info hit up
<a href="http://www.deadcenterfilm.org">http://www.deadcenterfilm.org</a></p>

<blockquote>

</blockquote>

<p>Notable works juried in this year include <strong>Official Rejection</strong>, a
documentary that walks us through the painful submission - and rejection -
process inherent in independent film. There will be a public panel on this
very topic, led by visiting filmmakers and distinguished film critics. There
will be a free screening of <strong>Saint Misbehavin’: The Wavy Gravy Movie</strong>, shown
for a hippie-infused outdoor audience. Filmmaker-of-note Chopper Burnet brings
<strong>The Twenty</strong> to deadCENTER. Chopper is the voice of NBC – literally. He’s
the voice that you hear on NBC’s national promos. The stars will shine at
<strong>Weather Girl</strong>, which is a hilarious and star-studded feature. And our Okie-
made documentary <strong>Sweethearts of the Prison Rodeo</strong> is sure to draw an
enthusiastic hometown crowd.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
