<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: SXSW 2015 | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/sxsw-2015/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Extra Thoughts on Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-25T15:28:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/25/steve-jobs-sxsw</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote a piece about Alex Gibney’s latest documentary, <em>Steve Jobs: The Man in the Machine</em>, <a href="http://magazine.good.is/articles/the-rotten-side-of-apples-founder">for GOOD Magazine</a>.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The film is by no means a comprehensive portrait of Jobs, though it features a number of interesting new interviews with those close to him, like the aforementioned [Chrisann] Brennan, iPod chief Jon Rubinstein, and Macintosh engineering head Bob Belleville. […] Mostly though, it seems Gibney set out to make a negative portrait of Jobs, and he succeeds.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Audiences who know little about Jobs are certainly in for a shock. I heard plenty of gasps among the SXSW audience I watched the film with.</p>

<p>While I believe Gibney made this film to better understand his relationship with the technology that has conquered the world, I think he’s a bit cagey in his narration about how deliberately unsavory his portrayal of Jobs is. This is not a flat out biography. I’m not sure I’d call it a hit piece either, but it comes very close.</p>

<p>That said: it’s all true. Jobs had a very dark side that was never quite hidden, but surely overshadowed by his incredible successes.</p>

<p>I’m not sure why now, but the legacy of Jobs seems to be coming more to the fore this year. Besides <em>Man in the Machine</em>, which has been picked up by Magnolia Pictures and will probably see a release sometime this year, just this week we saw the release of Brent Schlender and Rick Tetzeli’s <a href="https://itunes.apple.com/us/book/becoming-steve-jobs/id936502684?mt=11&amp;at=11l5Fb"><em>Becoming Steve Jobs: The Evolution of a Reckless Upstart into a Visionary Leader</em></a>.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" rel="footnote">1</a></sup> That latest unauthorized biography of Jobs has been met with praise so far by the Mac blogging community and even Apple itself.</p>

<p>I haven’t read it yet, so I can’t speak to whether it looks at Jobs through rose-colored glasses (whereas Gibney’s glasses would be more ashen) or if it truly is a comprehensive investigation into Jobs’s life. If I had to guess, <em>Man in the Machine</em> will fade, just as the scandals rehashed in it have done over the years.</p>

<div class="footnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p>That’s an iBooks affiliate link. If Amazon is more your bag, <a href="http://www.amazon.com/Becoming-Steve-Jobs-Evolution-Visionary/dp/0385347405?tag=thecandlerblo-20">here you go</a>. I thank you in advance.<a href="#fnref:1" rel="reference">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Jason Schwartzman's On-Screen Schmuckery in 7 Chinese Brothers]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/19/7-chinese-brothers/"/>
    <updated>2015-03-19T15:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/03/19/7-chinese-brothers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Me, <a href="http://heebmagazine.com/chosen-film-jason-schwartzmans-on-screen-schmuckery-in-7-chinese-brothers/54447">for Heeb Magazine</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>This year, at SXSW, we have the <a href="http://schedule.sxsw.com/2015/events/event_FS18118">premiere</a> of Bob Byington’s <a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt3488184/?ref_=ttfc_fc_tt"><em>7 Chinese Brothers</em></a>, a film that showcases the lighter side of [Jason] Schwartzman’s on-screen schmuckery. He plays Larry, a fuck-up to be sure, but a fuck-up you can cheer for.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I enjoyed this one. If you’re a Schwartzman fan, <em>7 Chinese Brothers</em> should head to the top of your list.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
