<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Sports | the candler blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/blog/categories/sports/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-20T19:14:52+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jonathan Poritsky]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baseball, 2015]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/03/baseball-2015/"/>
    <updated>2015-04-03T16:48:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2015/04/03/baseball-2015</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2015/04/05/sports/baseball/baseball-2015-preview-in-a-pitching-rich-era-baseball-ponders-legal-ways-to-boost-offense.html">For <em>The New York Times</em></a>, Tyler Kepner on the state of baseball in 2015:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>The areas of emphasis are changing, but teams, of course, will always seek ways to gain an edge. Players will, too, but the drug culture that once led to an offensive boom is mostly gone. Thousands of runs and homers have gone with it, but baseball — for now — can live with that.</p>

  <p>“You have to get rid of performance-enhancing drugs, because they are a threat to the integrity of the game,” [league commissioner Rob] Manfred said. “And whatever the game looks like with players playing clean is what the game looks like.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Strikeouts are up and homers are down. The game is evolving, but I say: good for the game. I grew up in the PED-fueled home run era. It was fun to watch, but now I look back on those years ashamed of what the game became. Baseball needs to move forward and if it’s a more defensive game, so be it.</p>

<p>Man, I’m so happy it’s Spring. Go, Phillies.</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/2015/04/phanatic-smaller.gif" width="700" title="Phanatic Dancing" ></p>

<p>Oh and <a href="http://m.phillies.mlb.com/news/article/116062924/ryne-sandberg-discusses-phillies-spring-struggles-praises-ryan-howard">speaking of my Phils</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>They lost Thursday afternoon to the Rays at Bright House Field, 10-1, to finish 1-7-1 in their last nine games. They were outscored 72-27 in that stretch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Oof. Whatever. Go team.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Baseball’s First Pitch Loses Its Exclusivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/29/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity/"/>
    <updated>2013-05-29T14:57:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/05/29/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Andrew Keh <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/05/29/sports/baseball/baseballs-first-pitch-loses-its-exclusivity.html">for the New York Times</a>:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>In a sport that clings to its traditions — from managers wearing uniforms to the playing of “Take Me Out to the Ball Game” during the seventh-inning stretch — one time-honored feature at the ballpark has taken an absurd turn, at least for the game’s purists: the ceremonial first pitch.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I’m torn. The first pitch <em>is</em> a time-honored tradition that is being sullied by corporate sponsorship. On the other hand, the Phillie Phanatic’s <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aW-ljrm7a6g">Hatfield hot dog launcher</a> holds a special place in my heart and has nothing to do with the game either.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[As ESPN Debated, Te’o Story Slipped Away]]></title>
    <link href="http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/23/espn-vs-deadspin/"/>
    <updated>2013-01-23T09:32:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://www.candlerblog.com/2013/01/23/espn-vs-deadspin</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Richard Sandomir and James Andrew Miller <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/2013/01/23/sports/ncaafootball/as-debate-raged-at-espn-manti-teo-story-slipped-from-its-hands.html">reporting for the <em>New York Times</em></a> on how Deadspin beat ESPN to the Manti Te’o story:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Some inside the network argued that its reporters — who had initially been put onto the story by Tom Condon, Te’o’s agent — had enough material to justify publishing an article. Others were less sure and pushed to get an interview with Te’o, something that might happen as soon as the next day. For them, it was a question of journalistic standards. They did not want to be wrong.</p>

  <p>“We were very close,” said Vince Doria, ESPN’s chief for news. “We wanted to be very careful.”</p>

  <p>ESPN held the story, and then lost it.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Hindsight is 20/20. They wanted an exclusive interview to break the news, so they waited. And they blew it.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
